DEV-MUC3-1240 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [MODERATOR] ROLANDO GONZALEZ, LOS ANGELES TIMES.

[GONZALEZ] MR. PRESIDENT, I WANT TO MAKE A QUESTION THAT WAS MADE IN SPANISH BEFORE AND IT'S RELATED ABOUT COLONEL OCHOA PEREZ. HE HAS BEEN A HARD-LINE MILITARY AND DON'T YOU THINK THAT HIS [WORDS INDISTINCT] GOT TO BE POSSIBLE? THIS IS ONE AND I GOT A SECOND ONE. CAN YOU TELL US IN ENGLISH WHAT'S GOING TO BE THE RELATION WITH THE NEW NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT AND WHAT DO YOU KNOW ABOUT RECENT MACHINEGUN TRAFFIC OF THE GUERRILLAS?

[CRISTIANI] WELL, WITH THE FIRST CASE MY OPINION IS THAT ANYBODY THAT HAS ANY INFORMATION WITH RESPECT TO THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS SHOULD -- INSTEAD OF SPECULATE WITH IT PUBLICLY -- SHOULD GO STRAIGHT TO THE COURT THAT IS IN CHARGE OF THE CASE AND GIVE ALL THE INFORMATION AVAILABLE TO HIM OR THAT HE IS KNOWLEDGEABLE OF, AND THEN HAVE THE JUDGE DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT.

I THINK THAT MERE SPECULATION IN PUBLIC IS SOMETHING THAT IS NOT GOOD FOR THE JUDICIAL PROCESS BECAUSE IT CREATES PROBLEMS FOR IT. SECONDLY, EVEN THOUGH HE WAS A HIGH-RANKING OFFICER, IN CASES LIKE THIS, IT IS NOT NECESSARILY THE OPINION OF A SPECIFIC MEMBER OF THE ARMED FORCES IS ONE WHICH IS TOTALLY TRUE OR TOTALLY FALSE [SENTENCE AS HEARD]. YOU CANNOT SIMPLY GO BY THAT AS A WAY TO SIMPLY STATE THAT HIS STATEMENTS ARE TRUE.

IT IS VERY INTERESTING TO SEE THAT WHEREAS BEFORE NO ONE REALLY WOULD BELIEVE COL. OCHOA, ALL OF A SUDDEN EVERYONE WANTS TO GIVE HIM ALL THE CREDIBILITY IN THIS CASE. I AM NOT SAYING THAT WHAT HE SAID IS TRUE OR UNTRUE. MY POINT IS THAT IT SHOULD NOT BE DEBATED PUBLICLY; THAT ANYBODY -- COL. OCHOA, MEMBERS OF THE JESUIT COMMUNITY, OR ANYBODY ELSE -- WHO HAS ANY INFORMATION WITH RESPECT TO THE TRIAL SHOULD GO TO THE JUDGE AND GIVE HIM THAT INFORMATION BECAUSE THAT WOULD BE HELPING THE PROCESS AND NOT MERE SPECULATIONS IN PUBLIC.

WITH RESPECT TO THE RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA, WE DISCUSSED THIS WITH ONE OF THE ADVISERS OF MRS. CHAMORRO DURING OUR VISIT AND WE DECIDED TO INITIATE [32-SECOND BREAK IN TRANSMISSION] PLANS AND, THEREFORE, WE ARE WILLING TO REINITIATE THE PROCESS. HER ADVISER WAS VERY CLEAR TO STATE THAT THEY WILL BY NO MEANS AID THE FMLN IN THAT RESPECT.

WE THINK THAT WHAT HAS BEEN HAPPENING BETWEEN THE 25TH OF FEBRUARY AND THE 25TH OF APRIL IS THAT THE FMLN THOUGHT THAT IT WAS TIME TO GET ALL THAT WAS LEFT IN NICARAGUA....[CORRECTS HIMSELF) OUT OF NICARAGUA BECAUSE THEY KNEW OF THE PROBLEMS THEY WOULD FACE WITH THE NEW GOVERNMENT, AND THAT THEY COULD NO LONGER GO ABOUT FREELY IN NICARAGUA WITH THEIR WEAPONS AND THEIR LOGISTIC SUPPORT. THEREFORE, THEY HAVE BEEN TRYING TO BRING THEM IN. IN THAT CASE THERE WAS A GROUP OF FMLN MEMBERS WHO WERE DETAINED IN HONDURAS WITH THE HELP OF THE HONDURAN AUTHORITIES, AND IT WAS OBVIOUS THAT THEY HAD BEEN SHIPPING WEAPONS BY LAND THROUGH HONDURAN TERRITORY, BUT THAT GROUP WAS DETAINED.

[MODERATOR, IN SPANISH] THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT; THANK YOU, MR. FOREIGN MINISTER. JOURNALISTS, THANK YOU.

DEV-MUC3-1241 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [GOVERNMENT MINISTER HORACIO SERPA URIBE] [TEXT] GOOD EVENING. WE COLOMBIANS HAD NOT GOTTEN OVER YESTERDAY'S CRUEL ATTACK IN MEDELLIN WHEN WE WERE CONFRONTED WITH ANOTHER DISGRACE THAT TOOK THE LIFE OF PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE CARLOS PIZARRO. IN A MESSAGE FROM THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC, THE GOVERNMENT VOICED ITS DEEP ANGER AND SADNESS OVER THIS CRIMINAL ATTACK AND IT RATIFIED ITS DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE TO STRUGGLE WITHOUT DISMAY AGAINST ALL FORMS OF CRIMES AND THE CRIMINALS WHO ARE SO INFAMOUSLY ATTACKING PEACE AND DEMOCRACY.

THIS IS NO TIME TO ABANDON ANY ATTITUDE THAT IS DEEMED ADVISABLE FOR THE NATION. IN THE FACE OF THE FRATRICIDAL AND ANTI-PATRIOTIC VIOLENCE, WE MUST ANSWER WITH ACTIONS OF UNDERSTANDING AND CONCILIATION, WITH DECISIONS THAT WILL DISMANTLE THE BANDS OF CRIMINALS WHO ARE DOING SUCH SERIOUS HARM TO THE PEOPLE AND WITH THE DETERMINATION THAT WILL RENEW FAITH IN DEMOCRATIC PRINCIPLES AND IN THE PURPOSE TO ACHIEVE THE BEST LEVELS OF COEXISTENCE. THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO DO THAT.

HOWEVER, THIS RESPONSIBILITY LIES WITH ALL COLOMBIANS OF GOODWILL. FROM EACH OF OUR FELLOW COUNTRYMEN, WE DEMAND POSITIVE ACTIONS AND A GREAT SOLIDARITY WITH THOSE WHO HAVE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF SAFEGUARDING THE CITIZENS' SECURITY THROUGHOUT THE NATION. THE PEACE, UNDERSTANDING, AND CONCILIATION TO WHICH CARLOS PIZARRO WAS COMMITTED SHOULD CONTINUE TO BE THE BASIC GOALS OF THE COUNTRY AND OF ITS CITIZENS.

ALL THE NECESSARY MEASURES THAT WILL LEAD TO CLARIFYING THAT TREACHEROUS CRIME ARE BEING TAKEN TO DETERMINE WHO IS RESPONSIBLE AND THEN PUNISH THEM. TO THIS EFFECT, THE GOVERNMENT'S ACTION WILL BE VERY SEVERE, AND THE INVESTIGATING AUTHORITIES ARE ALREADY BEING PROVIDED VERY AMPLE COOPERATION.

THE GOVERNMENT MAINTAINS DIRECT COMMUNICATIONS WITH THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT [M-19] LEADERS, AND IT HAS BEEN ATTENTIVE TO ITS DEMANDS, CHARGES, AND CONCERNS. THERE IS A MARKED INTEREST BECAUSE THERE CONTINUES TO BE DIRECT RELATIONS WITH ALL POLITICAL PARTIES, THE VARIOUS POLITICAL AND SOCIAL ASSOCIATIONS, AND THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES CONCERNING THE IMPLEMENTATION AND EFFECTIVENESS OF SECURITY AND INDISPENSABLE GUARANTEES SO THAT WE WILL HOLD THE ELECTIONS ON 27 MAY, AS THE PEOPLE WANT.

NATIONAL COEXISTENCE, TOGETHER WITH THE CITIZENS' DEMANDS FOR REFORMS, WILL CONTINUE TO BE A BASIC GOAL OF THE GOVERNMENT OF DR. VIRGILIO BARCO, WHO WILL TOMORROW ADDRESS THE COLOMBIANS. M-19 HAS ASKED THE GOVERNMENT TO ALLOW IT TO MAKE PUBLIC ITS FEELINGS AND OPINIONS IN THE FACE OF THIS GREAT TRAGEDY.

THROUGH ME, AND ACCORDING TO THE PROVISIONS OF LAW 42 OF 1985, THE GOVERNMENT HAS REQUESTED THIS AIR TIME SO THAT ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF, SPOKESMAN OF THE POLITICAL PARTY WHOSE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE WAS BRUTALLY MURDERED TODAY, WILL BE ABLE TO FREELY EXPRESS HIS IDEAS.

THOSE WHO SEEK TO EXCLUDE FROM THE ELECTORAL PROCESS A POLITICAL PARTY -- REGARDLESS OF WHICH ONE IT MAY BE -- WILL NOT ACHIEVE IT, BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT WILL GUARANTEE THAT ITS VOICE WILL CONTINUE TO BE HEARD. DESPITE OF THE DIFFICULTIES, COLOMBIAN DEMOCRACY WILL WIN.

DEV-MUC3-1242 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 24 APR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE LEFTIST PATRIOTIC UNION (UP) TODAY ASKED COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO TO BE ADMITTED TO THE NEGOTIATIONS THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS HOLDING WITH DIVERSE POLITICAL GROUPS TO REACH AN AGREEMENT THAT WILL PERMIT THE INTRODUCTION OF NATIONAL CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS.

THE UP NATIONAL DIRECTORATE MET TODAY WITH BARCO AND GAVE HIM A LETTER NOTING THAT THE EXCLUSION OF SOCIAL FORCES IN THE NEGOTIATIONS MAY AGAIN BE A MOCKERY OF THE PEOPLE. IT AGAIN ASKED FOR PROTECTION FOR THE LIVES OF ITS MILITANTS.

SINCE IT WAS FOUNDED IN 1985, MORE THAN 1,000 UP MEMBERS HAVE BEEN KILLED THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

THE UP EXPLAINS IN ITS LETTER THAT THE ASSASSINATION ON 22 MARCH OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO, ITS PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, FORCED IT TO WITHDRAW FROM THE 27 MAY ELECTIONS. THIS DID NOT DETER IT, HOWEVER, FROM ITS STRUGGLE FOR A PLEBISCITE AND FROM CALLING FOR A NATIONAL, POPULAR AND DEMOCRATIC CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY.

THE UP ADDED THAT A CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY, WHICH WILL REPRESENT ALL POPULAR SECTORS, WILL BE CHARGED WITH DRAFTING CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS. THE REFORMS MUST THEN BE SUBMITTED TO A PLEBISCITE.

A WEEK AGO, THE LIBERAL PARTY, SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PARTY, 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19), AND NATIONAL SALVATION MOVEMENT MET TO TRY TO REACH AN AGREEMENT THAT WILL PERMIT HOLDING A NATIONAL PLEBISCITE ON 27 MAY TO APPROVE SUBSTANTIAL REFORMS TO THE STATE.

GOVERNMENT MINISTER HORACIO SERPA URIBE STATED THAT THE ADMINISTRATION HAS NOT AND DOES NOT SEEK TO IMPOSE ITS CRITERIA ON THE WILL TO EFFECT CONSTITUTIONAL REFORM. HE ADDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION IS VERY CLEAR AND SEEKS TO RESPOND TO THE WILL OF THE PEOPLE.

ALSO, THE UP CONVENED POLITICAL PARTIES, SOCIAL FORCES, STUDENTS, AND COLOMBIANS IN GENERAL WHO WERE EXCLUDED FROM THESE NEGOTIATIONS, TO UNITE A PROPOSAL ON THE 27 MAY PLEBISCITE.

FINALLY, THE UP DIRECTORATE ASKED, AS A CONTRIBUTION TO PEACE IN THE COUNTRY, TO BE ABLE TO MEET WITH THE REBEL FORCES.

DEV-MUC3-1243 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 27 APR 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [STATEMENT] [LIBERAL PARTY PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO] [TEXT] COLOMBIANS, DURING THESE MONTHS OF NATIONAL TRAGEDY WE HAVE BEEN HIT BY EVENTS OVER AND OVER AGAIN. VIOLENCE STRIKES THE HEARTS OF OUR INSTITUTIONS, VALUES, DEMOCRACY, AND OUR BEST MEN. THE ULTIMATE GOAL OF THOSE ENGAGED IN VIOLENCE IS TO PREVENT DEMOCRACY FROM FUNCTIONING. THAT IS WHY THEY HAVE UNLEASHED THEIR EVIL AGAINST OPTIONS FOR CHANGES THAT COULD STRENGTHEN DEMOCRACY AND PREVENT VIOLENCE IN COLOMBIA. BRAVE COLOMBIANS HAVE BEEN MURDERED, ONE BY ONE. THEIR EXISTENCE WAS A THREAT TO THE SURVIVAL OF VIOLENT PRACTICES. IT IS NOT A COINCIDENCE THAT DURING THE CURRENT ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN THREE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES HAVE BEEN MURDERED. IT IS NOT A COINCIDENCE EITHER THAT OTHER BRAVE MINDS THAT ADVOCATED REFORM HAD BEEN KILLED BEFORE IN THAT STRUGGLE.

RODRIGO LARA, WHO WAS MURDERED SIX YEARS ON 23 APRIL, WAS THE FIRST TO DENOUNCE THE GRAVE EFFECTS OF DRUG TRAFFICKING ON THE STABILITY OF OUR INSTITUTIONS. THOSE WHO KILLED HIM WANTED TO OPEN PATHS FOR THE SO-CALLED CRIME TOLERANCE.

GUILLERMO CANO, A BRAVE NEWSMAN, REPRESENTED A FREE, CRITICAL PRESS, SUCH AS IS NEEDED IN A TRUE DEMOCRACY. HIS KILLERS THOUGHT THAT BY DROWNING OUT HIS VOICE THEY WOULD INTIMIDATE THE DEFENDERS OF FREEDOM OF SPEECH.

LUIS CARLOS GALAN WAS KILLED EIGHT MONTHS AGO. BY KILLING HIM, THEY SOUGHT TO ASSASSINATE A HOPE OF RENOVATION AND CHANGE AND A DEEP CONVICTION FOR THE NEED TO RADICALLY TRANSFORM POLITICAL HABITS AND THE CLIMATE OF CORRUPTION, IMMORALITY, AND INDIFFERENCE IN THE FACE OF CRIME. THIS INDIFFERENCE LED TO THE EMERGENCE OF THE GREAT EVILS THAT ARE CAUSING BLOODSHED IN THE COUNTRY.

BERNARDO JARAMILLO STRUGGLED FOR A PEACEFUL, DEMOCRATIC LEFT THAT REJECTED ARMED STRUGGLE AND THAT WANTED TO BUILD A MORE JUST SOCIETY. BY KILLING HIM, THE CRIMINALS SOUGHT TO BLOCK THE PATHS TO LEGITIMATE PROTEST WITHIN THE LAW.

CARLOS PIZARRO, THE LAST LINK IN THIS MACABRE CHAIN THAT INCLUDES SO MANY OTHERS, REPRESENTED THE POSSIBILITY FOR GUERRILLA GROUPS TO LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND JOIN INSTITUTIONAL POLITICS, OR FOR WEAPONS TO BE REPLACED BY LEGAL INSTRUMENTS TO STRUGGLE FOR LEGITIMATE IDEALS. BY KILLING HIM IN A DASTARDLY AND COWARDLY MANNER YESTERDAY, THEY SOUGHT TO DESTROY THE PROCESS OF RECONCILIATION AND REINCORPORATION OF ARMED GROUPS INTO CIVIL LIFE.

THE DEATH OF OUR COUNTRYMEN SHOULD NOT BE IN VAIN. IT STRIKES DEEP IN OUR HEARTS. IT AFFECTS THE SPIRIT PROFOUNDLY. IT MUST, THEREFORE, AWAKEN THE NATIONAL CONSCIENCE, BECAUSE THOSE CRIMES ARE NOT MERELY VILE CRIMES AGAINST UNARMED GREAT MEN WHO BELIEVED IN THE STRENGTH OF IDEALS. THESE HAVE BEEN CRIMES AGAINST OUR BASIC VALUES, AGAINST THE CLEAN IDEALS OF PROGRESS AND PEACE THAT THESE MEN REPRESENTED. WE MUST NOT BE MISTAKEN. THOSE WHO KILLED OUR LEADERS DID NOT EXTINGUISH THE NOBLE CAUSE FOR WHICH THEY GAVE THEIR LIVES. THEIR VALUES WILL PREVAIL. THEY ARE OUR VALUES. THEIR HOPES STILL LIVE. THOSE HOPES BELONG TO ALL COLOMBIANS. THEIR DREAM WILL NEVER DISAPPEAR. IT IS THE DREAM WE ALL HAVE OF ATTAINING PEACE AND PROSPERITY. THAT IS WHY I PRAISE WHAT ANTONIO NAVARRO SAID LAST NIGHT: "I INVITE THE M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] TO CONTINUE WALKING ALONG THE PATH THAT PIZARRO CHARTED. TERRORISM'S GOAL HAS BEEN TO CLOSE THE PATHS TO CHANGE, RENOVATION, AND REFORM.

OUR PATH, ON THE CONTRARY, IS TO MAKE PEACEFUL, DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTION VIABLE. IT IS A REVOLUTION OF HOPE. THIS DEEP CRISIS WILL NOT BE SOLVED BY RESTRICTIONS AND LIMITATIONS IMPOSED ON THE INSTRUMENTS OF DEMOCRACY, BUT BY UNITING EFFORTS OF ALL GOOD COLOMBIANS TO REPAIR THE ROADS TO CHANGE, RENOVATION, AND REFORM. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1244 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 27 APR 90 [INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] I AM HAPPY THAT NAVARRO, OVER THE TELEVISION, CALLED FOR COMMON SENSE AND FOR PIZARRO'S FUNERAL TO BE CONDUCTED IN PEACE TOMORROW. IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE LAW, THE GOVERNMENT WILL CONTINUE TO DO EVERYTHING POSSIBLE SO THAT THE M-19 AND THE OTHER POLITICAL PARTIES CAN CARRY ON THEIR CAMPAIGN ACTIVITIES. THE GOVERNMENT AND I HAVE FULLY SUPPORTED THE ARMY, THE POLICE, THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY], AND ALL OF THE AUTHORITIES CHARGED WITH MAINTAINING ORDER. THESE AGENCIES ARE AWARE OF THEIR RESPONSIBILITY AND ARE MAKING GREAT EFFORTS TO CARRY OUT THEIR DUTIES EFFICIENTLY.

AT THIS TIME, THERE IS A TENDENCY TO OVERLOOK THE RESULTS ACHIEVED IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE VIOLENT ONES AND THE SIGNIFICANT PROGRESS ACHIEVED. I UNDERSTAND THE IMPATIENCE AND THE DESIRE FOR DEFINITIVE RESULTS AGAINST NOT ONLY DRUG TRAFFICKING BUT ALL OTHER EXPRESSIONS OF VIOLENCE AS WELL.

I WILL NOW MENTION SOME OF THE MEASURES THAT COMPLEMENT THOSE THAT HAVE ALREADY BEEN TAKEN. THE GOVERNMENT HAS PROPOSED THE CREATION OF A HIGH-LEVEL COMMISSION, IN WHICH THE POLITICAL PARTIES ARE REPRESENTED, TO FOLLOW UP THE ELECTORAL PROCESS AND TO ASSESS THE SECURITY MEASURES THAT THE PUBLIC FORCE AND THE SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS HAVE BEEN PROVIDING FOR ALL CANDIDATES. THIS COMMISSION CAN BY ITSELF PROPOSE NEW MEASURES TO REINFORCE THE ELECTORAL GUARANTEES IN VARIOUS AREAS. IN ADDITION, THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER AND THOSE IN CHARGE OF SECURITY WILL MEET WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF EACH OF THE POLITICAL CAMPAIGNS TO CONSIDER THE EXISTING PROTECTION MEASURES. THE COMMISSION MET WITH THE M-19 AT THE SECURITY COUNCIL TODAY AND WILL MEET WITH THE OTHER POLITICAL MOVEMENTS IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS.

THE GOVERNMENT HAS MADE EFFORTS TO PROVIDE THE BEST POSSIBLE PROTECTION FOR ALL OF THE CANDIDATES. THE GOVERNMENT WILL CONTINUE TO WORK TO REDUCE THE RISK OF EACH OF THE CANDIDATES TO ITS LOWEST LEVEL. FOR THIS REASON, THE GOVERMENT WILL REVISE THE EXISTING SITUATION REGARDING MOBILIZATION AND LOCATION OF THE CANDIDATES. ALSO, THE GOVERNMENT WILL DOUBLE THE NUMBER OF ELITE POLICEMEN, WHO HAVE DEMONSTRATED THE GREATEST EFFICIENCY IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TERRORISM AND THE PARAMILITARY GROUPS. THE 1ST ARMY DIVISION COMMANDER HAS BEEN ASSIGNED THE SPECIFIC TASK OF COORDINATING ALL FORCES, SECURITY AGENCIES, AND MILITARY OPERATIONS IN THE MEDELLIN AREA.

THE COUNTRY KNOWS THAT THIS GOVERNMENT HAS ENCOURAGED A BROAD, PARTICIPATIVE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORM PROCESS. TWO YEARS AGO, THE GOVERNMENT PROPOSED A PLEBISCITE AND THEN PRESENTED TO THE CONGRESS A CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS BILL. IN THIS WAY, THE GOVERNMENT INTERPRETED THE NATIONAL FEELING, WHICH DEMANDS A MORE EFFICIENT ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE AND EVEN MORE STRINGENT ANTITERRORIST MEASURES, FOR WHICH IT IS NECESSARY TO AMEND THE CONSTITUTION. THE GOVERNMENT ALSO ECHOED THE PEOPLE'S CALL FOR STRONGER INSTITUTIONS AND A MORE EFFICIENT AND REPRESENTATIVE CONGRESS. COLOMBIANS KNOW THAT THE CURRENT EVILS WILL BE DEFINITIVELY OVERCOME BY EXPANDING AND STRENGTHENING OUR DEMOCRACY EVEN FURTHER, CREATING OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE CITIZENS' PARTICIPATION IN THE DECISIONS THAT CONCERN THEM MOST.

I WANT TO REAFFIRM THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO DO EVEYTHING NECESSARY SO THAT IN THE NEXT ELECTIONS WE CAN PAVE THE WAY FOR CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1245 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 27 APR 90 [INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] FELLOW COUNTRYMEN: THE MURDER OF CARLOS PIZARRO SOUGHT BOTH TO DISRUPT THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE ELECTORAL PROCESS, AS WELL AS TO DESTROY THE PROCESS OF RECONCILIATION THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND M- 19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] HAD CAREFULLY BUILT, SURPASSING NUMEROUS OBSTACLES. IT ALSO SEEKS TO WEAKEN THE STATE AND MAKE COLOMBIANS LOSE FAITH IN DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS. HOWEVER, THOSE WHO FOMENT VIOLENCE WILL NOT MANAGE TO WEAKEN A STRONG DEMOCRACY THAT IS SUPPORTED BY ALL COLOMBIANS OR TO DESTROY THE PATH OF PEACE THAT WE HAVE BUILT AFTER SO MANY DIFFICULTIES.

TWO OF THESE DIFFICULTIES STEM BACK MORE THAN FIVE DECADES. THE FIRST DIFFICULTY WAS TO BUILD AN ATMOSPHERE OF PEACE IN A COUNTRY WHERE THE VIOLENCE WE HAVE INHERITED FLARED UP IN THE FIFTIES, AND AFTER HAVING EVOLVED, IT HAS TAKEN ON DIFFERENT FORMS, SUCH AS NARCO-TERRORISM AND BANDS OF HIRED ASSASSINS ENCOURAGED BY GROUPS OF THE EXTREME RIGHT.

THE SECOND OBSTACLE, ALONG WITH THE PREVIOUS ONE, IS THE LACK OF TOLERANCE FOR POLITICAL PLURALISM. EVEN PROGRESSIVE IDEAS ARE MANY TIMES CONSIDERED DANGEROUS BY PEOPLE WHO DO NOT REALIZE THAT THE COLD WAR IS OVER. A PLURALIST DEMOCRACY IS NOT AFRAID OF COMMUNISM. ON THE CONTRARY, IT ACCEPTS COMMUNISM, BUT IT DOES NOT ACCEPT VIOLENCE, REGARDLESS OF ITS SOURCE. THE USE OF WEAPONS BOTH TO DEFEND AN IDEOLOGY, AS WELL AS TO FIGHT AGAINST IT, IS UNACCEPTABLE IN A PLURALIST DEMOCRACY.

THE PERSONS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE TRAGIC MURDER OF CARLOS PIZARRO WILL NOT MANAGE TO DESTROY WHAT HAS BEEN BEEN ACHIEVED, THAT IS, A CLEAR, VIABLE, AND DEFINED PATH TO PEACE. THE OBLIGATION WE HAVE AHEAD OF US AND THAT WE WILL CARRY OUT UNITED IS TO KEEP THAT PATH OF PEACE OPEN.

ALL COLOMBIANS ADMIRE THE PEACE INITIATIVES OF THE M-19, AND WE SHARE THE GRIEF OF THE RELATIVES AND FOLLOWERS OF CARLOS PIZARRO, BECAUSE THEIR SADNESS AND ANGER IS SHARED BY ALL COLOMBIANS WHO LOVE PEACE. FACTS SHOW THAT THE M-19 MEMBERS WISELY ADOPTED THE DECISION TO REJOIN DEMOCRACY AND REMAIN IN DEMOCRACY, TO STRUGGLE FOR PEACE, AND TO PROMOTE LEGALLY THE REFORMS THEY CONSIDER NECESSARY.

WHEN THEY ABANDONED THEIR WEAPONS, THEY DID NOT ABANDON THE STRUGGLE FOR THEIR IDEALS. THEY HAVE ALL THEIR RIGHTS, BECAUSE THEY ARE NO LONGER A GUERRILLA GROUP. M-19 IS NOW A POLITICAL PARTY, WITH ALL RIGHTS AND DUTIES OF A POLITICAL PARTY AND WHOSE IDEAS SHOULD BE TOLERATED. THOSE WHO, THROUGH VIOLENCE, ARE TRYING TO BRING DOWN THE M-19 FLAG AND TO PREVENT ITS CANDIDATES FROM RUNNING IN THE ELECTIONS AND TO STOP THEM FROM CONDUCTING POLITICAL CAMPAIGNING, ARE NOT JUST THE ENEMIES OF THAT MOVEMENT, THEY ARE THE ENEMIES OF PEACE. THEY ARE TRYING TO DESTROY THE PATH THAT WAS BUILT FOR THE REINCORPORATION OF THE GUERRILLA GROUPS INTO CIVILIAN LIFE.

THE MATERIAL AND INTELLECTUAL AUTHORS OF CARLOS PIZARRO'S MURDER ARE THE ENEMIES OF DEMOCRACY, BECAUSE THEY HOPE TO SABOTAGE THE ELECTIONS AND PREVENT NEW OPPORTUNITIES FOR POLITICAL PARTICIPATION. THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT ALLOW THE VOICE OF M-19 TO BE SILENCED. THEREFORE, THE GOVERNMENT YESTERDAY REQUESTED AIRTIME ON TELEVISION SO THAT ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF, LEADER OF THAT PARTY, COULD EXPRESS HIS OPINIONS TO ALL COLOMBIANS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1246 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 27 APR 90 [INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] WHEN THE CONVERGENCE OF OPINIONS ON THE FUNDAMENTAL ASPECTS OF THE CREATION OF A CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY IS MADE PUBLIC, THE GOVERNMENT WILL CONTRIBUTE TOWARD THE COUNTING OF THE RELEVANT BALLOT PAPERS.

THE GOVERNMENT BELIEVES IT IS NECESSARY TO REDUCE AS MUCH AS POSSIBLE THE RISK FOR EACH OF THE CANDIDATES. DESPITE THE STRICT SECURITY MEASURES TAKEN BY CARLOS PIZARRO, THE SUICIDAL CALLING OF A HIRED ASSASSIN AT THE SERVICE OF EVIL INTERESTS ENDED HIS LIFE.

IN VIEW OF THESE TOTALLY IRRATIONAL METHODS, LARGE NUMBERS OF BODYGUARDS, BULLETPROOF VESTS, AND PRACTICAL SECURITY MEASURES COULD HELP, BUT THEY ARE NOT ENOUGH.

IT IS NECESSARY FOR AUTHORITIES AND CAMPAIGN OFFICIALS TO TAKE MAXIMUM PRECAUTIONARY MEASURES. THERE MUST BE MORE MODERN AND DIRECT COMMUNICATION WITH THE PEOPLE.

I ADMIRE THE COURAGE OF THE CANDIDATES WHO HAVE GONE TO PUBLIC SQUARES, BUT WE ALL KNOW THAT THE HEALTH OF DEMOCRACY AND THE STABILITY OF INSTITUTIONS DEPENDS ON THE LIVES OF THE CANDIDATES.

SO THIS CAMPAIGN CAN TAKE PLACE UNDER THE BEST OF CONDITIONS WITHOUT THE NEED FOR CANDIDATES TO RUN THE RISKS INVOLVED IN TRADITIONAL FORMS OF PROSELYTISM, THE GOVERNMENT HAS DECIDED TO INCREASE TELEVISION TIME FOR THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES OF THE PARTIES AND MOVEMENTS THAT ARE REPRESENTED IN CONGRESS, ON BOTH NATIONAL AND REGIONAL CHANNELS.

IN ADDITION, THE GOVERNMENT WILL ALLOW THE FREE USE OF RADIO STATIONS FOR THE SAME PURPOSE AND WILL GIVE MORE OPPORTUNITIES FOR ADVERTISEMENTS. WE ARE TRYING FOR A MORE MODERN CAMPAIGN IN WHICH NEW TECHNIQUES CAN BE USED TO EXPLAIN THE PROGRAMS OF THE CANDIDATES SO THAT THEY CAN DIRECTLY MAKE CONTACT WITH CITIZENS AND THEIR FAMILIES IN THEIR OWN HOMES.

BESIDES, THE GOVERNMENT WILL INTENSIFY ITS CIVIC CAMPAIGN BY INVITING ALL CITIZENS TO VOTE IN THE NEXT ELECTIONS. THEIR VOTE FOR ANY OF THE CANDIDATES OR EVEN A BLANK VOTE IS AN EXPRESSION OF THE PEOPLE'S REJECTION OF VIOLENCE. IT IS A WAY OF RESOLVING CONFLICTS BY PEACEFUL AND DEMOCRATIC MEANS.

TO ACTIVELY PARTICIPATE IN THE NEXT ELECTIONS IS TO VOTE FOR PEACE, FOR DEMOCRACY AND TOLERANCE. AMID THE SITUATION IN WHICH THIS COUNTRY IS LIVING, VOTING IS AN OBLIGATION. NO CITIZEN WITH A RIGHT TO VOTE CAN AFFORD TO REMAIN AT HOME AND REMAIN INDIFFERENT. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1247 (BOEING)

TEGUCIGALPA, 23 APR 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH CALLEJAS BY MODERATOR VALLADARES AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CALLEJAS] WHAT I HAVE TO SAY THIS EVENING IS THAT WE MADE A CORRECT DECISION. THE ARMED FORCES' BUDGET WAS REDUCED BY 10 PERCENT; TO ASK FOR A GREATER REDUCTION IS NOT TO KNOW OUR COUNTRY'S REALITY AND TO DESTROY THE ARMED FORCES. TO REDUCE THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES' BUDGET BY 50 PERCENT IS TANTAMOUNT TO DISMANTLING IT, AND I FOR ONE AM NOT WILLING TO MAKE THAT DECISION. I AGREED TO TAKE THE CORRECT PATH AT THE RIGHT MOMENT; TO REDIRECT THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES AND TO SEE THEY ALSO ACT WITH AUSTERITY AND IN THE BEST NATIONAL INTEREST.

IT IS EASY TO CRITICIZE AND SAY THINGS, BUT WHEN THESE PEOPLE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO RESOLVE THIS, NOTHING WAS DONE. I HAVE ACTED.

[VALLADARES] GERMAN REYES OF ACAN-EFE.

[REYES] GOOD EVENING. BEFORE ANYTHING ELSE I THINK WE SHOULD APOLOGIZE TO THE HOUSEWIVES FOR HAVING RUINED THEIR SOAP OPERA. REGARDING THE GREEN BATTALIONS YOU MENTIONED, MR. PRESIDENT, WHICH ARE GOING TO BE INSTALLED IN YAMALES -- WHERE THEY SHOULD HAVE BEEN BEFORE THE CONTRAS ENTERED -- HOW ARE THE ONUCA [UNITED NATIONS OBSERVER GROUP IN CENTRAL AMERICA] OFFICERS GOING TO VERIFY THAT THE CONTRA WITHDRAWAL FROM HONDURAN TERRITORY?

[CALLEJAS] THERE IS NO PROBLEM. THE YAMALES CAMP IS INSIDE HONDURAN TERRITORY. THERE ARE MECHANISMS THAT ALLOW ONUCA AND CIAV [INTERNATIONAL COMMISSION FOR SUPPORT AND VERIFICATION] FORCES TO CONTROL THESE PERSONS. ONCE MORE I WOULD LIKE TO REFER TO THE POSITION YOU ARE TAKING: WHY NOT SEE THINGS POSITIVELY? INSTEAD OF SAYING WE HAD CONTRAS HERE FOR 10 YEARS, SAY THAT NOW WE DO NOT HAVE ANY. I THINK THIS IS THE TYPE OF OPTIMISM WE SHOULD IMPRESS UPON THE COUNTRY. LET US NOT COMPLAIN ABOUT YESTERDAY, INSTEAD BUILD ON TODAY'S REALITY. I AM VERY HAPPY TO BE HERE AT THIS NEWS CONFERENCE AND TO BE ABLE TO TELL MY FELLOW CITIZENS AND YOU THAT NO LONGER ARE WE TO HAVE CONTRAS IN HONDURAS -- A POSITIVE STEP. IN THIS REGARD THE GREEN BATTALIONS AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE TAKING ACTION TO ADMINISTER A TERRITORY THAT ONLY YESTERDAY WAS RELATIVELY OUT OF CONTROL OF THE GOVERNMENT.

[VALLADARES] [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, MUCH HAS BEEN SAID ABOUT THESE $247 MILLION -- IT SEEMS LIKE A LARGE SUM -- WHICH TELLS OF THE SUCCESS OF YOUR TRIP TO THE UNITED STATES. THIS, HOWEVER, IS TO BE USED TO PAY DEBTS. DO YOU KNOW OF ANY SPECIFIC AMOUNTS YOU MAY BE RECEIVING IN THE FUTURE, OR IS IT A QUESTION OF HAVING TO WAIT THERE WITH A LITTLE PAPER BAG TO THEN HAND IT OVER TO [CENTRAL BANK PRESIDENT] DON RICARDO MADURO? WHAT ARE THE RESOURCE FORECASTS AND WHAT DEFINITE INVESTMENT PLANS ARE THERE FOR THESE RESOURCES? ONE MUST ESPECIALLY TAKE INTO ACCOUNT THE IMPACT THIS WILL HAVE ON THE CENTRAL BANK CURRENCY RESERVES SINCE INFLATION CAN BE A TIME BOMB. LASTLY, I WOULD LIKE TO ASK YOU IF YOU.... [CHANGES THOUGHT] APPARENTLY MY COLLEAGUE REGINA HAS AN IMPORTANT QUESTION BEFORE YOU END THE CONFERENCE WITH ME. THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.

[CALLEJAS] NO PROBLEM. I WOULD CONTINUE THIS CONFERENCE ALL NIGHT LONG, ALTHOUGH I DO NOT WISH TO KEEP THE HOUSEWIVES FROM THEIR PROGRAMS. HOWEVER, EVERYTHING HAS A TIME FRAME AND OUR INTEREST IS THAT ALL REPORTERS HERE TONIGHT SHOULD HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY OF TAKING PART IN THIS NEWS CONFERENCE. GETTING BACK TO YOUR QUESTION, THE TOTAL AMOUNT OF FUNDS AVAILABLE FOR THE ARMED FORCES WAS ESTABLISHED THIS WAY: THE 1989 BUDGET APPROVED BY CONGRESS WAS 150 MILLION LEMPIRAS.

[REPORTER] PERHAPS I DID NOT MAKE MYSELF CLEAR. I WAS REFERRING TO THE FUNDS THE GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE AVAILABLE ONCE LOANS WERE PAID OFF WITH THESE STOPGAP LOANS.

[CALLEJAS] YOU ARE RIGHT. WE ARE TALKING ABOUT THE STOPGAP FINANCING FOR $247 MILLION. THIS STOPGAP LOAN OPENS THE PATH SO THAT FRIENDLY COUNTRIES AND BILATERAL AND MULTILATERAL FINANCIAL ORGANIZATIONS CAN RESUME THEIR LOANS TO THE COUNTRY. THESE FUNDS WILL GIVE US THE RIGHT TO DRAW ON SPECIAL IMF ACCOUNTS, FUNDS FROM SPECIAL WORLD BANK PROGRAMS SUCH AS SAL-1 AND SAL-2, OR FUNDS THAT HAVE BEEN WITHHELD FROM JAPAN AND GERMANY. THE TOTAL AMOUNT OF THESE FUNDS IS ENOUGH TO PAY THE $247 MILLION STOPGAP LOAN IN FULL AND STILL HAVE SOME CASH LEFT OVER FOR SOME OF THESE ORGANIZATIONS THAT MAY GENERATE FUNDS FOR THE COUNTRY. THE PRECISE AMOUNTS WILL BE GIVEN BY THE CENTRAL BANK PRESIDENT; HOWEVER, TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, THE AMOUNT OF FUNDS TO BE RECEIVED WILL BE NO LESS THAN THE AMOUNT BEING LOANED, PLUS SOME SURPLUSES FROM INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS AND FRIENDLY COUNTRIES, WHICH HAVE WITHHELD THEIR LOANS OR DONATIONS BECAUSE OF HONDURAS' INELIGIBILITY WITH THE IMF. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1249 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 29 APR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] FOLLOWING THE FUNERAL OF M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] PRESIDENT CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ, THE GROUP'S NEW PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF SAID THAT HIS GROUP WILL CONTINUE THE STRUGGLE FOR PEACE. THE M-19, THE ORGANIZATION THAT SIGNED A PEACE AGREEMENT WITH PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO'S GOVERNMENT ON 8 MARCH AND LAID DOWN ITS WEAPONS ON 9 MARCH TO BECOME A POLITICAL PARTY, SAID THAT IT WILL NOT PICK UP ITS WEAPONS AGAIN AS A RESULT OF THE MURDER OF THE 39-YEAR-OLD PIZARRO. PIZARRO WAS BURIED YESTERDAY. ONLY 50 DAYS AFTER REJOINING CIVILIAN LIFE FOLLOWING MORE THAN 20 YEARS OF ARMED STRUGGLE, PIZARRO BECAME A SYMBOL FOR PEACE, ALTHOUGH, ACCORDING TO COMMENTATORS, WITH HIS DEATH HIS KILLERS ARE ATTEMPTING TO DESTABILIZE THE COUNTRY.

WHEN ACCEPTING THE PRESIDENTIAL NOMINATION, ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF, A 42-YEAR-OLD ENGINEER, FORMER DEAN OF A UNIVERSITY, REBEL, AND THE OLDEST OF SEVEN BROTHERS AND SISTERS, SAID THAT HE WAS RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT FOR THAT COLOMBIA WHICH WANTS DEMOCRACY AND WISHES TO LIVE IN PEACE. THE NEW M-19 PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE WAS FORCED TO SPEAK AND ACCEPT THE NOMINATION WHEN PIZARRO'S FUNERAL PROCESSION MADE A STOP AT THE HOME OF THE LIBERATOR SIMON BOLIVAR. HE SAID THAT THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE MUST UNITE TO MAKE HARMONY POSSIBLE, AND HE URGED EVERYONE TO CONTRIBUTE TO A FUTURE OF PEACE, A BETTER FUTURE FOR COMING GENERATIONS. SPEAKING BEFORE PIZARRO'S CASKET, WHICH WAS DRAPED WITH THE COLOMBIAN FLAG, NAVARRO, WHO IN 1985 SURVIVED AN ATTACK DURING WHICH HE LOST A LEG, SWORE TO FIGHT FOR PEACE AS PIZARRO HAD DONE.

THE THOUSANDS OF PERSONS WHO ATTENDED SATURDAY'S FUNERAL CARRIED PLACARDS WITH SLOGANS THAT READ: COMMANDER PIZARRO, WE CONTINUE FORWARD, AND COMRADE PIZARRO, WE ARE FOR PEACE, WE SWEAR. OTHERS WHO JOINED THE THOUSANDS OF VOICES ASKING NAVARRO TO ACCEPT THE PRESIDENTIAL NOMINATION BROKE THE SILENCE ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS TO CHANT: PIZARRO PRESENT, NAVARRO PRESIDENT.

PIZARRO'S MOTHER MARGOT DE PIZARRO, ALONG WITH HIS LADY FRIEND LAURA, SPOKE AT THE GRAVE SITE AND ASKED THE CROWD TO FIGHT FOR PEACE AS HE HAD ALWAYS DONE.

AT THE CEMETERY THE NEW PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE AGAIN ADDRESSED THE CROWD, WHO HAD FOLLOWED THE MORE THAN SEVEN-HOUR-LONG FUNERAL PROCESSION FROM THE CATHEDRAL TO SIMON BOLIVAR'S HOME AND THEN TO THE CEMETERY. HE SAID: TOGETHER WITH ALL THE GOOD COLOMBIANS, WE ARE GOING TO CHANGE THE COURSE OF HISTORY. HE ADDED THAT PIZARRO'S MURDER WAS USELESS BECAUSE THE M-19 WILL CONTINUE ITS STRUGGLE FOR PEACE.

PIZARRO'S FUNERAL WAS HELD IN BOGOTA. THE AUTHORITIES PRAISED THE FACT THAT NO INCIDENTS OR PUBLIC DISORDERS DEVELOPED DURING THE FUNERAL. THE M-19 LEADERS HAD ASKED THE PEOPLE TO REMAIN CALM.

THE NEW COLOMBIAN PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE IS THE SIXTH COMMANDER M-19 HAS HAD, THE SECOND SINCE THE REBEL GROUP ENTERED ITS NEW PHASE TO BECOME A POLITICAL PARTY. ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF WILL BE RUNNING AGAINST 12 OTHER CANDIDATES IN THE ELECTIONS SCHEDULED FOR 27 MAY.

DEV-MUC3-1250 (BOEING)

BUENOS AIRES, 29 APR 90 (CLARIN) -- [ARTICLE] [DANIEL E. ARIAS] [TEXT] EVERYBODY IS PRAISING AND JUSTIFYING THE ARGENTINE CONDOR II PROJECT -- THE ONLY ONE WE HAD -- NOW THAT IT HAS OFFICIALLY DIED, HOWEVER, A MORE TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION OF THE DEFUNCT PROJECT WILL REVEAL THE GAP LEFT BY OUR FLIMSY SPACE PROJECT.

ACCORDING TO THE TYPE OF FUEL USED, MISSILES ARE CLASSIFIED AS SOLID, LIQUID, AND CRYOGENIC-FUELED MISSILES. THE SOLID-FUELED MISSILES CARRY THEIR FUEL (THAT BURNS) AND THE COMBURENT (THAT SUPPLIES THE OXYGEN TO TRIGGER THE COMBUSTION) ON A STICKY ROD, THE COMBUSTION OF WHICH CANNOT BE REGULATED. THE CAKE BURNS COMPLETELY ONCE THE COMBUSTION STARTS. THEREFORE, SOLID-FUELED MISSILES ARE DIFFICULT TO CONTROL ALTHOUGH THEY ARE MUCH SIMPLER AND CHEAPER. MOREOVER, THEY PUT UP WITH ROUGH HANDLING AND CAN BE EASILY FIRED. THE MILITARY PREFER THIS TYPE FOR MANUFACTURING SHORT-RANGE MISSILES.

THE LIQUID-FUELED MISSILES CARRY THE FUEL AND THE COMBURENT IN COMPLETELY SEPARATE TANKS. THE TWO ELEMENTS MEET IN A COMBUSTION CHAMBER WHERE THEY IGNITE AFTER TRAVELLING THROUGH PIPES. VALVES MAKE IT POSSIBLE TO REGULATE THE POWER OF THE ENGINE. GROUND PERSONNEL ARE ABLE TO STOP THE ENGINE AND RESTART IT IN FULL FLIGHT, IN SHORT, TO CONTROL THE MISSILE AS THEY WISH THROUGH RADIO MESSAGES.

THE CRYOGENIC-FUELED MISSILES WERE DEVELOPED DURING THE 70'S AND 80'S. THEY CARRY HYDROGEN AND LIQUID GAS WHICH ARE LIGHTER THAN ANY OTHER PROPELLANT ELEMENT BUT WHICH ARE VERY EXPENSIVE TO REFRIGERATE AND TO ISOLATE. THIS TECHNOLOGY MAKES IT POSSIBLE TO BUILD VERY FAST VEHICLES BECAUSE OF THEIR POWER TO WEIGHT RATIO.

THEY ARE USED TO PLACE HUGE COMMUNICATION SATELLITES IN SPACE SOME 36,000 KM ABOVE THE EQUATOR, OR TO ATTACK A CITY FROM THE OTHER SIDE OF THE WORLD.

LIQUID-FUELED MISSILES REPRESENT THE TECHNOLOGY DEVELOPED DURING THE 50'S AND 60'S AND, TO A CERTAIN EXTENT, EXPLAINS SOVIET LEADERSHIP IN SPACE RESEARCH. THESE OLD, HEAVY, CUMBERSOME, AND UNBREAKABLE MISSILES DO NOT HAVE FRAGILE EQUIPMENT AND MAKE IT POSSIBLE TO PLACE CARGO INTO OUTER SPACE AT A REASONABLE COST. ON THE OTHER HAND, THE LARGE FAMILY OF U.S. AND EUROPEAN CRYOGENIC- FUELED MISSILES CONTINUE AT AN EXPERIMENTAL STAGE AND ARE UNPREDICTABLE (AS THE CASE OF THE SPACE SHUTTLE AND THE ARIANE IV AND V). MOREOVER, THEY ARE INCREDIBLY COSTLY.

TOO POOR TO EVEN THINK OF DEVELOPING LIQUID-FUELED MISSILES, BRAZIL AND ARGENTINA HAVE TRIED TO PLACE SOLID-FUELED VEHICLES INTO ORBIT FOR DECADES. THIS IS NOT ALL THAT EASY BECAUSE THESE MISSILES ARE REALLY LITTLE MORE THAN FLYING RODS [CANITAS VOLADORAS], BUT THE CASTOR, WHICH WAS DEVELOPED BY ARGENTINA IN 1978, THE SONDA IV DEVELOPED BY BRAZIL, AND THE JAPANESE LAUNCHING DEVICES DEVELOPED BY ISAS (A UNIVERSITY SPACE RESEARCH AGENCY) HAVE PROVED TO BE REASONABLY MANAGEABLE BEASTS.

THE CASTOR REPRESENTED THE PHASE PREVIOUS TO DESIGNING A SPACESHIP AND THIS MUST BE THE REASON WHY IT MYSTERIOUSLY DIED IN 1978 AFTER A SERIES OF INCREDIBLY SUCCESSFUL TESTS AND AFTER HAVING ALLOWED US TO REACH AN AGREEMENT FOR A "JOINT-VENTURE" WITH THE FRG TO STUDY THE ATMOSPHERE. THE ABSENCE OF MISTAKES BY A DEBTOR COUNTRY MAY BE FATAL.

WHEN ARGENTINA ONCE AGAIN STARTED TO DISCREETLY THINK ABOUT OUTER SPACE (1982/83), IT ALREADY HAD ENOUGH KNOWLEDGE TO CONSIDER LARGER PROJECTS. IN FACT, WITH ITS ONE METER DIAMETER TUBE, THE CONDOR COULD PLACE A 200 KG CARGO IN A LOW POLAR ORBIT OF ONLY 200 KM.

THIS PROJECT WOULD HAVE ALLOWED ARGENTINA TO HAVE ONE OR MORE PAIRS OF EYES IN SPACE SO THAT COULD ASSESS ITS NATURAL RESOURCES, PREDICT THE WATER FLOW OF RIVERS ON WHICH HYDROELECTRIC DAMS COULD BE BUILT, DETERMINE WHERE IT COULD FIND OIL AND URANIUM, AND CHEAPLY STOP ILLEGAL FISHING ON THE CONTINENTAL PLATFORM. THIS POSSIBILITY COULD NOT BE ACCEPTED BY SOME PEOPLE.

BRAZIL, WHICH IS LESS HARD UP, IS ABOUT TO PROGRESS FROM THE SONDA IV TO THE SONDA V AND HAS OPENLY INVITED US TO JOINTLY DEVELOP THE SPACESHIP. WHAT WILL ARGENTINA ANSWER? "WE WILL"? OR WILL IT HAVE A CHAUVINIST ATTITUDE? WHAT A PITY IT DID NOT ADOPT THAT ATTITUDE NOW THAT IT IS LETTING THE CONDOR PROJECT DIE IN ITS FIRST STAGE -- IT WAS NEVER TESTED -- WHEN THE PRESSURE IS NOT AS GREAT AS IT HAS BEEN. WORST OF IT ALL IS THAT IT IS NOT RECEIVING ANYTHING IN EXCHANGE.

VERY WELL THEN, IT IS ACCEPTED, THE CONDOR WILL GO NO FURTHER. WHAT IS LEFT? VERY LITTLE. SHOULD WE DEVELOP SATELLITES EXCLUSIVELY FOR SPACE RESEARCH TO DISCOVER THE SECRETS OF THE SUN, OR STUDY THE COSMIC EXPLOSIONS OF X-RAYS. THESE ISSUES, IF UNAFFECTED BY ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL FACTORS, DO NOT DISTURB ANYBODY. THE NASA IS QUITE WILLING TO GIVE US ROOM, FREE OF CHARGE, ON THEIR ROCKETS FOR THIS TYPE OF SATELLITES. THERE IS NO POSSIBILITY THAT WE WILL GAIN EITHER MONEY OR SPACE SOVEREIGNTY. THERE IS NO NEED TO POINT OUT THAT ANY SIMILARITY BETWEEN THIS POSSIBILITY AND AN INDEPENDENT SPACE RESEARCH PROGRAM, SUCH AS BRAZIL'S, IS MERE COINCIDENCE.

IN THE 80'S ARGENTINA ALLOWED ITS NUCLEAR PROGRAM, WHICH AT THAT TIME WAS THE MOST ADVANCED IN THE THIRD WORLD, TO BE HINDERED. NOW IT IS ALLOWING ITS WINGS TO BE CLIPPED AND, WITH A STUPID SMILE, IS YIELDING EVERY ATTEMPT TO ACHIEVE SOVEREIGNTY IN SPACE. EACH ATTEMPT TO DEVELOP TECHNOLOGY IS LABELLED ARMS ESCALATION BY THOSE CHAMPIONS OF PEACE, OUR CREDITORS.

IT IS QUITE TRUE, THE CONDOR II MAY BE A MISSILE, AS A CARGO AIRCRAFT MAY DROP BOMBS AND A TRUCK MAY BE EQUIPPED WITH ARTILLERY FOR WAR. DOES THIS MEAN THAT ARGENTINA MUST STOP MANUFACTURING ALL TYPE OF VEHICLES? THIS QUESTION IS NOT POINTLESS IN A COUNTRY THAT REFUSES TO MAKE ANY PROGRESS.

DEV-MUC3-1252 (BOEING)

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE ARMY, SEINELDIN BELIEVES, IS DIVIDED INTO ''NATIONALIST'' AND ''ADMINISTRATIVE'' FACTIONS, AND WARNS HE ''CAN'T PREDICT WHAT WILL HAPPEN WHEN THEY CLASH.'' IF A SOLUTION IS NOT FOUND SOON, ''LIBERALISM OR THE LEFT IS GOING TO MAKE HEADWAY AND ENCIRCLE US, AND THAT IS WHY WE HAVE TO ORGANIZE OURSELVES TO DEFEND THE INSTITUTIONS,'' SOMOS OF 14 FEBRUARY REPORTS.

THE PRESS ALSO REPORTS SEINELDIN'S COMMENTS REGARDING THE UNITED STATES. DURING HIS VISIT TO MENDOZA, FOR INSTANCE, HE ADVOCATED A ''CIVILIAN-MILITARY ALLIANCE TO DEFEAT THE TWO IMPERIALISMS, REPRESENTED BY THE UNITED STATES AND THE SOVIET UNION,'' ACCORDING TO LA NACION OF 21 MARCH. SOMOS OF 14 FEBRUARY QUOTES SEINELDIN AS STATING THAT ''THE WORLD IS DIVIDED, AND WHAT WAS THE THIRD WORLD HAS BEEN INFILTRATED BY IMPERIALISM AND COMMUNISM. WE HAVE ALREADY SEEN HOW THE UNITED STATES BLOCKADED VENEZUELA AND IS NOW TRYING TO DO THE SAME WITH MEXICO, WHERE IT HAS INSTALLED A SINGLE PARTY. DRUG TRAFFICKING WILL BE GIVEN AS AN EXCUSE FOR INVADING IT.''

LEVEL OF POPULAR SUPPORT

LA PRENSA OF 13 MARCH ANALYZES A SURVEY ON SEINELDIN'S POPULARITY CONDUCTED BY THE DEMOSKOPIA INSTITUTE FOR MARKET RESEARCH AND POLITICAL STUDIES. ACCORDING TO THE STUDY, ''SEINELDIN IS BETTER KNOWN THAN MANY POLITICIANS'' AND CABINET MEMBERS, SINCE 91 PERCENT OF THE POPULATION KNOWS OR HAS HEARD ABOUT HIM. THE SURVEY SHOWS 20 PERCENT OF THE POPULATION APPROVES OF HIM, 40 PERCENT DISAPPROVES, WHILE 21 PERCENT IS UNDECIDED. THE DEMOSKOPIA STUDY ALSO POINTS OUT THAT, ALTHOUGH SEINELDIN MAY HAVE ''HALF OF PUBLIC OPINION AGAINST HIM,'' THERE IS ''A LARGE PERCENTAGE THAT DOES NOT YET HAVE A DEFINITE OPINION,'' AND THAT ''DEPENDING ON SEINELDIN'S POLITICAL SKILL AND ON HOW MUCH THE COUNTRY'S SITUATION CONTINUES TO DETERIORATE,' HE COULD INCREASE HIS FOLLOWING, PARTICULARLY FROM AMONG THE UNDECIDED.

ACCORDING TO AN OPINION POLL CONDUCTED IN LATE FEBRUARY BY THE UNION STUDY CENTER FOR THE NEW MAJORITY AND REPORTED IN LA NACION OF 23 MARCH, SEINELDIN IS SEEN IN A MORE POSITIVE LIGHT OUTSIDE THE CAPITAL AND GREATER BUENOS AIRES, AMONG PEOPLE WITH LOWER LEVELS OF EDUCATION, AND AMONG SUPPORTERS OF THE RULING JUSTICIALIST PARTY. MORE SPECIFIALLY:.

GEOGRAPHIC LOCATION--IN THE CITY OF BUENOS AIRES, SEINELDIN RECEIVED 14 PERCENT FAVORABLE AND 40 PERCENT NEGATIVE RATINGS; IN GREATER BUENOS AIRES, 26 AND 32 PERCENT, RESPECTIVELY; AND IN THE NORTHWEST REGIONS OF THE COUNTRY, 41 PERCENT FAVORABLE VERSUS 30 PERCENT UNFAVORABLE.

LEVEL OF EDUCATION--IN THE CAPITAL AND GREATER BUENOS AIRES, SEINELDIN HAS A 19 PERCENT APPROVAL RATING AMONG THOSE WHO COMPLETED ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, 14 PERCENT AMONG THOSE WHO COMPLETED SECONDARY SCHOOL, AND 10 PERCENT AMONG THOSE WITH COLLEGE DEGREES.

POLITICAL AFFILIATION--SURVEY PARTICIPANTS WHO VOTED FOR THE RADICAL PARTY DURING THE LAST NATIONAL ELECTIONS GIVE SEINELDIN A 7 PERCENT APPROVAL RATING, THOSE WHO VOTED FOR THE UNITED LEFT GIVE HIM 8 PERCENT, AND AMONG THOSE WHO VOTED FOR THE MENEM-DUHALDE TICKET HIS APPROVAL RATE IS 25 PERCENT.

MILITARY CONCERNS

MILITARY PERSONNEL ARE CONCERNED ABOUT LOW SALARIES AND THE SHARP DECREASE IN PURCHASING POWER, ACCORDING TO AN 11 MARCH ARTICLE IN LA PRENSA. THEIR DISSATISFACTION, WHICH WAS PUBLICIZED IN A FLIER WHICH APPEARED IN SEVERAL PROVINCIAL GARRISONS, WAS DISCUSSED DURING SEINELDIN'S MEETING WITH COMMISSIONED AND NONCOMMISSIONED OFFICERS IN SANTA FE, ACCORDING TO SOMOS OF 14 FEBRUARY.

THE POSSIBILITY OF A SOCIAL EXPLOSION AND THE RELUCTANCE OF THE ''CARAPINTADAS'' TO INTERVENE WERE DISCUSSED DURING SEINELDIN'S MEETINGS IN ROSARIO, ACCORDING TO THE 14 FEBRUARY ISSUE OF SOMOS. ''WE CANNOT ENGAGE IN REPRESSION, AND THAT COULD CAUSE A LOT OF PROBLEMS FOR THE SECURITY FORCES,'' AN ''AUTHORIZED SPOKEMAN'' REPORTEDLY CONFIDED. IF THE ECONOMY DETERIORATES AND SOCIAL UNREST ENSUES, ''UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCE WILL THE ARMED FORCES BE INCLINED TO TAKE THE PLACE OF THE POLICE FORCES IN GUARDING SUPERMARKETS OR ANY PLACE NOT CLEARLY IDENTIFIED AS 'VITAL TO THE NATION,'' ACCORDING TO THE 11 MARCH ISSUE OF LA PRENSA.

DEV-MUC3-1253 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 APR 90 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] THE HIGH COMMAND OF THE ARMED FORCES IS ANALYZING NEWS REPORTS ABOUT COLONEL SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ, PRESIDENT OF AN AUTONOMOUS INSTITUTION, HAVING SAID THAT THE OFFICER INVOLVED IN THE DEATH OF SIX JESUITS AND THEIR TWO MAIDS "FOLLOWED ORDERS FROM ABOVE".

OCHOA MADE THOSE COMMENTS ON A U.S. TELEVISION NEWSCAST AT A TIME WHEN SEVERAL MEMBERS OF [THE U.S.] CONGRESS WANT TO CUT AID TO EL SALVADOR AND ARE CONDUCTING THEIR OWN INVESTIGATIONS OF THE CASE. THE RESULTS OF THEIR INVESTIGATION WILL BE KNOWN NEXT WEEK.

DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS CONFIRMED ON THE MORNING OF 24 APRIL THAT THE HIGH COMMAND IS ANALYZING OCHOA'S DECLARATIONS AND STRESSED THAT VERSIONS SUCH AS THE ONE ATTRIBUTED TO THE OFFICIAL USUALLY COME FROM "INTERESTED PARTIES."

LARIOS, QUESTIONED WHEN HE BID FAREWELL TO PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, WHO LEFT FOR NICARAGUA ON 24 APRIL, SAID THAT "THE CASE IS IN THE COURTS AND ALL THOSE WHO HAVE NEW EVIDENCE MAY APPROACH THEM TO CONTRIBUTE WHAT THEY HAVE SO THAT IT MAY BE SOLVED."

"BOTH THE ARMY AND THE GOVERNMENT WANT EVERYTHING TO BE CLARIFIED WITHIN A FAIR AND LEGAL FRAMEWORK," HE SAID.

ARMY OFFICERS WHO ASKED TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS SAID ON 24 APRIL THAT "THE COMMENTS MADE BY OCHOA, CONTROVERSIAL POLITICIAN AND SOLDIER KNOWN FOR HIS FREQUENT OUTBURSTS, HAVE NO BASIS BECAUSE HE HAS NO ACCESS TO CONFIDENTIAL ARMED FORCES SOURCES DUE TO HIS RETIRED STATUS."

HOWEVER, THE INFORMERS HAVE SAID THAT "WHAT OCHOA SAID NOT ONLY DAMAGES THE ARMY'S IMAGE, BUT THAT OF THE ENTIRE COUNTRY WHILE IT CONTRIBUTES TO THE DEFAMATION CAMPAIGN BEING CARRIED OUT ABROAD BY INTERESTED PARTIES, AMONG THEM, THE LEADERS OF THE FMLN-FDR [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT-REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT]."

THEY ADDED THAT OCHOA'S DECLARATION, "MADE WITHOUT PRESENTING ANY PROOF, ENDANGERS THE MILITARY AID THAT THE UNITED STATES OFFERS TO EL SALVADOR AND, AT THE SAME TIME, FAVORS THE INTERNATIONALIST LEFT WHICH INTENDS TO PLAY THE LAST CARD IT HAS TO ASSAULT POWER IN THIS COUNTRY."

THE POLITICIANS' IMMEDIATE REACTION TO OCHOA PEREZ' COMMENTS WAS TO DEMAND THAT HE BE MORE SPECIFIC IN HIS ACCUSATION. PDC [CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY] LEADER EDUARDO COLINDRES SAID IN A PRESS CONFERENCE THAT "OCHOA PEREZ HAS THE MORAL OBLIGATION OF NAMING" THOSE OF HIS COMRADES-IN-ARMS HE IMPLICATES IN THE DEATH OF THE JESUITS, SINCE THE VERSION HE GAVE TO THE TELEVISION PROGRAM THAT INTERVIEWED HIM IS VAGUE.

THE POLITICIAN SAID: "IF HE KNOWS SOMETHING, IT IS TIME THAT HE BRING IT OUT INTO A PUBLIC LIGHT SO THAT JUSTICE AUTHORITIES MAY TAKE THE APPROPRIATE PATHS."

MEANWHILE, IN MANAGUA, SPANISH GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS WHO ATTENDED VIOLETA CHAMORRO'S INAUGURATION SAID THAT THEY WERE DISAPPOINTED BY THE SLUGGISH MANNER IN WHICH THE INVESTIGATIONS OF THE JESUITS' CASE ARE APPARENTLY BEING CARRIED OUT. THEY SAID THAT THEY MIGHT MENTION THE TOPIC DURING THE MEETINGS THEY WILL HOLD WITH PRESIDENT CRISTIANI IN NICARAGUA.

REPORTS FROM WASHINGTON D.C. QUOTE THE LEFTIST LEADER OF THE FDR, GUILLERMO MANUEL UNGO, AS SAYING THAT "HIS EFFORTS IN THE AMERICAN CAPITAL TO EXPOSE THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR, ARE A SUCCESS."

THE SOURCES SAID THAT UNGO AND HIS MARXIST-LENINIST ALLIES WANT THE U.S. SENATE TO STOP GIVING MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR. THE SOURCES ALSO SAID THAT UNGO DISCREDITS THE ARMY AND THE GOVERNMENT AND FAVORS THE LEGAL RECOGNITION OF THE REBEL GROUPS OPERATING IN THE COUNTRY.

"EVERYTHING SEEMS TO INDICATE THAT THE LEFTIST INTERNATIONALISTS HAVE UNLEASHED A NEW DISINFORMATION OFFENSIVE AGAINST EL SALVADOR WITH THE AID OF BAD SALVADORANS," THE SOURCES SAID.

REFERRING TO OTHER COMMUNIST MOVES IN THE COUNTRY, GENERAL LARIOS SAID THAT THE LOCAL LEFTISTS ARE PREPARING TO STAGE TERRORIST ACTIONS AND STREET DISTURBANCES OVER THE NEXT FEW DAYS UNDER THE PRETEXT OF COMMEMORATING LABOR DAY.

LARIOS URGED THE FMLN-FDR TERRORISTS TO REFRAIN FROM PERPETRATING VIOLENT ACTIONS, THUS CREATING AN ADEQUATE CLIMATE FOR THE "DIALOGUE" ANNOUNCED BY THE GOVERNMENT TO BE HELD ON 3 MAY. "OTHERWISE, THE TERRORISTS WOULD BE VIOLATING THE COMMITMENTS THEY MADE," LARIOS POINTED OUT.

IN ADDITION, IT HAS BEEN REPORTED FROM COSTA RICA THAT FMLN-FDR LEADERS HAVE SAID THAT THEY HAVE PREPARED ANOTHER OFFENSIVE FOR THE NEXT FEW DAYS. THIS ANNOUNCEMENT HAS ELICITED STRONG REJECTION BY VARIOUS SECTORS.

DEV-MUC3-1254 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 MAY 90 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] FOLLOWING A MEETING OF THE GENERAL STAFF WITH ALL THE BRIGADE AND DETACHMENT COMMANDERS, THE ARMED FORCES TODAY ISSUED A PUBLIC COMMUNIQUE DESCRIBING THE RECENT STATEMENTS BY COLONEL SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ AS IRRESPONSIBLE AND TENDENTIOUS. IN PARTS, THE COMMUNIQUE POINTED OUT THAT:

1. WE EMPHATICALLY AND CATEGORICALLY REJECT THE RECENT STATEMENTS BY DISCHARGED COL. SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ PUBLISHED IN THE LOCAL AND FOREIGN MEDIA. THESE STATEMENTS ARE IRRESPONSIBLE AND TENDENTIOUS AND SEEK TO CREATE CONFUSION AND DISTRUST IN THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITIES BY TRYING TO INVOLVE THE MEMBERS OF THE HIGH COMMAND IN THE REGRETTABLE CASE OF THE DEATH OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS AND THEIR WORKERS.

2. WE DEMAND THAT BOTH COL. OCHOA PEREZ, AS WELL AS ANY OTHER PERSON HAVING ANY INFORMATION THAT COULD LEAD TO CLARIFYING THIS CASE OR ANY OTHER CASE, PRESENT IT TO THE CORRESPONDING TRIBUNALS AND NOT TRY TO OBTAIN POLITICAL PROFIT BASED ON ALLEGED STATEMENTS THAT ARE ADDED ON TO THE CAMPAIGN OF DISINFORMATION THAT IS BEING CARRIED OUT IN A SYSTEMATIC MANNER BY NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL MARXIST-LENINIST TERRORISTS.

3. WE CONDEMN SUCH IRRESPONSIBLE STATEMENTS AS THEY SEEK TO UNDERMINE THE INSTITUTIONALITY OF THE STATE, AND ONLY FAVOR THE DARK AND NEFARIOUS INTERESTS OF THE ENEMIES OF DEMOCRACY.

IN CONCLUDING, THE ARMED FORCES COMMUNIQUE REAFFIRMS ITS COMMITMENT TO THE INSTITUTIONALITY OF THE COUNTRY AND THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND POINTED OUT THAT THE INSTITUTION IS RULED BY SOLID PROFESSIONAL, MORAL, AND ETHICAL PRINCIPLES. WITH THIS STATEMENT, ALL THE COMMANDERS GIVE THEIR UNCONDITIONAL VOTE OF CONFIDENCE TO THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND OF THE ARMED FORCES.

DEV-MUC3-1255 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 MAY 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN GUERRILLA GROUPS LAUNCHED SEVERAL ATTACKS ON SEVERAL POINTS OF THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL TONIGHT CAUSING BLACKOUTS AND AN UNDETERMINED NUMBER OF DEAD, IN ADDITION TO CAUSING PANIC AMONG THE CITIZENRY.

MILITARY SPOKESMEN REPORTED THAT THE GUERRILLA ATTACKS BEGAN AT 2130 AND WERE AIMED AT THE PUBLIC SECURITY FORCES' ACADEMY, LOCATED IN THE SOUTHERN SECTOR OF THE CAPITAL, AND MILITARY POSITIONS IN THE WEALTHY ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, WHERE THE SHERATON HOTEL IS LOCATED.

A HEAVY BARRAGE OF RIFLE FIRE AND EXPLOSIONS WERE HEARD FOR APPROXIMATELY ONE HOUR IN THE SAN RAMON AREA, LOCATED IN THE NORTHWESTERN SECTOR OF SAN SALVADOR, WHILE ONE AIR FORCE HELICOPTER OVERFLEW THE CITY.

THERE WERE ALSO REPORTS OF ATTACKS ON A MILITARY POST AT THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL AND OTHER POSITIONS ON THE NORTHWESTERN OUTSKIRTS OF THE CAPITAL.

SIMULTANEOUSLY, URBAN GUERRILLA COMMANDOS ATTACKED THE CIVIL DEFENSE GROUP IN THE COSTA RICA NEIGHBORHOOD OF SOUTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

SEVERAL ELECTRIC POLES WERE BROUGHT DOWN IN VARIOUS SECTORS OF THE CITY, CAUSING BLACKOUTS OVER LARGE AREAS.

THERE ARE STILL NO OFFICIAL REPORTS ON THE NUMBER OF DEAD AND WOUNDED.

EARLY THIS MORNING, GUERRILLA COLUMNS ATTACKED THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE'S POSITIONS IN MARIONA, LOCATED ON THE NORTHERN OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR, KILLING ONE SOLDIER AND WOUNDING ANOTHER.

DEV-MUC3-1257 (BOEING)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 2 MAY 90 (NOTIMEX) -- [EXCERPTS] SAN SALVADOR, 2 MAY (NOTIMEX) -- INTENSE CLASHES WERE HAVE BEEN REPORTED IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER PARTS OF THE COUNTRY WITHIN THE LAST FEW HOURS. THIS IS A NEW MILITARY MANEUVER BY THE GUERILLAS TO PRESSURE THE GOVERNMENT INTO RENEWING THE DIALOGUE.

AT LEAST 10 SOLDIERS WERE KILLED AS A RESULT OF THE HARASSMENT AND ATTACKS BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION MOVEMENT] IN SEVEN OF THE COUNTRY'S 14 DEPARTMENTS.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, THE ATTACKS WERE ACCOMPANIED BY SABOTAGE TO THE ELECTRIC SERVICE SYSTEM. THE ATTACKS STARTED AT 2030 ON 2 MAY AND CONTINUED UNTIL LATE THIS MORNING. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE NATIONAL ENERGY ENTERPRISE REPORTED THAT ELECTRIC POWER WILL BE RATIONED FOR AT LEAST FOUR HOURS DURING THIS MORNING IN MOST OF THE CAPITAL AND OTHER DEPARTMENTS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

MEANWHILE, FMLN SPOKESMEN MADE A TELEPHONE CALL TO A LOCAL RADIO STATION REPORTING THAT THE MILITARY MANEUVER UNLEASHED ON THE NATIONAL LEVEL IS AIMED AT PRESSURING THE ALFREDO CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT TO RENEW THE DIALOGUE.

TALKS BETWEEN THE FNLM AND THE GOVERNMENT ARE SCHEDULED TO START DURING THE FIRST PART OF THIS MONTH, ACCORDING TO UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR, WHO IS ACTING AS A MEDIATOR.

PEREZ DE CUELLAR'S PERSONAL REPRESENTATIVE, ALVARO DE SOTO, TODAY WILL DELIVER TO PRESIDENT CRISTINAI AN FMLN PROPOSAL TO PROMOTE THE DIALOGUE.

DEV-MUC3-1258 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 2 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [TEXT] COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FMLN: WE ANNOUNCE THAT BETWEEN THE NIGHT OF 1 MAY AND THE EARLY MORNING OF 2 MAY, OUR FORCES CONDUCTED SEVERAL MILITARY OPERATIONS IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER CITIES OF THE COUNTRY IN RESPONSE TO:

1. THE PREVAILING TOTAL IMPUNITY OF MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES IN VIOLATING HUMAN RIGHTS, AS DEMONSTRATED BY THE STANDSTILL REACHED IN THE TRIAL, THE EVIDENT COVER UP OF THE MASTERMINDS OF THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE RELEASE OF THE GROUP OF KIDNAPPERS, AND THE RECENT MURDER OF A UNIVERSITY PROFESSOR AND A COOPERATIVE LEADER.

2. THE MILITARY OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE ARMED FORCES IN RURAL AREAS WITH INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS AND ARRESTS OF CIVILIANS.

3. THE ARROGANT AND BOASTFUL ATTITUDE OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE MILITARY BECAUSE OF AN ALLEGED WEAKNESS SHOWN BY THE FMLN, WHICH OBSTRUCTS THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS.

4. THE UNPOPULAR ECONOMIC MEASURES AND THE PLANS TO CARRY OUT THE BIGGEST ECONOMIC FRAUD AND ACT OF CORRUPTION IN OUR COUNTRY'S HISTORY WITH THE PRIVATIZATION OF BANKS.

WE BELIEVE THAT:

1. THE U.S. CONGRESSIONAL PLAN TO CUT ONLY 50 PERCENT OF THE MILITARY ASSISTANCE TO THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT ENOUGH. ANY ASSISTANCE TO TERRORIST ARMED FORCES ONLY CONTRIBUTES TO WAR AND REDUCES THE POSSIBILITY FOR A SHORT-TERM CEASE-FIRE AGREEMENT.

2. AS LONG AS THERE ARE NO GUARANTEES FOR THE ENTIRE SOCIETY, AS LONG AS CRIMES COMMITTED BY THE MILITARY GO UNPUNISHED, AND AS LONG AS REPRESSION DOES NOT STOP, WAR WILL CONTINUE.

FINALLY WE REITERATE OUR WILLINGNESS TO CONTINUE THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS. CONSEQUENTLY, WE HAVE ALREADY PRESENTED OUR POSITIONS TO THE GOVERNMENT AND ARE AWAITING ITS REPLY SO THAT WE CAN START HOLDING THE NEGOTIATIONS. [SIGNED] GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FMLN

EL SALVADOR, 2 MAY 1990

DEV-MUC3-1259 (BOEING)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 2 MAY 90 (NOTIMEX) -- [TEXT] THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT [M - 19] TODAY ACCUSED THE COLOMBIAN INTELLIGENCE SERVICES OF ASSASSINATING M-19 PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE CARLOS PIZARRO.

"WE ATTRIBUTE PIZARRO'S DEATH TO THE COLOMBIAN SECURITY SERVICES," SAID M-19 DIRECTORATE MEMBER RAFAEL VERGARA DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE HELD IN MEXICO CITY.

THE POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION OF THE FORMER REBEL GROUP TURNED POLITICAL PARTY HAS PROPOSED THE CREATION OF AN INTERNATIONAL GROUP TO PERMANENTLY PROTECT THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES' LIVES.

MIGUEL MARIN, ALSO A MEMBER OF THE M-19'S DIRECTORATE, POINTED OUT THE NEED FOR VARIOUS INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS TO DESIGNATE POLITICAL PERSONALITIES WHO WOULD ACCOMPANY EACH OF THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES ON THEIR CAMPAIGNS.

"WE INTEND TO CHECK THE TRIGGERS OF THE COLOMBIAN OLIGARCHY, WHO ARE TO BLAME FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF FOUR PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES IN THE PAST FEW YEARS," THE POLITICAL MOVEMENT'S REPRESENTATIVES SAID.

THEY DENIED THAT THE M-19 IS IN FAVOR OF DRUG TRAFFICKING, BUT ADVOCATED THE LEGALIZATION OF DRUGS AND THE NONEXTRADITION OF DRUG PRODUCERS.

THE M-19 MEMBERS SAID THAT THE CLARIFICATION OF THEIR TOP LEADER'S DEATH IS ESSENTIAL FOR THE CREDIBILITY OF VIRGILIO BARCO'S REGIME. THEY SAID THAT PIZARRO'S BASIC PROPOSALS TO PACIFY THE COUNTRY WILL BE TAKEN UP BY ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF, WHO REPLACED PIZARRO AS THE M-19'S PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.

THEY ASKED THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO HELP PUT AN END TO THE ARMS TRAFFIC TO COLOMBIA, BECAUSE IN 1989 FOREIGN INVESTMENT INCREASED BY 148 PERCENT OVER THAT OF 1988.

"WHAT COLOMBIA NEEDS IS TO ATTAIN PEACE WITH SOCIAL JUSTICE. FOR THIS REASON, IT IS NECESSARY TO TALK AND NEGOTIATE WITH ALL OF THE INFLUENTIAL SECTORS IN COLOMBIA, INCLUDING THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS," VERGARA AND MARIN POINTED OUT.

DEV-MUC3-1260 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A GROUP PURPORTEDLY REPRESENTING YOUNG SALVADORAN MILITARY OFFICERS HAS CALLED FOR A PURGE OF THE ARMED FORCES HERE, ACCUSING THEIR SUPERIORS OF INVOLVEMENT IN THE MASSACRE OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS.

THE CALL CAME WEDNESDAY IN THE WAKE OF A BOLD OFFENSIVE BY LEFTIST GUERRILLAS WHO ATTACKED STRATEGIC TARGETS ACROSS THE CAPITAL, INCLUDING THE RESIDENCE OF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, IN A SHOW OF FORCE BEFORE PEACE TALKS.

THE STATEMENT DISTRIBUTED TO NEWS ORGANIZATIONS WAS MADE IN THE NAME OF A "COMMANDO OF YOUNG OFFICERS." IT GAVE NO NAMES BUT SAID THE GROUP WAS FORMED SECRETLY AMONG OFFICERS FED UP WITH CORRUPTION BY A SMALL GROUP OF MILITARY LEADERS.

IF AUTHENTIC, THE STATEMENT WOULD MARK THE FIRST TIME SINCE A 1979 MILITARY COUP THAT A GROUP OF JUNIOR OFFICERS HAD BROKEN RANKS WITH EL SALVADOR'S MILITARY LEADERSHIP.

"TODAY MORE THAN EVER, ALL THE OFFICERS WHO TRULY WANT TO SAVE OUR INSTITUTION, MUST DEMAND AND EXACT PROFOUND CHANGES AND A GENERAL PURGE AT ALL LEVELS OF THE ARMED FORCES," THE STATEMENT SAID.

THE STATEMENT BLAMED A THREATENED LOSS OF U.S. MILITARY AID ON A FEW CORRUPT OFFICERS WHOM IT HELD RESPONSIBLE FOR THE "EXECRABLE" ASSASSINATIONS OF SIX ROMAN CATHOLIC PRIESTS DURING A REBEL OFFENSIVE IN NOVEMBER.

EL SALVADOR IS SUPPOSED TO RECEIVE 315.4 MILLION DOLLARS IN U.S. AID THIS YEAR, 85 MILLION DOLLARS OF IT IN MILITARY AID. BUT THE U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES HAS VOTED TO CUT MILITARY AID IN HALF AND U.S. SECRETARY OF STATE JAMES BAKER HAS WARNED THAT AID TO EL SALVADOR WILL DEPEND ON PROGRESS IN THE PRIESTS' CASE.

THE PRIESTS, THEIR HOUSEKEEPER AND HER DAUGHTER WERE MURDERED IN THEIR RESIDENCE NOVEMBER 16 IN THE MIDST OF PROLONGED AND BLOODY GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE IN THE CITY. NINE MEMBERS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN CHARGED IN THE KILLINGS BUT MR. CRISTIANI HAS EXPRESSED DOUBTS THAT THEY WILL BE CONVICTED.

"IT IS TRULY SAD AND INFURIATING FOR US THAT THE LOSS OF PRESTIGE OF THE ARMED FORCES HAS GROWN SO MUCH THAT INTERNATIONALLY WE ARE SEEN AS THE ONES TO BLAME FOR THE SITUATION OUR COUNTRY IS IN," SAID THE STATEMENT ATTRIBUTED TO THE YOUNG OFFICERS.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN), MEANWHILE, ALSO SAID ITS ATTACKS IN SAN SALVADOR EARLY WEDNESDAY WERE TO PROTEST THE LACK OF PROGRESS IN PROSECUTING MEMBERS OF THE MILITARY FOR THE MASSACRE OF THE PRIESTS.

BUT ANALYSTS SAID THE RENEWED FIGHTING APPEARED INTENDED AS A SHOW OF FORCE AHEAD OF U.N.-MEDIATED PEACE [WORD INDISTINCT] THIS MONTH, WHICH SEEK TO END A DECADE-LONG CIVIL WAR THAT HAS LEFT MORE THAN 70,000 DEAD.

IN THE FIGHTING EARLY WEDNESDAY, AT LEAST SEVEN GOVERNMENT TROOPS WERE KILLED AND 18 WERE WOUNDED, AN ARMY SPOKESMAN SAID. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES IN THE ATTACK ON THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE AND MR. CRISTIANI WAS NOT AT HOME AT THE TIME, THE SPOKESMAN SAID.

THE REBELS RETREATED TO THEIR STRONGHOLD AROUND THE SAN SALVADOR VOLCANO JUST NORTH OF THE CAPITAL AFTER THE ATTACKS IN UPPER CLASS NEIGHBORHOODS.

THE UNITED STATES SHARPLY CONDEMNED THE ATTACKS AND CALLED ON THE REBELS TO DEMONSTRATE THEY CAN WORK WITH THE GOVERNMENT OF EL SALVADOR TO END THE WAR.

"WE CONDEMN THE OUTRAGEOUS VIOLENCE BY THE FMLN," SAID STATE DEPARTMENT SPOKESMAN RICHARD BOUCHER. "THE FMLN HAS DEMONSTRATED THAT IT CAN DESTROY THE SALVADORAN ECONOMY AND KILL SALVADORAN CITIZENS."

DEV-MUC3-1261 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] THE YOUNG MILITARY OFFICERS WHO HAVE CIRCULATED A 5-PAGE LETTER OUTLINING THEIR VIEWS CONTEND THAT THE VIOLATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND THE NEGLECT IN CORRECTING WRONGDOINGS COMMITTED BY THE U.S. ADVISERS AND EMBASSY ARE THE MAIN PROBLEMS KEEPING THE COUNTRY MIRED IN WAR. THE OFFICERS ADD THAT THEY DO NOT TRUST THE CURRENT U.S. AMBASSADOR, WHOM THEY ACCUSE OF BETRAYING TRUTH AND JUSTICE IN THE COUNTRY IN CONNECTION WITH THE LATEST DEVELOPMENTS.

THE OFFICERS NOTE THE DIPLOMAT'S POSITION REGARDING THE CASE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS; HOW HE FAILED TO DENOUNCE A COLONEL WHO ACCIDENTALLY DISCOVERED THE CULPRITS AND HOW, LATELY, HE HAS WARNED THE HIGH COMMAND ABOUT SOME INFORMATION THAT WAS GOING TO BE MADE PUBLIC BY A U.S. NETWORK.

THE LETTER, WHICH WAS RELEASED DURING THE LAST FEW HOURS AND IS DATED 1 MAY, EXPRESSES THE YOUNG ARMY OFFICERS SUPPORT FOR COLONEL SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ, AFTER THE DEFENSE MINISTRY, WITH THE BLESSING OF SEVERAL COMMANDERS, DECIDED TO TAKE THE CURRENT PRESIDENT OF CEL [LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE] TO TASK PUBLICLY. IN THEIR LETTER, THE OFFICERS STATE THAT THEY AGREE COMPLETELY WITH THE FORMER MILITARY COMMANDER REGARDING WHICH SENIOR OFFICERS GIVE ORDERS TO JUNIOR OFFICERS.

WE ARE OBEDIENT AND NONCONFRONTATIONAL AND THAT IS WHY WE CONTINUE TO OBEY ORDERS FROM SUPERIORS, BUT THIS MUST STOP WHEN THE VIOLATION OF PRINCIPLES AND RIGHTS ARE INVOLVED, SAYS THE CALL FROM THE YOUNG OFFICERS TO THE PRESIDENT AND HIGH COMMAND.

THE EXTENSIVE DOCUMENT DELIVERED TO THE MEDIA BY THE SELF-STYLED DOMINGO MONTERROSA LIVES MOVEMENT SAYS THAT TWO OF THE OFFICERS IT MENTIONS WERE REMOVED FROM THEIR POSTS IN THE MILITARY ORDER OF 30 APRIL. THE YOUNG OFFICERS PROVIDE NO FURTHER DETAILS BUT MAKE SOME ALLUSIONS TO MISSIONS CONDUCTED WHILE THEY DID THEIR DUTIES.

THE DOCUMENT SAYS THAT SOME OF THE SENIOR OFFICERS WHO ARE OBTAINING MONEY ILLEGALLY MUST STOP AND MENTIONS THE NAMES OF FORMER MILITARY OFFICERS WHO ARE NOW LIVING AND ENJOYING THEIR WEALTH IN EXILE. THE DOCUMENT SAYS THAT THE CONTRADICTION RAISED BY THE ABOVE IS THE LUCK OF SOME GENTLEMEN OFFICERS WHO, AT THE END OF THEIR SERVICE, LIVE ABROAD AND ENJOY THEIR POSITIONS WITHOUT ANY QUESTION. THE DOCUMENT ASKS HOW SOME FORMER OFFICERS ARE ABLE TO LIVE SO WELL WHEN WE KNOW THEY GRADUATED FROM OUR MILITARY ALMA MATER.

THE CASE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS IS ALSO EXAMINED IN THEIR LETTER. THEY NOTE THAT THE IDENTITY OF THE CULPRITS BECAME KNOWN SHORTLY AFTER THE MURDER, BUT SOME OF THE SENIOR OFFICERS WITHHELD IMPORTANT INFORMATION FROM THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND ARMED FORCES COMMANDER IN CHIEF. A FEW HOURS AFTER THE MURDER, MANY OF US SUSPECTED WHAT HAD HAPPENED. WE, THE YOUNG OFFICERS, HAVE THE BEST SOURCES OF INFORMATION AND MANY OF US DID NOT THINK THAT THE CASE WOULD HAVE ANY MAJOR IMPACT BECAUSE THE ACTIVISM OF THE PRIESTS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL FRONT [FMLN] WAS WELL-KNOWN. HOWEVER, THERE WAS CAUSE FOR CONCERN ALMOST IMMEDIATELY AFTER THE CRIME BECAME KNOWN. THE PRIESTS' MURDER WAS DESCRIBED AS IRRATIONAL AND SENSELESS BECAUSE OPEN FIGHTING AGAINST TERRORISM IS ONE THING AND THE STRUGGLE AGAINST THE IDEOLOGISTS IS ANOTHER.

THE ATTORNEY GENERAL OF THE REPUBLIC MADE UP THE STORY ABOUT THE FMLN HATCHING A PLOT TO MURDER THE SAN SALVADOR BISHOPS IN AN ATTEMPT TO DISTRACT ATTENTION FROM THE KILLING OF THE PRIESTS, THE LETTER SAYS. THE ATTORNEY GENERAL COULD NOT BE REACHED FOR COMMENT ABOUT THIS. AS STATED BY THE YOUNG OFFICERS, WHEN THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S IDEA WAS RAISED, IT WAS POINTED OUT THAT IT WOULD NOT BE CREDIBLE. THIS WAS TREATED AS A CHILDISH AND ILLOGICAL WAY OUT. THE GROSS LIE MADE UP BY THE ATTORNEY GENERAL WAS NEVER CONSIDERED A PRACTICAL OPTION, THE DOCUMENT SAYS.

THE SELF-STYLED DOMINGO MONTERROSA LIVES MOVEMENT HAS SENT THE LETTER TO PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, THE ASSEMBLY, AND THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND, ASKING THEM TO MEASURE THE CONSEQUENCES OF THE POSITION ASSUMED BY THE U.S. EMBASSY AND VARIOUS SECTORS OF THE COUNTRY REGARDING MILITARY AID. THE YOUNG OFFICERS HAVE TAKEN THE NAME OF THE CHARISMATIC OFFICER WHO DIED WHEN HIS HELICOPTER WAS ATTACKED WHILE FLYING OVER THE AREA OF CACAOPERA, IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY'S EASTERN REGION.

IN THEIR EXTENSIVE DOCUMENT THE YOUNG OFFICERS ASK PRESIDENT CRISTINI NOT TO BE DECEIVED BY REPORTS FROM THE HIGH COMMAND MEMBERS OF LA TANDONA [NAME GIVEN TO 1966 GRADUATES OF CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY].

DEV-MUC3-1262 (BOEING)

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [TEXT] SAN SALVADOR DOMESTIC SERVICE IN SPANISH AT 1808 GMT ON 3 MAY BEGINS TO BROADCAST LIVE A NEWS CONFERENCE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI FROM THE PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE IN SAN SALVADOR.

CRISTIANI BEGINS BY SAYING THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS LOOKING TO PUT TOGETHER A VIABLE AGENDA FOR ITS UPCOMING MEETING WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] SO THAT SOME HEADWAY CAN BE MADE IN THE TALKS. HE ADDS: "FROM WHAT WE CAN FORESEE, WE HOPE THE DIRECT MEETINGS WILL BEGIN IN A WEEK AND A HALF, OR SOMEWHERE AROUND THERE. THAT IS WHEN WE THINK THEY COULD START.... IN GENERAL TERMS, WE DO BELIEVE PROGRESS WILL BE MADE AND THAT WE WILL ADVANCE QUITE RAPIDLY."

IN RESPONSE TO A QUESTION REGARDING A LETTER FROM AN UNNAMED GROUP OF YOUNG MILITARY OFFICERS ADVOCATING A PURGE OF THE MILITARY AND SUPPORTING CRITICISMS MADE BY FORMER ARMY COLONEL SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ, CRISTIANI SAYS: "I HAVE NEVER BELIEVED ANONYMOUS LETTERS OR NOTES. THE FACT THAT IT IS ANONYMOUS CASTS SOME DOUBT ON THE INTENTIONS BEHIND IT OR ABOUT THE GROUP THAT COULD BE SENDING IT. POSING AS YOUNG OFFICERS IS EASY TO DO. THIS COULD HAVE COME FROM THE FMLN -- MAKING AN ISSUE OF ALL THAT THEY HAVE BEEN TALKING ABOUT -- OR FROM ANY OTHER GROUP."

REGARDING THE FMLN COMMUNIQUE ON THE REBELS' RECENT MILITARY OFFENSIVE, HE STATES: "I READ THE COMMUNIQUE AND I HONESTLY BELIEVE THAT IT IS ONE OF THE MOST RIDICULOUS FMLN COMMUNIQUES I HAVE SEEN TO DATE.... I FEEL THAT THIS WAS A WAY TO SEEK NOTORIETY THROUGH THE NEWS. THIS COULD BE ONE OF THE REASONS. THE OTHER REASON COULD BE THAT THEY ARE HAVING PROBLEMS AMONG THEMSELVES.... SOME OF THEM VIEW THE DIALOGUE AS SOMETHING SERIOUS WHILE OTHERS DO NOT, AND IT COULD BE THAT THESE PROBLEMS ARE RESULTING IN THESE IRRATIONAL ADVENTURES BY THE FMLN."

TURNING TO RECENT U.S. GOVERNMENT CRITICISM CHARGING SLOWNESS IN THE HANDLING OF THE INVESTIGATION AND PROSECUTION OF THOSE INVOLVED IN THE JESUIT MURDER CASE, CRISTIANI SAYS: "AS CHIEF EXECUTIVE, I CANNOT SPEED UP, SLOW DOWN, OR ALTER THE JUDGE'S DECISIONS. IN NO DEMOCRACY CAN THE CHIEF EXECUTIVE DICTATE ORDERS TO THE JUDICIAL BRANCH. THE SAME HAPPENS IN THE UNITED STATES AS IN ANY OTHER DEMOCRATIC COUNTRY. I BELIEVE THAT AS FAR AS WE HAVE BEEN ABLE TO SEE -- ALTHOUGH THERE IS MUCH URGENCY IN SEEING THIS TRIAL COMPLETED; THERE ARE GREAT EXPECTATIONS -- THAT THE JUDGE IS DUTY BOUND TO CONTINUE WITH THE JUDICIAL PROCEDURES STIPULATED BY SALVADORAN LAW." HE POINTS OUT THAT THE PROSECUTION OF GENERAL NORIEGA IN THE UNITED STATES IS ALSO TAKING A LONG TIME.

REGARDING A REPORTED FMLN ATTACK ON HIS RESIDENCE IN SAN SALVADOR YESTERDAY, CRISTIANI SAYS: "I DO NOT KNOW WHO THE PERSON WAS WHO REPORTED AN ATTACK ON THE PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE, EITHER THE OFFICIAL OR THE PRIVATE ONE. NEITHER OF THEM WAS ATTACKED, THOUGH THERE COULD HAVE BEEN SOME INFORMATION THAT SUCH AN ATTACK WAS EXPECTED. AN FMLN COLUMN WAS DISPERSED IN AREAS CLOSE TO THE TWO RESIDENCES."

QUESTIONED ABOUT THE EFFECTS ON THE GOVERNMENT OF A POSSIBLE CUT IN U.S. GOVERNMENT AID TO EL SALVADOR, CRISTIANI RESPONDS: "WELL, I THINK THAT FIRST OF ALL, THE EFFECTS OF A REDUCTION OR CUT OF AID WOULD BE TWOFOLD. FIRST, I THINK IT WOULD BE A NEGATIVE SIGNAL FOR THE FMLN AND FOR THE OBJECTIVE OF TRYING TO FIND AN END TO THE CONFLICT THROUGH THE DIALOGUE PROCESS THAT HAS BEEN STARTED; AND THAT A CUT IN AID MIGHT BE ANALYZED BY SOME OF THE MEMBERS, OR ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE FMLN, AS MEANING A WEAKENING OF THE GOVERNMENT AND ITS DEFENSE AND THAT, THEREFORE, THEIR MILITARY VICTORY IS NOW CLOSER. AND IT WOULD MAKE IT A LOT MORE DIFFICULT TO END THE CONFLICT IN A SHORT WHILE THROUGH A POLITICAL DIALOGUE. SECOND, OBVIOUSLY THE GOVERNMENT HAS THE RESPONSIBILITY TO DEFEND THE INSTITUTIONS, THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS OF THE COUNTRY, AND WILL NOT STANDBY WITH A WEAKENED DEFENSE. THEREFORE, THIS MEANS REALLOCATING RESOURCES THAT MIGHT BE USED FOR OTHER TYPES OF PROGRAMS -- SOCIAL PROGRAMS, ECONOMIC OR POLITICAL PROGRAMS -- ... FOR DEFENSE PURPOSES."

RETURNING THE JESUITS MURDER CASE, CRISTIANI IS ASKED IF THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND IS BEING INVESTIGATED. HE SAYS: "FIRST OF ALL I WOULD SAY THAT THE HIGH COMMAND -- AND THIS IS JUST MY OWN POINT OF VIEW -- WAS INSTRUMENTAL IN MAKING IT POSSIBLE TO CARRY OUT THE INVESTIGATION. THE HIGH COMMAND MADE IT POSSIBLE FOR THE INVESTIGATION TO BE WITHIN THE ARMED FORCES, AN INVESTIGATION THAT HAS NO PRECEDENT IN THE PAST WITH RESPECT TO INVESTIGATING MILITARY UNITS.... IT WOULD BE VERY DIFFICULT TO BELIEVE THAT BY SUPPORTING THE INVESTIGATION AND OPENING UP THE ARMED FORCES SO THAT THEY CAN BE INVESTIGATED IN THIS CASE, THEY WOULD HAVE DONE SO IF THERE WERE SOME INVOLVEMENT ON THEIR PART."

FURTHER AS AVAILABLE.

DEV-MUC3-1263 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [MODERATOR] JUAN AMADEO CABRERA FROM LA NOTICIA.

[CABRERA] MR. PRESIDENT, IF THE COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE YOUNG MILITARY OFFICERS IS TRUE, IF IT IS TRUE THAT THEY ARE MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES, WHAT IS THE OUTLOOK FOR THE ARMED FORCES AND FOR YOUR GOVERNMENT?

[CRISTIANI] I BELIEVE SOME SPECULATION WOULD BE REQUIRED. I BELIEVE THAT AS AN ANONYMOUS LETTER, IT CANNOT BE GIVEN THE CREDIT IT DESERVES, IF IT WAS WRITTEN BY SOMEONE WHO IS COMPLETELY RESPONSIBLE. IN THIS REGARD, I REPEAT THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN WILLING TO CONDUCT A PROCESS OF PROFESSIONALIZING AND MODERNIZING. THEY ARE TRYING TO IMPROVE THEIR INSTITUTION AS MUCH AS POSSIBLE.

[MODERATOR] LUISA MELGAR FROM TELEPRENSA.

[MELGAR] MR. PRESIDENT, YESTERDAY THE FMLN CARRIED OUT DIFFERENT ARMED ACTIONS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY. A COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND JUSTIFIED THE ACTIONS BECAUSE OF ALLEGED HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS, REPRESSION, AND LACK OF SECURITY FOR CIVILIANS. HOW DO YOU VIEW THESE ACTIONS JUST WHEN THE TALKS ARE ABOUT TO BEGIN?

[CRISTIANI] I READ THE COMMUNIQUE AND I HONESTLY BELIEVE THAT IT IS ONE OF THE MOST RIDICULOUS FMLN COMMUNIQUES I HAVE SEEN TO DATE. IT IS A JUSTIFICATION THAT IS NOT VERY JUSTIFIABLE, I WOULD SAY. I BELIEVE THE EVENTS ON 1 MAY IN THE MORNING CAN CLEARLY BE UNDERSTOOD. ALL GROUPS WISHING TO PARTICIPATE WERE ABLE TO MARCH PEACEFULLY. THEIR FREEDOMS ARE NOT BEING REPRESSED. I IMAGINE YOU HAVE ALL HEARD AND SEEN WHAT THEY SAID AND DID AND THERE WERE NO PROBLEMS. I FEEL THAT THIS WAS A WAY TO SEEK NOTORIETY THROUGH THE NEWS. THIS COULD BE ONE OF THE REASONS. THE OTHER REASON COULD BE THAT THEY ARE HAVING PROBLEMS AMONG THEMSELVES. WE HAVE INFORMATION TELLING US THAT THERE ARE DIFFERENCES AMONG THE DIFFERENT GROUPS. SOME OF THEM VIEW THE DIALOGUE AS SOMETHING SERIOUS, WHILE OTHERS DO NOT, AND IT COULD BE THAT THESE PROBLEMS ARE RESULTING IN THESE IRRATIONAL ADVENTURES BY THE FMLN. I FEEL THAT AT THIS STAGE OF THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, THEIR ACTIONS ARE COMPLETELY UNJUSTIFIABLE. THAT IS NOT ALL. THEY HAVE EVEN VIOLATED WHAT THEY HAVE CALLED UNILATERAL GESTURES MADE IN THE PAST. THIS SHOWS THE LACK OF SERIOUSNESS AND SINCERITY IN ALL OF THEM, OR SOME OF THEM, CONCERNING THE OBJECTIVES WE ARE TRYING TO ACHIEVE WITH THE DIALOGUE PROCESS.

[CRISTIANI] GUILLERMO PENATE FROM EL DIARIO DE HOY.

[PENATE] THERE ARE SOME LABOR GROUPS THAT WANT TO BE INCLUDED IN THE DELEGATION THAT WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE TALKS WITH THE FMLN. COULD THIS NOT BE SOME SORT OF DISADVANTAGE FOR THE OFFICIAL DELEGATION, BECAUSE THE OPPOSITE GROUPS COULD GAIN STRENGTH?

[CRISTIANI] I THINK THAT IS TRUE. SOME GROUPS HAVE ASKED TO BE INCLUDED IN THE DELEGATION. I BELIEVE THE PARTICIPATION OF THE DIFFERENT GROUPS IS STIPULATED IN THE GENEVA AGREEMENTS. WE HAVE ALREADY EXPLAINED HOW THE GOVERNMENT CAN ALLOW FOR THE PARTICIPATION OF POLITICAL AND SOCIAL SECTORS OF THE COUNTRY. WE ARE NOT GOING TO CHANGE THE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION, WHICH IS COMPRISED OF GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS FOR THE MOST PART. I BELIEVE THAT THE PARTICIPATION OF MEMBERS OF SOCIAL ORGANIZATIONS HAS ALREADY BEEN EXPLAINED IN THE PAST.

[MODERATOR] RAUL BELTRAN FROM RADIO CADENA YSKL.

[BELTRAN] MR. PRESIDENT, OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS WE HAVE LEARNED ABOUT THE OFFICIAL STATEMENT ISSUED BY THE COMMANDERS OF THE VARIOUS GARRISONS AND THE HIGH COMMAND. SINCE YOU ARE THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES, DO YOU SUPPORT THE DOCUMENT THAT WAS PUBLISHED, WHICH CONDEMNED THE STATEMENTS MADE BY COL. SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ?

[CRISTIANI] CONCERNING THAT SITUATION, I HAVE SAID THAT SEVERAL PEOPLE HAVE MADE STATEMENTS, NOT JUST ONE. THERE HAS BEEN PUBLIC SPECULATION AS TO WHAT MAY HAVE HAPPENED IN THE ASSASSINATIONS OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS AND THE OTHER TWO PEOPLE AND THAT IS NOT RIGHT. IF SOMEONE HAS ANY INFORMATION TO CONTRIBUTE, AND IF THAT SOMEONE IS REALLY INTERESTED IN THE PROGRESS OF JUSTICE IN THIS COUNTRY, HE SHOULD GO TO THE JUDGE TO GIVE HIM THE INFORMATION. HE SHOULD NOT CONTINUE TO SPECULATE IN PUBLIC, BECAUSE IT CONFUSES PEOPLE AND IT OBSTRUCTS THE JUDICIAL PROCESS.

I WOULD LIKE TO MENTION, FOR EXAMPLE, THAT NOT LONG AGO A DELEGATION OF SPANISH LEGAL EXPERTS VISITED THE COUNTRY AND THEY WERE PLEASED TO SEE HOW THE 4TH CRIMINAL JUDGE WAS HANDLING THE JUDICIAL PROCESS, AS OPPOSED TO OTHER REPORTS THAT HAVE BEEN RELEASED IN THE UNITED STATES. HOWEVER, I BELIEVE THAT NO ONE SHOULD SPECULATE IN PUBLIC AS TO WHAT MAY HAVE HAPPENED. IF SOMEONE HAS INFORMATION OR EVIDENCE, HE SHOULD GO TO THE JUDGE, OTHERWISE THERE WILL BE CONFUSION. IN THAT REGARD, I BELIEVE THAT THE ARMED FORCES COMMANDERS' REJECTION OF COL. OCHOA'S STATEMENTS IS JUST THAT. IN MANY OF THE STATEMENTS THEY WROTE -- I DID NOT PARTICIPATE IN DRAFTING THE STATEMENT -- THEY MENTIONED THAT THEY ARE WILLING TO SUPPORT AND STRENGTHEN THE JUDICIAL PROCESS, BUT THEY CANNOT COME OUT IN PUBLIC WITH SPECULATION BECAUSE THEY WOULD ONLY CONFUSE PEOPLE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1264 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 MAY 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] HOWEVER, THE FMLN IDEA THAT THEY HAVE TO SHOW FORCE HERE, OR THERE, OR SOMEWHERE IS NOT LOGICAL. THE IMPORTANT POINT IS THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WANT TO LIVE IN PEACE AND TRANQUILITY. THEREFORE, IT MAKES NO DIFFERENCE THAT THEY MAY HAVE 1,000, 2,000, OR 100. THAT DOES NOT MATTER. I THINK THAT, WHETHER THEY HAVE A HIGH OR A LOW MORALE OR WHATEVER, WITH JUST 100 RADICALS THEY COULD KILL PEOPLE AND DESTROY SOURCES OF EMPLOYMENT. IN SUM, THEY CAUSE PANIC AND TERROR IN SOME HAMLETS. I BELIEVE THAT HAS TO BE STOPPED. IT IS NOT A MATTER OF WHO SHOWS FORCE AND WHO DOES NOT. REGARDLESS OF THE DEMONSTRATIONS OF FORCE THE FMLN MAY CARRY OUT, WE STILL BELIEVE THAT, IN THE LONG RUN, THE MILITARY VICTORY BY THE GOVERNMENT FORCES AND THE GOVERNMENT IS POSSIBLE, BECAUSE THEY HAVE A STRONG MORAL SUPPORT. THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN ELECTED BY THE PEOPLE AND HAS THE SUPPORT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE PEOPLE SUPPORT THE SYSTEM AND THE GOVERNMENT, NO MATTER WHO IS HEADING IT, NOT JUST A PARTICULAR INDIVIDUAL. HOWEVER, THAT IS NOT THE POINT. WE DO NOT WANT THIS CONFLICT TO LAST 10 YEARS LONGER, WITH MORE BLOODSHED. THEREFORE, WE ARE SEARCHING FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION BECAUSE WE BELIEVE IN IT, NOT BECAUSE IT SUITS US BECAUSE THEY ARE STRONGER OR NOT STRONGER.

[MODERATOR] JAMES LOHMAN.

[LOHMAN] MR. PRESIDENT, WITH THE REDUCTION IN THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S MILITARY AID, HAS YOUR GOVERNMENT CONSIDERED THE POSSIBILITY OF SEEKING MILITARY AID IN OTHER COUNTRIES ON THIS CONTINENT OR FROM OTHER PARTS OF THE WORLD? FOR EXAMPLE, WE KNOW THAT A COUNTRY LIKE ISRAEL HAS GIVEN MILITARY AID TO CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES. HAVE YOU CONSIDERED THAT POSSIBILITY?

[CRISTIANI] I CAN ONLY TELL YOU THAT, YES, CERTAINLY, THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC HAS THE DUTY OF DEFENDING THE SYSTEM AND THE SALVADORAN DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS, AND -- REGARDLESS OF WHAT MAY HAPPEN, AND WE HOPE THAT WILL NOT OCCUR -- IF THAT HAPPENS, WE WILL ALWAYS HAVE TO SEEK ALTERNATE RESOURCES FOR THE DEFENSE OF THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS. A FEW DAYS AGO I LISTENED TO STATEMENTS BY SOME POLITICIANS AND MEMBERS OF OTHER SECTORS, WHO COMPLAINED BECAUSE I SAID: WE HAVE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF DEFENDING THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS, WE HAVE TO FIND THE RESOURCES, AND THERE ARE OTHER ALTERNATIVES TO GET RESOURCES FOR THE NATIONAL DEFENSE. THOSE POLITICIANS SAID IT WOULD BE DISASTROUS TO AFFECT SOCIAL PROGRAMS TO HELP THE NEEDY. THAT IS ACTUALLY WHAT THOSE POLITICIANS SHOULD THINK ABOUT WHEN THEY ASK FOR A REDUCTION IN AID. I BELIEVE THAT IS SOMETHING THE GOVERNMENT CANNOT NEGLECT. THE GOVERNMENT MUST DEFEND THE SYSTEM FROM POSSIBLE ATTACKS -- THROUGH VIOLENCE TO REACH POWER -- WHICH HAS BEEN TERMED BY CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS AND BY MANY COUNTRIES THROUGHOUT THE WORLD AS ILLEGAL.

[LOHMAN] HAVE YOU CONSIDERED [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] ALL I CAN TELL YOU IS THAT WE ARE TAKING INTO CONSIDERATION SOME ALTERNATIVES. HOWEVER, WE ARE NOT GOING TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS DEFENSELESS.

[MODERATOR] WE WILL NOW HAVE QUESTIONS IN ENGLISH. TOM GIBBS FROM THE BBC.

[GIBBS] WHAT WOULD BE THE EFFECT OF CUTTING U.S. MILITARY AID? AND ALSO IT SEEMS THAT THE DEMOCRATS IN CONGRESS PUT AS A HIGH PRIORITY FOR THE CONTINUATION OF AID THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] JESUITS' CASE, AND ALSO THE CLEANING UP OF THE OFFICERS CORPS OF THE ARMY, OR CHANGES IN THE MILITARY. HOW INCONVENIENT WOULD IT BE TO YOUR GOVERNMENT, OR HOW [WORDS INDISTINCT] IT WOULD BE TO YOUR GOVERNMENT TO BE ABLE TO [WORDS INDISTINCT]?

[CRISTIANI] WELL, I THINK THAT, FIRST OF ALL, THE EFFECT OF THE REDUCTION OR CUT OF AID WOULD BE TWOFOLD. ON THE FIRST HAND, I THINK IT WOULD BE A NEGATIVE SIGNAL FOR THE FMLN AND FOR THE OBJECTIVE OF TRYING TO FIND AN END TO THE CONFLICT THROUGH THE DIALOGUE PROCESS THAT HAS BEEN STARTED, AND THAT A CUT IN AID MIGHT BE ANALYZED BY SOME OF THE MEMBERS, OR ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE FMLN, AS MEANING A WEAKENING OF THE GOVERNMENT AND ITS DEFENSE AND THAT, THEREFORE, THEIR MILITARY VICTORY IS NOW CLOSER. AND IT WOULD MAKE IT A LOT MORE DIFFICULT TO END THE CONFLICT IN A SHORT WHILE THROUGH A POLITICAL DIALOGUE. SECONDLY, OBVIOUSLY THE GOVERNMENT HAS THE RESPONSIBILITY TO DEFEND THE INSTITUTIONS, THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS OF THE COUNTRY, AND WILL NOT STAND BY WITH A WEAKENED DEFENSE. THEREFORE, THIS MEANS REALLOCATING RESOURCES THAT MIGHT BE USED FOR OTHER TYPES OF PROGRAMS -- SOCIAL PROGRAMS, ECONOMIC, OR POLITICAL PROGRAMS THAT THE GOVERNMENT CAN HAVE ACCESS TO, AND OBVIOUSLY TO REALLOCATE RESOURCES FOR DEFENSE PURPOSES. THUS, IT WOULD HAVE A TWOFOLD IMPACT IF THAT WAS THE CASE.

ON THE OTHER HAND, I THINK THAT THE JUDICIAL PROCESS IN THE CASE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS IS ONGOING. IT WILL BE DIFFICULT FOR ME [WORDS INDISTINCT] TO THINK THAT BEFORE IT HAS ENDED, THAT THERE IS PREJUDGEMENT ON WHAT THE RESULTS WOULD BE. I THINK THAT THE JUDGE, AS I SAID EARLIER, HAS RECEIVED AT LEAST THE VISITS OF MANY PEOPLE. JUST RECENTLY A GROUP OF LAWYERS FROM SPAIN CAME IN AND ANALYZED THE CASE, AND WERE VERY PLEASED WITH THE WAY THE JUDGE WAS HANDLING THE CASE, ACCORDING, OBVIOUSLY, TO SALVADORAN LAW. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1266 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 4 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE, COPREFA] [TEXT] THE MILITARY HIGH COMMAND EMPHATICALLY REJECTS THE JUNIOR OFFICER'S STATEMENTS, CONSIDERED A TYPE OF GRAY PROPOGANDA, BECAUSE NO PERSON OR GROUP OF PERSONS HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THEM. THE STATEMENTS ARE BIASED IN FAVOR OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN].

ON 10 JANUARY 1981 A SERIES OF SIMILARLY ANONYMOUS LETTERS AND STATEMENTS WERE CIRCULATED. THE MILITARY INTELLIGENCE LEARNED THAT THE LETTERS WERE PART OF A STRATEGY IMPLEMENTED BY FORMER CAPTAIN FRANCISCO SANDOVAL, ALONG WITH OTHER MEMBERS OF THE SALVADORAN SUBVERSION.

IN ADDITION, SOMETHING SIMILAR HAPPENED IN NOVEMBER 1989, BUT THIS TIME IT WAS DONE BY A HIGH-RANKING MEMBER OF THE NATIONAL UNION OF SALVADORAN WORKERS, WHO CLAIMED THAT HE HAD RECEIVED A COMMUNIQUE FROM JUNIOR OFFICERS ON A NUMBER OF IRREGULARITIES THAT WERE REPORTEDLY OCCURRING WITHIN THE ARMED FORCES.

THE FMLN TERRORIST GROUPS LAUNCHED OFFENSIVES ON BOTH OCCASIONS. ACCORDING TO THEIR GOALS, THE FINAL TASK WAS TO SEIZE POWER BY FORCE AND BY ALL MEANS, EVEN IF THEY HAD TO SACRIFICE THE LIVES OF MANY SALVADORAN CIVILIANS AND SEVERELY DAMAGE HOUSES AND THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMIC INFRASTRUCTURE.

THE ARMED FORCES ARE AWARE OF THEIR HIGH LEVEL OF PROFESSIONALISM AND THEIR OWN INSTITUTIONAL ETHICS AND PHILOSOPHY AS DEMANDED BY THE CONSTITUTION OF THE REPUBLIC AND REITERATE THAT THEIR MISSION WILL ALWAYS BE TO DEFEND THE NATION'S SOVEREIGNTY AND TO PROTECT EACH AND EVERY ONE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S LIFE AND INTERESTS.

THEREFORE, IT IS USELESS TO TRY TO UNDERMINE THE ARMED FORCES' MORALE AND TO CONFUSE AND DIVIDE ALL THE MEMBERS COMPRISING THE ARMED FORCES THROUGH GROUNDLESS COMMUNIQUES WHICH ARE INTENDED TO CREATE FALSE EXPECTATIONS FOR THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC.

DEV-MUC3-1267 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [INTERVIEW WITH MNR'S UNGO BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] I HAVE ANOTHER QUESTION. A FEW MOMENTS AGO, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI TERMED THE MOST RIDICULOUS COMMUNIQUE HE HAD EVER HEARD FROM THE FMLN THE ONE IN WHICH THEY JUSTIFIED YESTERDAY'S MILITARY ACTIONS. HE TERMED THEM PROPAGANDA-ORIENTED. WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE NEGOTIATIONS, HOW DO YOU VIEW THIS?

[UNGO] IN MY OPINION, THE FMLN COMMUNIQUE HAS ASPECTS THAT ARE INTERESTING AND OTHERS WHICH I THINK ARE NOT VALID. THE TIME AND OPPORTUNITY OF THAT ACTION IS AMBIVALENT. I THINK IT HAS NEGATIVE EFFECTS, AS WELL AS POSITIVE EFFECTS FOR THEM. THERE IS ALWAYS THE FAMOUS VICIOUS CIRCLE WHEREIN IF THE FMLN CEASES TO ACT MILITARILY, IT IS BAD FOR THE FMLN BECAUSE IT SHOWS A SIGN OF WEAKNESS. IF IT ACTS MILITARILY IT IS ALSO BAD, BECAUSE IT SHOWS THAT IT DOES NOT WANT PEACE. IN THIS SENSE, I THINK THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT IT HAS EXHIBITED A SHOW OF FORCE, THAT ITS ACTIONS HAVE BEEN STRICTLY PROPAGANDA-ORIENTED OR WITH PROPAGANDA OBJECTIVES. IT DOES NOT CEASE TO CREATE DIFFICULT CONDITIONS THAT GENERATE A NEGATIVE REACTION ON THE OTHER'S PART, IF THEY WANT TO SIT DOWN AND TRY TO EASE CONFRONTATIONS AS MUCH AS POSSIBLE AND SEEK AN AGREEMENT AS MUCH AS POSSIBLE. I BELIEVE, AS I TOLD PRESIDENT CRISTIANI ON THE TELEPHONE YESTERDAY WHEN WE SPOKE OF OTHER THINGS BUT TOUCHED ON THIS TOPIC, THAT I UPHOLD THE GOVERNMENT'S THESIS. WE HAVE ALWAYS CRITICIZED THE FACT THAT WHEN NEGATIVE THINGS OCCUR, THEY ARE INVOKED TO SUSPEND A PROCESS WHICH IN OUR OPINION SHOULD BE CONTINUOUS. WE HAVE ALWAYS UPHELD THE CONTINUITY OF THE DIALOGUE. THE GOVERNMENT CRITICIZED THE FMLN WHEN ON TWO OCCASIONS IT SUSPENDED THE DIALOGUE DUE TO TERRORIST ACTIONS ON THE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT OR SECURITY CORPS. THE DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION PROCESS HAS SUFFERED AS A RESULT OF THIS. I BELIEVE THAT IN THIS CASE THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD TAKE ITS OWN MEDICINE. IT SHOULD MAINTAIN THE CONTINUITY OF THE PROCESS AND NOT USE AS A PRETEXT THE FMLN MILITARY ACTIONS TO TRY TO SEEK WAYS OF CONDITIONING OR PERTURBING A PROCESS OF DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION, WHICH INVOLVES NOT ONLY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN, BUT THE POLITICAL PARTIES AND SOCIAL FORCES AS WELL.

[REPORTER] DR. UNGO, IN THAT SENSE THE GOVERNMENT HAD ANNOUNCED THROUGH PRESIDENT CRISTIANI THAT THE DIALOGUE WOULD BE RESUMED ON 3 MAY. SUBSEQUENTLY, THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL'S ENVOY ANNOUNCED THAT IT WOULD BE THE FIRST PART OF MAY. DON'T YOU THINK THAT TOO MUCH TIME IS BEING SPENT WITHOUT BEING ABLE TO AGREE ON SUMMIT MEETINGS THAT WILL PERMIT SECURING AGREEMENTS?

[UNGO] I HAVE A VERY POSITIVE ANALYSIS OF HOW THE PROCESS IS DEVELOPING IN THIS FIRST PHASE, JUDGING BY THE CONDUCT ON THE PART OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN. I THINK THERE HAS BEEN A DELAY, BUT I THINK IT IS A DELAY THAT IMPROVES THE POSSIBILITIES AND CONDITIONS. APPARENTLY THE TIMES WERE MARKED BY HASTE AND PRECIPITATION FOR THE FMLN TO PRESENT A PROPOSAL. ALSO, THERE WAS A VERY SHORT TIME FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO PREPARE ITS RESPONSE AND HOLD A BILATERAL MEETING LATER. AT THE SAME TIME, IT LEFT A VERY NARROW MARGIN OF INFLUENCE TO THE POLITICAL PARTIES AND SOCIAL ORGANIZATIONS.

PRESIDENT CRISTIANI HIMSELF CONVENED THE POLITICAL PARTIES TO EXPLAIN TO THEM WHAT THE SITUATION WAS AND HOW HE VIEWED THE ROLE OF THE PARTIES. THE PARTIES HAVE THEIR OWN CONCEPT OF THEIR ROLE AND HAVE BEEN WORKING ARDUOUSLY AND RESPONSIBLY. IN TWO WEEKS THEY HELD FOUR PROLONGED, HIGH-LEVEL MEETINGS, TWO PER WEEK. WE WANT TO DO THE SAME THING WITH THE FMLN. I BELIEVE THAT THE PERIOD OF TWO TO THREE WEEKS TO ONE MONTH, SINCE THE GENEVA AGREEMENT WAS SIGNED, HAS BEEN POSITIVE. IF WE HAD HURRIED THINGS UP, PERHAPS THE POSSIBILITY OF ACHIEVING RESULTS WOULD HAVE BEEN AFFECTED. WHAT HAPPENS IS THAT ALL OF THIS GIVES WAY TO SOMEWHAT PESSIMISTIC EVALUATIONS, BECAUSE THE CONFIDENTIALITY WAS VIOLATED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI. I HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT THESE THINGS ARE PART OF A PRIVATE, CONFIDENTIAL AIDE-MEMOIRE THAT WAS AGREED TO IN GENEVA BETWEEN THE TWO TOP LEADERS OF THE FMLN AND THE GOVERNMENT DELEGATION WITH UN SECRETARY GENERAL PEREZ DE CUELLAR'S REPRESENTATIVE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1268 (BOEING)

GUATEMALA CITY, 5 MAY 90 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE REPORTED THAT A GUATEMALAN CARGO PLANE OWNED BY THE TRASLADOS COMPANY CRASHED THIS AFTERNOON ON TOP OF SEVERAL HOUSES IN NORTHERN GUATEMALA CITY, CAUSING AN UNDETERMINED NUMBER OF DEAD AND WOUNDED.

CIVIL AERONAUTICS PERSONNEL CONFIRMED TO ACAN - EFE THAT THE THREE CREW MEMBERS OF THE DC-6 WERE U.S. CITIZENS WHO HAD BEEN HIRED TO FLY THE PLANE TO MIAMI.

SOURCES FROM THE MUNICIPAL FIRE DEPARTMENT SAID THE PLANE DESTROYED 12 HOUSES. THE NUMBER OF DEAD AND WOUNDED ARE STILL UNKNOWN.

ACCORDING TO THE INITIAL REPORTS, THE ACCIDENT OCCURRED SHORTLY AFTER THE PLANE TOOK OFF FROM THE LA AURORA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT, AND APPARENTLY WAS DUE TO THE LOSS OF AN ENGINE.

FIRE DEPARTMENT SPOKESMAN HAROLDO JUAREZ SAID THERE HAVE BEEN EXPLOSIONS IN THE DRAINAGE SYSTEM BECAUSE OF THE GASES THAT HAD ACCUMULATED FROM THE FUEL SPILLED BY THE PLANE.

ACCORDING TO THE SPOKESMAN, THE PILOT TRIED TO LAND ON AN EMPTY LOT BUT HE WAS UNABLE TO DO SO AND CRASHED IN THE HOUSING AREA.

JUAREZ SAID THE EXACT NUMBER OF DEAD AND WOUNDED IS UNKNOWN BUT UNOFFICIALLY THERE ARE REPORTS OF 15 DEAD AND MORE THAN 20 INJURED.

DEV-MUC3-1269 (BOEING)

GUATEMALA CITY, 6 MAY 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] CIVIL AERONAUTICS AUTHORITIES HAVE REPORTED THAT FOUR PLANE ACCIDENTS HAVE BROUGHT DESTRUCTION AND DEATH TO GUATEMALA IN LESS THAN 24 HOURS.

THE MOST SERIOUS ACCIDENT TOOK PLACE IN A NEIGHBORHOOD JUST OUTSIDE THE CAPITAL WHEN A CARGO PLANE THAT HAD JUST TAKEN OFF FROM THE LA AURORA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT CRASHED INTO A RESIDENTIAL AREA DESTROYING SEVERAL HOMES AND KILLING 17 PEOPLE INCLUDING CHILDREN.

A SECOND ACCIDENT OCCURRED WHEN A SMALL PLANE HAD TO MAKE AN EMERGENCY LANDING IN RABINAL, IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY. IN THIS ACCIDENT THE PILOT WAS INJURED.

IN A THIRD ACCIDENT, A PLANE THAT HAD MANEUVERED ON THE RUNWAY OF THE LA AURORA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT TURNED OVER AND CRASHED. THE PLANE WAS SEVERELY DAMAGED AND THE PILOT AND MEMBERS OF THE CREW WERE INJURED.

IN A FOURTH ACCIDENT, A HELICOPTER OF THE PRESIDENTIAL STAFF HAD TECHNICAL PROBLEMS AND WAS FORCED TO MAKE AN EMERGENCY LANDING.

DETAILS OF THE LAST THREE ACCIDENTS WERE NOT YET KNOWN. THESE ACCIDENTS HAVE MADE THIS THE WORST DAY FOR GUATEMALAN AVIATION IN RECENT YEARS.

DEV-MUC3-1271 (BOEING)

LIMA, 7 MAY 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THE POLICE CONFIRMED TODAY THAT PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE ALBERTO FUJIMORI ESCAPED A DYNAMITE ATTACK PERPETRATED BY A SHINING PATH CELL ON 6 MAY. ACCORDING TO THE POLICE, THE DYNAMITE CHARGE WAS DETONATED ON THE ROUTE FOLLOWED BY FUJIMORI'S MOTORCADE IN THE DISTRICT CAPITAL OF SAN JUAN DE LURIGANCHO.

THE ATTACKERS LEFT FLIERS IDENTIFYING THEMSELVES AS MEMBERS OF THE MOVEMENT FOR THE PEOPLE'S DEFENSE, A SHINING PATH FRONT ORGANIZATION. DORA VILCHEZ, A 26-YEAR-OLD WOMAN, WAS INJURED IN THE ATTACK.

FUJIMORI, WHO WILL CONTEND WITH WRITER MARIO VARGAS LLOSA IN A RUNOFF ELECTION DURING THE FIRST HALF OF JUNE, WAS ONLY INFORMED OF THE ATTACK BY HIS AIDES AFTER THE POLICE HAD TIGHTENED THEIR SECURITY AROUND HIM. THE "CHANGE 90" LEADER MINIMIZED THE ATTACK AND CONTINUED HIS SCHEDULED ACTIVITIES.

THE POLICE SAID THAT A SHINING PATH GROUP MANAGED TO INFILTRATE A CROWD OF DEMONSTRATORS AND SET OFF THE DYNAMITE CHARGE ON THE ROUTE FOLLOWED BY FUJIMORI'S MOTORCADE, NEAR A LOCAL MARKET, ON THE EASTERN SIDE OF LIMA.

VILCHEZ, WHO WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED, WAS HOSPITALIZED.

THE BOMB SQUAD UNIT (UDE) DEFUSED ANOTHER EXPLOSIVE DEVICE NEAR THE MARKET.

THE FLIERS DISSEMINATED BY THE TERRORISTS URGED THE PEOPLE NOT TO VOTE IN THE RUNOFF ELECTION. ONE OF THE FLIERS SAID: "NEITHER FUJIMORI NOR VARGAS LLOSA IS THE SOLUTION BECAUSE THEY BOTH REPRESENT THE RIGHT WING. LONG LIVE THE ARMED STRUGGLE. PCP.SL." EXPANSION UNKNOWN

DEV-MUC3-1272 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 8 MAY 90 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS WARNED TODAY THAT THE POSSIBLE REPLACEMENT OF GENERAL HUMBERTO LARIOS BY COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CURRENT CHIEF OF STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES, "WILL SERIOUSLY AFFECT THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS" WITH THE GOVERNMENT, WHICH WILL BE RESUMED THIS COMING 16 MAY IN VENEZUELA.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) RELEASED A COMMUNIQUE HERE TODAY ON THE CHANGE IN THE SALVADORAN MILITARY LEADERSHIP AS WELL AS THE POSSIBLE RETIREMENT OF DEPUTY DEFENSE MINISTER COLONEL ORLANDO ZEPEDA.

"THESE CHANGES WILL SERIOUSLY AFFECT THE CONCERTED CEASE-FIRE PROCESS, BECAUSE ONE CANNOT REACH AGREEMENTS BASED ON DEMOCRATIZATION WHILE IMPUNITY PREVAILS IN THE ARMY AND IT IS NOT SUBJECTED TO A THOROUGH PURGE," THE FMLN ADDED.

GEN LARIOS TOLD NEWSMEN YESTERDAY ABOUT HIS POSSIBLE REPLACEMENT BY COL EMILIO PONCE IN THE DEFENSE MINISTRY IS A CHANGE WHICH HE REGARDED AS "NATURAL."

"EVENTUALLY THERE MAY BE A CHANGE OF THAT SORT. IT IS A NATURAL AND ROUTINE CHANGE," THE DEFENSE MINISTER SAID WHEN ASKED ABOUT PERSISTENT RUMORS TO THIS EFFECT IN THAT PAST FEW DAYS IN EL SALVADOR.

COL PONCE, A MEMBER OF THE 1966 GRADUATION CLASS KNOWN AS "LA TANDONA," CURRENTLY HAS GREAT INFLUENCE AMONG THE ARMED FORCES OFFICERS. HE HAS HELD THE POST OF CHIEF OF STAFF SINCE THE MIDDLE OF LAST YEAR.

THE FMLN COMMUNIQUE STATED THAT PONCE'S REMOVAL FROM THE POST OF CHIEF OF STATE "WOULD BREAK THE CHAIN OF RESPONSIBILITY OF THE HIGH COMMAND IN THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS." THE JESUIT PRIESTS WERE ASSASSINATED ON 16 NOVEMBER BY ALLEGED ARMED FORCES MEMBERS, WHO WERE TURNED OVER TO JUDICIARY AUTHORITIES.

DEV-MUC3-1274 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 MAY 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] FIRST LADY OF THE NATION, MR. VICE PRESIDENT, YOUR EXCELLENCIES OF THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS, MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND, GENERALS, CHIEFS, OFFICERS, NON-COMMISSIONED OFFICERS, TROOPS, PUBLIC SECURITY POLICEMEN, AND ADMINISTRATIVE PERSONNEL, SALVADORAN PEOPLE:

WE HAVE GATHERED HERE, UNITED BY A SHARED FEELING OF PATRIOTISM, TO OFFER A TRIBUTE OF ADMIRATION AND APPRECIATION TO ALL OF THE MEMBERS OF OUR ARMED FORCES. WITHIN THE COMMEMORATIVE FRAMEWORK OF SOLDIERS DAY, FROM THE VERY DEPTH OF OUR HEARTS, WE FIRST OF ALL PAY HOMAGE OF UNDYDING GRATITUDE TO OUR SALVADORAN BROTHERS WHO, WEARING THE ARMED FORCES' UNIFORM, HAVE GIVEN THEIR LIVES TO DEFEND OUR DEAR FATHERLAND. WITH THEIR GENEROUS BLOOD THEY HAVE FERTILIZED THE PATH OF PEACE, DEMOCRACY, AND FREEDOM FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

WE PAY HOMAGE TO THE SOLDIERS KILLED IN COMBAT WHILE FULFILLING THE SACRED MISSION OF DEFENDING THE RPUBLIC'S SOVEREIGNTY AND INTEGRITY. IT IS WITH EMOTION THAT WE EVOKE THOSE BROTHERS WHO, STOICALLY CONFRONTING DANGER AND DEATH, GAVE THEIR LIVES SO THAT OUR COUNTRY WOULD HAVE A BETTER FUTURE, AND SO THAT PRESENT AND FUTURE GENERATIONS COULD BUILD A MORE HUMAN AND SOLIDARY SOCIETY.

WE PAY SPECIAL TRIBUTE TO ONE OF THOSE MEN WHO, IN THE FULL BLOOM OF YOUTH, HAS GONE ON TO FORM PART OF OUR ARMED FORCES' GLORIOUS HISTORY, WHO GAVE HIS LIFE FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. I AM REFERRING TO CAPTAIN JOSE ALFONSO CHAVEZ GARCIA, A WORTHY EXAMPLE OF DEVOTION TO SERVICE TO THE FATHERLAND. HIS MEMORY WILL ALWAYS BE A SOURCE OF INSPIRATION TO EVERY SALVADORAN SOLDIER WHO IS FIGHTING FOR OUR PEOPLE'S FREEDOM AND GLORY. AS OF TODAY, THE SPECIAL ANTI- TERRORIST COMMANDO, CEAT, WILL BEAR CAPT CHAVEZ' NAME IN JUST RECOGNITION OF HIS PROFESSIONALISM AND DEVOTION TO THE FATHERLAND'S SACRED VALUES.

WITH THESE SAME FEELINGS OF ADMIRATION AND AFFECTION, WE GREET THE MOTHERS, FATHERS, CHILDREN, BROTHERS, WIVES, AND RELATIVES OF OUR SOLDIERS, WHO IN FULFILLING THEIR DUTIES HAVE WRITTEN PAGES OF FEARLESSNESS AND COURAGE, THEREBY ENDLESSLY PROLONGING THEIR NOBLE EXAMPLES IN OUR PEOPLE'S CONSCIENCES.

AT THIS SOLDIERS DAY EVENT, IN MY CAPACITY AS PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND GENERAL COMMANDER OF THE ARMED FORCES, I STRONGLY EMBRACE ALL OF THE MEMBERS OF OUR ARMED INSTITUTION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1276 (BOEING)

LHASA (TIBET), 7 MAY 90 (LHASA TIBET TELEVISION NETWORK) -- [TEXT] ECUADORAN FOREIGN AFFAIRS MINISTER CORDOVEZ, MADAME CORDOVEZ, AND FOUR OTHER ECUADORAN OFFICIALS ARRIVED IN LLASA ON THE MORNING OF 5 MAY.

AT 1830 THE SAME DAY, PUQUANG, VICE CHAIRMAN OF THE TIBET AUTONOMOUS REGIONAL PEOPLE'S GOVERNMENT, MET WITH THE ECUADORAN VISITORS AT THE TIBETAN-STYLE MEETING ROOM AT THE HOLIDAY INN IN LHASA. IN A FRIENDLY ATMOSPHERE, VICE CHAIRMAN PUQUANG BRIEFED FOREIGN MINISTER CORDOVEZ ON TIBET'S AGRICULTURE, ANIMAL HUSBANDRY, INDUSTRY, ENERGY, AND COMMUNICATIONS; AND ESPECIALLY THE SUCCESSES TIBET HAS ACHIEVED IN VARIOUS FIELDS UNDER THE LEADERSHIP OF THE CENTRAL PEOPLE'S GOVERNMENT SINCE TIBET'S DEMOCRATIC REFORM.

ON BEHALF OF THE TIBETAN AUTONOMOUS REGIONAL PEOPLE'S GOVERNMENT, VICE CHAIRMAN PUQUANG PRESENTED GIFTS TO THE VISITORS. THEN, VICE CHAIRMAN PUQUANG HOSTED A DINNER IN HONOR OF THE ECUADORAN VISITORS.

MAKING HIS WELCOMING SPEECH, VICE CHAIRMAN PUQUANG SAID: YOUR EXCELLENCY MINISTER CORDOVEZ HAS VISITED CHINA MANY TIMES AND YOU HAVE CONTRIBUTED SIGNIFICANTLY TO THE DEVELOPMENT OF FRIENDLY RELATIONS BETWEEN CHINA AND ECUADOR AND THE PEOPLES OF THE TWO COUNTRIES. YOUR EXCELLENCY'S CURRENT VISIT TO TIBET WILL CERTAINLY ENABLE YOU TO UNDERSTAND CHINA BETTER.

VICE CHAIRMAN PUQUANG STRESSED: TIBET HAS ALWAYS BEEN CHINA'S SACRED TERRITORY SINCE THE MIDDLE OF THE 13TH CENTURY. IT IS A FACT ACKNOWLEDGED BY THE WHOLE WORLD THAT ALL PREVIOUS CENTRAL GOVERNMENTS EFFECTIVELY EXERCISED THEIR SOVEREIGNTY IN TIBET.

VICE CHAIRMAN PUQUANG ALSO SAID THAT, SINCE THE LIFTING THE MARTIAL LAW ORDER IN LHASA, TIBET'S SITUATION HAS BEEN STABLE, ITS PUBLIC ORDER HAS BEEN NORMAL, ITS ECONOMY HAS BEEN DEVELOPING STEADILY, AND THE PEOPLE HAS BEEN LIVING AND WORKING IN PEACE AND CONTENTMENT.

MAKING HIS EXTEMPORANTEOUSLY SPEECH AT THE DINNER, FOREIGN AFFAIRS MINISTER CORDOVEZ SAID: VISITING THE TIBETAN AUTONOMOUS REGION HAS BEEN MY DREAM FOR MANY YEARS. LIKE TIBET, ECUADOR IS A COUNTRY ON A PLATEAU. WHEN I SET FOOT IN BEAUTIFUL LHASA, I HAD THE FEELING THAT I HAD RETURNED TO MY HOMETOWN.

MINISTER CORDOVEZ WHOLEHEARTEDLY WISHED TIBET PROSPERITY IN ALL FIELDS AND THE TIBETAN PEOPLE HAPPINESS.

DEV-MUC3-1277 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 7 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [REPORT] [JULIO ERNESTO RODRIGUEZ] [TEXT] DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS STATED TODAY THAT THE OFFICERS WHO COULD SERVE AS WITNESSES IN THE CASE OF THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS ASSASSINATED AT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY ARE TAKING TRAINING COURSES ABROAD. HE DENIED THE OFFICERS LEFT FOR REASONS OTHER FOR THE STRICTLY MILITARY NEED OF TRAINING. IF THE JUDGE SO ASKS FOR IT, THEY MAY RETURN TO GIVE THEIR STATEMENT ON THE JESUITS' CASE, HE SAID. WHEN ASKED ABOUT THE LOSS OF THE REGISTRY RECORDING THE ENTRY AND DEPARTURE OF PERSONS FROM THE MILITARY ACADEMY, GEN. LARIOS SAID HE WAS NOT AWARE OF THIS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LARIOS] THE CADETS ARE NOW OUT OF THE COUNTRY. THIS IS IN LINE WITH A PROGRAM PLANNED WELL IN ADVANCE. CADETS OF CERTAIN CLASSES LEAVE TO CONDUCT STUDIES, CHIEFLY IN THE UNITED STATES. THIS IS NORMAL, AS IT CORRESPONDS TO A SCHEDULED PLAN. THEY WILL HAVE TO RETURN AT SOME POINT WHEN THEY CONCLUDE THEIR STUDIES IN THE UNITED STATES. THEN WE WILL HAVE THE TIME AND THE OPPORTUNITY TO CLARIFY ANY ASPECT OF THIS MATTER.

[REPORTER] COULD NOT THE JUDGE CALL THEM EARLIER?

[LARIOS] IF THE JUDGE DEEMS THEIR PRESENCE ADVISABLE, THEY MAY BE CALLED IMMEDIATELY.

[REPORTER] REFERRING TO THE ENTRY AND DEPARTURE REGISTRY OF THE DAY WHEN THE JESUITS WERE KILLED, HOW WILL THIS SITUATION END UP?

[LARIOS] SO FAR, I CANNOT COMMENT ON THE MATTER. I AM NOT AWARE OF THE SITUATION. WE HAVE TO SEE WHAT HAPPENED. [END RECORDING]

GEN. LARIOS FEELS THAT THE JESUITS' CASE HAS HAD A GREAT BEARING ON THE CONDITIONS PLACED ON THE MILITARY AID THE U.S. SENATE WILL APPROVE. THE MILITARY CHIEF REGRETTED IT IS NOT UP TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY TO SAY WHEN THE AID MUST BE CUT. THE U.S. LAWMAKERS HAVE THEIR MEANS AND CRITERIA TO DECIDE WHEN TO CUT AID, HE SAID REFERRING TO THE DECISION BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT. THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION HAS SAID IT WILL CUT MILITARY AID BY 50 PERCENT IF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DOES NOT TRY THE PERSONS GUILTY OF MURDERING SIX JESUITS AND TWO OTHERS. THE AID WILL BE CUT IF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT DOES NOT TRY TO OBTAIN SPECIFIC AGREEMENTS IN THE NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE GUERRILLAS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LARIOS] WE ALL KNOW WHAT WILL HAPPEN REGARDING THE MILITARY AID. UNFORTUNATELY, WE MUST ADMIT WE CANNOT DECIDE THE TERMS UNDER WHICH WE WILL RECEIVE THAT MILITARY AID. THEY MUST DO THAT. THEY WILL DECIDE WHEN AND BY HOW MUCH THAT AID WILL BE CUT.

[REPORTER] GENERAL, DO YOU THINK THAT THE 60 MINUTES PROGRAM IN WHICH COL.OCHOA PEREZ PARTICIPATED WAS INFLUENTIAL IN THE DECISION TO ASK THE THE U.S. HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES TO CUT THE AID?

[LARIOS] I THINK THAT IT HAS DEFINITELY BEEN INFLUENTIAL. WE MUST UNDOUBTEDLY RECOGNIZE THIS. NEVERTHELESS, THAT IS NOT ALL. I BELIEVE THAT THE SITUATION EXISTED EVEN BEFORE THE 60 MINUTES PROGRAM WAS BROADCAST. THEREFORE, I BELIEVE THAT THE PROBLEM EXISTED REGARDLESS OF WHAT WAS SAID DURING THE 60 MINUTES PROGRAM, AND WE WERE [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] WHAT WERE THE ISSUES WHICH HAD ALREADY DETERMINED THIS? WHAT COULD THEY BE?

[LARIOS] THAT IS REALLY NOTHING NEW. THE JESUITS' CASE HAS BEEN, LET US SAY, THE DECISIVE FACTOR FOR DECIDING ONE THING OR ANOTHER IN THE U.S. CONGRESS, SENATE, AND ADMINISTRATION ABOUT THE MILITARY AID. THAT IS BASICALLY THE ISSUE. [END RECORDING]

GEN. LARIOS ALSO TALKED ABOUT POSSIBLE CHANGES WHICH MIGHT OCCUR IN THE ARMY LEADERSHIP. RECENT RUMORS INDICATE THAT HE MIGHT LEAVE HIS POST AS DEFENSE MINISTER, AND THAT CHANGES MIGHT OCCUR WITHIN THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND. HE SAID THAT HE DOES NOT RULE OUT THE POSSIBILITY THAT THESE CHANGES MAY OCCUR, BUT HE TERMED THEM AS ROUTINE.

REFERRING TO A U.S. TELEVISION PROGRAM WHICH IMPLIED COLONEL ORLANDO ZEPEDA'S PARTICIPATION IN THE JESUITS' CASE, THE DEFENSE MINISTER SAID HE DOES NOT BELIEVE THIS TYPE OF INFORMATION BECAUSE THE DEPUTY DEFENSE MINISTER IS A COLLEAGUE WHO ONLY HANDLES ADMINISTRATIVE ISSUES WITHIN THE ARMY.

DEV-MUC3-1278 (BOEING)

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [TEXT] ACTING ON INFORMATION OBTAINED DURING QUESTIONING OF POLICEMEN INVOLVED IN THE LOCAL COCAINE TRADE, BRAZILIAN POLICE AGENTS SEIZED A LAB IN WESTERN MATO GROSSO DO SUL STATE IN EARLY APRIL. IN ADDITION, BROADCASTS AIRED IN THE STATE CAPITAL OF CORUMBA DENOUNCING THE DRUG PROBLEM AND POLICE INVOLVEMENT HAVE MADE A LOCAL RADIO STATION A TARGET OF BOMB THREATS FROM NARCOTRAFFICKERS, ACCORDING TO REPORTS IN THE BRAZILIAN PRESS. SUBSEQUENTLY, PRESIDENT FERNANDO COLLOR DE MELLO HAS LAUNCHED AN ANTIDRUG CAMPAIGN.

ON 7 APRIL FEDERAL POLICE OF MATO GROSSO DO SUL STATE RAIDED A WELL-EQUIPPED COCAINE REFINING LABORATORY ON A RANCH IN AQUIDAUANA, THE RIO DE JANEIRO DAILY O GLOBO OF 8 APRIL REPORTS. THE LAB WAS THE FIFTH UNCOVERED IN THE STATE IN THE LAST 14 MONTHS. AGENTS SEIZED 50 KILOS OF PROCESSED COCAINE, ONE OF THE LARGEST SEIZURES IN BRAZIL THIS YEAR, AND MORE THAN 100 LITERS OF ETHER AND ACETONE. TWENTY HEAVILY ARMED TRAFFICKERS WERE ARRESTED. WITH INADEQUATE POLICE STRENGTH AND BORDERING BOTH BOLIVIA AND PARAGUAY, THE STATE IS CONSIDERED ONE OF THE MAIN ROUTES FOR THE DRUG RINGS THAT SUPPLY COCAINE TO BRAZIL'S PRINCIPAL URBAN CENTERS, PARTICULARLY RIO AND SAO PAULO. THE TRAFFICKERS ALSO HAVE CONNECTIONS ABROAD.

THE LABORATORY IN AQUIDAUANA WAS DISCOVERED AS A RESULT OF THE RECENT ARREST OF EIGHT CIVILIAN POLICE DETECTIVES, TWO FEDERAL POLICEMEN, AND FOUR HIGHWAY POLICEMEN INVOLVED IN A NARCOTICS RING, CONTINUES O GLOBO. DURING QUESTIONING, THEY PROVIDED INFORMATION THAT LED TO THE OTHER MEMBERS OF THE RING, INCLUDING A BOLIVIAN CHEMIST IN AQUIDAUANA. THE RING WAS HEADED BY A MATO GROSSO DO SUL BUSINESSMAN AND A POLITICIAN WHO FINANCED THE TRAFFICKING ACTIVITIES AND PROVIDED COVER; NEITHER MAN WAS IDENTIFIED BY NAME IN THE REPORT. ACCORDING TO FEDERAL AGENTS, THE COCAINE PASTE WAS BROUGHT FROM BOLIVIA BY FISHERMEN AND CANOERS HIRED ON THE BRAZILIAN- BOLIVIAN BORDER, AND WAS PROCESSED AND DISTRIBUTED IN AQUIDAUANA.

O GLOBO TERMS THE RAID A "REAL CLEAN-UP" IN THE CIVILIAN, MILITARY, AND FEDERAL POLICE DEPARTMENTS. THE FIRST SUCH ACTION WAS TAKEN IN LATE 1989 WHEN FEDERAL POLICE ARRESTED 22 POLICEMEN. O GLOBO OF 2 APRIL CITES THE ARREST OF SIX MILITARY POLICEMEN CAUGHT IN THE ACT OF DISTRIBUTING COCAINE IN CAMPO GRANDE, MATO GROSSO DO SUL STATE, ADDING THAT THE RING INCLUDED MORE THAN 20 MILITARY POLICEMEN. THE RINGLEADER WAS OLDINEY FREIRE, AN ATTORNEY ARRESTED IN MARCH 1989 AND A CLOSE ASSOCIATE OF RANCHER CAMBARALAMAIA DE SOUSA. PRIOR TO HIS ARREST IN JUNE 1988, CAMBARALAMAIA CONTROLLED COCAINE TRAFFICKING IN A LARGE PORTION OF MATO GROSSO USING THE COCHABAMBA, BOLIVIA ROUTE. HE ALSO SUPPLIED 300 KILOS OF PURE COCAINE MONTHLY TO SAO PAULO, RIO DE JANEIRO, AND ESPIRITO SANTO.

RIO DE JANEIRO DAILY JORNAL DO BRASIL NOTES ON 17 APRIL THAT THE FEDERAL POLICE DEPARTMENT (DPF) IS INVESTIGATING CHARGES THAT FEDERAL POLICE ARE INVOLVED IN DRUG SMUGGLING AND TRAFFICKING IN CORUMBA AND LADARIO. TRAFFICKING IN THE REGION HAS INCREASED STEADILY IN RECENT YEARS DUE TO THE PROXIMITY TO BOLIVIAN TOWNS INCLUDED IN THE ROUTE USED BY INTERNATIONAL TRAFFICKING RINGS, ACCORDING TO THE PAPER. ACKNOWLEDGING THAT THERE HAVE BEEN SERIOUS PROBLEMS WITH THE FEDERAL POLICE IN MATO GROSSO DO SUL, DPF LEGAL COORDINATOR MARIO CASSIANO DUTRA SAID THAT IN FEBRUARY ALONE, FOUR INVESTIGATIONS WERE OPENED INTO CHARGES OF POLICE INVOLVEMENT IN DRUG AND ARMS TRAFFICKING AND BRIBERY, AN ADDITIONAL 12 WERE CURRENTLY IN PROGRESS, AND ANOTHER FIVE ONLY NEEDED DOCUMENTS IN ORDER TO BE CONCLUDED.

TO COMBAT THE GROWING NARCOTICS PROBLEM IN THE STATE CAPITAL OF CORUMBA, ON 11 APRIL LOCAL STATION RADIO CLUBE DE CORUMBA LAUNCHED AN ANTIDRUG CAMPAIGN. IT DEVOTED AN HOUR OF ITS REGULAR PROGRAM "PUBLIC DEBATE" TO AN EXPOSE OF DRUG DISTRIBUTION POINTS IN THE CITY AND THE COMPLICITY OF FEDERAL POLICE, MILITARY POLICE, AND CIVILIAN POLICE INVESTIGATORS WITH NARCOTRAFFICKERS. ACCORDING TO O GLOBO OF 12 APRIL, PROGRAM MODERATOR ARMANDO AMORIM ANACHE IDENTIFIED 21 COCAINE DISTRIBUTION POINTS AS WELL AS POLICEMEN AND THE TRAFFICKERS WHO SUPPLIED THEM IN EXCHANGE FOR PROTECTION.

AFTER THE PROGRAM, ANACHE RECEIVED FOUR THREATENING PHONE CALLS, INCLUDING A BOMB THREAT AGAINST THE BUILDING HOUSING THE RADIO STATION, O GLOBO OF 14 APRIL REPORTS. HE RECEIVED WIDESPREAD PUBLIC SUPPORT WHEN HE BROADCAST THOSE THREATS. RADIO CLUBE RECEIVED LETTERS ALERTING POLICE TO THE USE OF CHILDREN WHO PICK UP DRUGS FROM BOLIVIAN WOMEN AT THE RAILROAD STATION. A MOTHERS' PROTEST PARADE WAS PLANNED, AND 850 LOCAL BUSINESSMEN RESOLVED TO CLOSE THEIR DOORS FOR ONE DAY AS A SYMBOLIC PROTEST AGAINST THE TRAFFICKING SITUATION IN CORUMBA. ON 18 APRIL, THE STATION RECEIVED SIX BOMB THREATS FROM COCAINE TRAFFICKERS WHO ALSO THREATENED TO BOMB ITS SISTER STATION RADIO INDEPENDENTE DE AQUIDAUANA, O GLOBO OF 19 APRIL REPORTS.

WEARING A YELLOW T-SHIRT WITH THE SLOGAN "DRUGS: OUT OF HERE," PRESIDENT FERNANDO COLLOR DE MELLO LAUNCHED AN ANTIDRUG CAMPAIGN, O ESTADO DE SAO PAULO OF 29 APRIL REPORTED IN A FRONT-PAGE PHOTO WITH ACCOMPANYING INSIDE-PAGE ARTICLE. COLLOR THEN DONATED THE T-SHIRT TO THE FEDERAL POLICE FOR AN AUCTION TO RAISE FUNDS FOR EQUIPMENT, PARTICULARLY FOR MONITORING THE BORDER AREAS. THE MOTHERS OF CORUMBA ARE CONDUCTING THAT AUCTION, IN WHICH THE MINIMUM BID WILL BE 100,000 CRUZEIROS. COLLOR IS SEEKING THE PARTICIPATION OF THE ENTIRE SOCIETY. HE IS NOT INTERESTED IN JUST A HEALTH MINISTRY SPONSORED PROGRAM, O ESTADO REPORTS.

DEV-MUC3-1279 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 10 MAY 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN SUPREME COURT TODAY DECLARED UNCONSTITUTIONAL THE REGISTRATION OF FIVE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES FOR THE UPCOMING 27 MAY ELECTIONS.

THE MEASURE ESPECIALLY AFFECTS ANTONIO NAVARRO WOLFF, CANDIDATE OF THE FORMER 19 APRIL (M-19) GUERRILLA MOVEMENT, WHO REPLACED CARLOS PIZARRO LEON-GOMEZ, WHO WAS ASSASSINATED LAST MONTH WHILE HE WAS ABOARD A FLIGHT, AS M-19 PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.

THE SUPREME COURT, WHICH HAS PRONOUNCED ITSELF ON THE DECREES AND LAWS PROMULGATED BY THE LEGISLATIVE AND EXECUTIVE BRANCHES, DECLARED UNCONSTITUTIONAL A DECREE ISSUED BY THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS WHICH ELIMINATED THE QUALIFICATIONS FOR PERSONS TO REGISTER AS PRESIDENTIAL CANDDIDATES. THE DECREE WAS ISSUED UNDER THE STATE OF SIEGE THAT HAS EXISTED FOR THE PAST SIX YEARS.

THE GOVERNMENT DECREE WAS ISSUED TO FAVOR PIZARRO LEON-GOMEZ, WHO ENTERED THE PRESIDENTIAL RACE AFTER A PEACE PROCESS WHEREBY THE M-19 DEMOBILIZED AND ABANDONED THE ARMED STRUGGLE.

ALSO AFFECTED ARE CANDIDATES GUILLERMO ALEMAN, POPULAR SINGER AND CUMBIA COMPOSER MARIO GARENA, JAIRO RODRIGUEZ LEON, AND HENRY FARFAN SILVA, WHO HAD ALREADY RESIGNED, ALTHOUGH NONE OF THEM HAD ANY CHANCE OF WINNING.

ACCORDING TO THE SUPREME COURT, THE STATE OF SIEGE MUST ONLY BE CONSIDERED WHEN ISSUING DECREES DEALING WITH THE RESTORING OF PUBLIC ORDER, WHICH DOES NOT CONTEMPLATE PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS.

THE COLOMBIAN LAWS DEMAND THAT A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE MUST BE OR HAS BEEN A PARLIAMENTARIAN, UNIVERSITY PROFESSOR, AMBASSADOR, OR ATTORNEY GENERAL, AND HAS BEEN A PROFESSIONAL FOR AT LEAST FIVE YEARS.

NONETHELESS, THE SUPREME COURT'S DECISION IS NOT RETROACTIVE AND THE CANDIDACIES WILL BE WITHDRAWN ONLY IF THEY ARE OFFICIALLY CHALLENGED.

DEV-MUC3-1280 (BOEING)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 10 MAY 90 (LA ESTRELLA DE PANAMA) -- [STATEMENT] [PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA CITY] [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY SALUTES THE HONORABLE FOREIGN MINISTRY AND IN REFERENCE TO NOTE NO. A.J.122 FROM THAT MINISTRY IS PLEASED TO ANNOUNCE THAT WE HAVE DULY ACKNOWLEDGED NOTE DPG 1794 OF 30 APRIL 1990 FROM THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE, THROUGH WHICH THIS EMBASSY HAS BEEN INFORMED THAT OUR REFUGEE GONZALO GONZALEZ RIVERA IS ACCUSED OF BEING THE MASTERMIND OF CHILD MARCOS ALBERTO RODRIGUEZ JUSTINES' MURDER ACCORDING TO CANCIO CIACCI TASON'S STATEMENTS.

IN THIS REGARD, THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY REITERATES THAT, THROUGH NOTE NO.5-20-M/002 DATED 8 JANUARY 1990, IT NOTIFIED THE PANAMANIAN FOREIGN MINISTRY THAT DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM HAD BEEN GRANTED TO 12 PERSONS WHO CAME TO THIS MISSION'S RESIDENCE, INCLUDING FORMER DEFENSE FORCES MAJOR GONZALO GONZALEZ RIVERA, AND REQUESTED THAT SAFE-CONDUCTS BE GRANTED FOR THEM TO TRAVEL ABROAD. WE MIGHT STRESS THAT SUCH GRANTING OF ASYLUM AND REQUESTING SAFE-CONDUCTS, AS WAS INDICATED IN THIS EMBASSY'S NOTE NO.5-20-/M-027 DATED 2 MARCH 1990, WAS BASED ON THE QUALIFICATION GRANTED TO THIS EMBASSY AS THE STATE GRANTING THE ASYLUM ACCORDING TO THE CONVENTION ON DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM SIGNED IN CARACAS IN MARCH 1954. THEREFORE, THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT CANNOT TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION ANY ACTIONS OF WHICH THE REFUGEE MAY BE ACCUSED, OR ANY LEGAL SITUATION THAT MAY PREVAIL AFTER THE SUBJECT HAS BEEN GRANTED ASYLUM.

HOWEVER, AND WITHOUT GOING AGAINST WHAT HAS BEEN PREVIOUSLY STATED, THE REFUGEE GONZALO GONZALEZ IS WILLING TO RENDER TESTIMONY BEFORE AN AUTHORIZED LEGAL OFFICIAL SO AS TO CLARIFY HIS SITUATION. THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY WILL ALLOW THAT OFFICIAL TO ENTER THE PREMISES OF THE EMBASSY FOR THIS PURPOSE.

AT THIS TIME, THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY, BASED ON THE CLEAR DISPOSITIONS OF THE CARACAS CONVENTION ON DIPLOMATIC ASYLUM -- THE INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENT IN EFFECT BETWEEN PANAMA AND PERU -- REITERATES ONCE AGAIN THE REQUEST FOR A SAFE-CONDUCT FOR THE AFOREMENTIONED REFUGEE.

THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY AVAILS ITSELF OF THIS OPPORTUNITY TO REAFFIRM ITS HIGHEST AND MOST DISTINGUISHED CONSIDERATION TO THE HONORABLE FOREIGN MINISTRY.

PANAMA, 7 MAY 1990

DEV-MUC3-1281 (BOEING)

BRIDGETOWN (BARBADOS), 13 MAY 90 (CANA) -- [TEXT] ST. JOHN'S, ANTIGUA, MAY 13, CANA -- BRITISH LAWYER LOUIS BLOM COOPER WAS PREPARING TO HEAD BACK TO LONDON SUNDAY AFTER DISCUSSIONS HERE ON A JUDICIAL INQUIRY INTO A 1989 ARMS SHIPMENT THROUGH ANTIGUA AND BARBUDA. THE QUEEN'S COUNSEL [QC] ARRIVED HERE FOR TALKS WITH GOVERNOR GENERAL SIR WILFRED JACOBS AND ATTORNEY GENERAL FORDE ON THE ILLEGAL ARMS SHIPMENT THAT ENDED UP IN THE HANDS OF COLOMBIAN DRUG DEALERS. THE PROBE, SAID CANARADIO, WILL BEGIN IN TWO MONTHS.

IN IDENTIFYING THE BRITON TO HEAD THE INVESTIGATION, THE CABINET HERE DESCRIBED HIM AS A RESPECTED JURIST WITH EXPERIENCE IN CONDUCTING COMMISSIONS OF ENQUIRY. BLOM COOPER CONDUCTED A COMMISSION OF ENQUIRY INTO ARSON, CORRUPTION, AND OTHER RELATED MATTERS IN THE TURKS AND CAICOS ISLANDS IN 1986.

ISRAEL SAYS IT SOLD THE ARMS TO THE ANTIGUA GOVERNMENT, BUT ST. JOHN'S DENIES THIS. THE ISRAELIS HAVE IMPLICATED AN ANTIGUAN MINISTER, VERE BIRD JR. IN THE SCANDAL, BUT BIRD SAYS HE HAD NO LINKS WITH THE ARMS.

MEANWHILE, ISRAEL ON SUNDAY CALLED COLOMBIAN DIPLOMATIC SANCTIONS OVER THE SALES OF ISRAELI ARMS TO DRUG TRAFFICKERS UNJUSTIFIED AND SAID IT WAS WORKING TO END THE ROW. AFTER COLOMBIAN POLICE FOUND HUNDREDS OF ISRAELI-MADE GUNS ON THE FARM OF A DEAD DRUG BARON, BOGOTA SAID ON FRIDAY IT WAS REVOKING 1962 AND 1966 AGREEMENTS ALLOWING ISRAELIS TO VISIT WITHOUT VISAS.

"WE REGRET THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT DECISION, WHICH WE THINK IS NEITHER RIGHT NOR JUSTIFIED. WE WILL REMAIN IN CONTACT WITH THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT IN ORDER TO RESOLVE THE ISSUE," AN ISRAELI FOREIGN MINISTRY SPOKESMAN TOLD REUTERS.

BOGOTA HAS ALSO ACCUSED ISRAELI AND BRITISH MERCENARIES OF HELPING DRUG TRAFFICKERS TRAIN PRIVATE ARMIES BLAMED FOR KILLING CIVILIANS IN NORTHERN COLOMBIA.

ANTIGUA AND BARBUDA'S FINANCE MINISTER JOHN ST. LUCE HAS MET WITH AND APPRISED THE HEADS OF THE COUNTRY'S TEN FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS OF GOVERNMENT'S PROGRESS IN SETTING UP THE JUDICIAL ENQUIRY, A STATEMENT FROM THE MINISTRY OF FINANCE SAID.

"I'M AWARE THAT ALL BANK MANAGERS NEED TO KEEP THEIR HEAD OFFICES AND, OR DIRECTORS ABREAST OF DEVELOPMENTS," ST. LUCE WAS QUOTED AS SAYING.

THE MINISTER ASKED THE BANKS TO "BE OBJECTIVE AND ALLOW THE JUDICIAL INQUIRY TO DETERMINE WHAT REALLY TRANSPIRED AND TO INFORM THE COUNTRY AS TO WHO ARE THE PERSONS INVOLVED." THE STATEMENT SAID THE BANK MANAGERS "EXPRESSED APPRECIATION FOR MR. ST. LUCE'S FRANKNESS AND THE OPPORTUNITY FOR DISCUSSION."

DEV-MUC3-1282 (BOEING)

QUITO, 14 MAY 90 (RADIO QUITO) -- [TEXT] ERNESTO BUENANO AND JAIME GALARZA, AUTHORS OF THE BOOKS PLANNED CRIME AND WHO KILLED ROLDOS, ARE SCHEDULED TO TESTIFY ON TUESDAY, 15 MAY, BEFORE THE CONGRESS' MULTIPARTY COMMISSION THAT IS INVESTIGATING THE DEATH OF FORMER PRESIDENT JAIME ROLDOS AGUILERA.

ERNESTO BUENANO SAID THAT IN TOMORROW'S MEETING HE WILL REVEAL THE NAMES OF THOSE INVOLVED IN JAIME ROLDOS AGUILERA'S DEATH, AND HE WILL PRESENT THE NECESSARY DOCUMENTS. HE ALSO REQUESTED THAT THE COMMISSION MEETING BE HELD IN PUBLIC.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUENANO] WE WANT TO THANK REPORTERS LIKE YOU BECAUSE WE HAVE BEEN STRUGGLING FOR EIGHT YEARS. WE HAVE DEDICATED EIGHT YEARS TO INVESTIGATING PRESIDENT ROLDOS' ACCIDENT, AND IT WAS NOT UNTIL TODAY THAT WE WERE SUMMONED TO TESTIFY BEFORE THE MULTIPARTY COMMISSION.

THIS STRUGGLE [WORDS INDISTINCT] IS NOTHING BUT THE RESULTS OF THE EFFORTS EXERTED MY MANY REPORTERS LIKE YOU, WHO HAVE HELPED US SO SELFLESSLY AND WHO HAVE NOT TRIED TO WITHHOLD THE INFORMATION. I BELIEVE THAT THIS DESERVES PRAISE AND I AM GRATEFUL FOR THIS.

IN REGARD TO WHAT WE WILL SAY TOMORROW, WE WILL PROVE TO THE COUNTRY THAT THE SO-CALLED HUMAN FAILURE [WHICH REPORTEDLY CAUSED THE ACCIDENT] IS A LIE. SECOND, WE WILL PROVE HOW THE CIA ACTS ON THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL; WHO ITS AGENTS ARE IN ECUADOR AND THEIR NAMES; AND WHAT CAUSED THE PRESIDENTIAL PLANE CRASH, WHICH WE HAVE TERMED A HOMICIDE. WE WILL TELL THE COUNTRY WHO THE MAIN POLITICAL CONSPIRATOR WAS AGAINST PRESIDENT ROLDOS. WE WILL PROVE THIS WITH DOCUMENTS BECAUSE WE WILL NOT BE TALKING ABOUT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE WILL REVEAL WHAT THIS POLITICAL CONSPIRATOR SAID BEFORE THE PRESIDENT'S DEATH AND AFTER HIS ASSASSINATION. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1283 (BOEING)

SANTIAGO, 15 MAY 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] AT LEAST SIX [AS HEARD] BOMBS EXPLODED IN VARIOUS PLACES IN THE CAPITAL DURING THE NIGHT. ONE INDIVIDUAL WAS INJURED. THE DAMAGES WERE DIFFERENT IN EACH CASE.

ONE OF THE MOST SERIOUS INCIDENTS OCCURRED IN THE AREA OF THE U.S. CONSULATE, IN FRONT OF FORESTAL PARK AND THE PURISIMA BRIDGE. HERE, UNIDENTIFIED INDIVIDUALS THREW A BOMB ONTO THE DIPLOMATIC PREMISES, INJURING A GUARD NAMED BARROSO, WHO WAS TAKEN TO THE CENTRAL HOSPITAL.

THE SERIES OF BOMBINGS BEGAN WHEN AN UNKNOWN NUMBER OF INDIVIDUALS THREW A BOMB INTO THE DEFENSE MINISTRY'S PARKING LOT, LOCATED OFF AN ALLEY BETWEEN ALAMEDA AND ALONSO VALLE STREETS. TWO CARS WERE DAMAGED BUT NO ONE WAS INJURED. OTHER BOMBS EXPLODED ON BANDERA AND ALAMEDA STREETS, AND NEAR AN AUSTRALIAN INTERNATIONAL TRANSPORT FIRM ON TARAPACA AND SANTA ROSA STREETS. ANOTHER BOMB EXPLODED ON THAT CORNER A FEW WEEKS AGO.

THE OTHER BOMBS DAMAGED AN ISRAELI COMMUNITY OFFICE AT SERRANO AND TARAPACA STREETS, A FRUIT EXPORTING FIRM AT ELIODORO YANEZ AND GENERAL SALVO STREETS IN PROVIDENCIA, AND A MORMON CHURCH AT PEDRO DE VALDIVIA AND OCURO STREETS.

DEV-MUC3-1284 (BOEING)

LIMA, 14 MAY 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE PERUVIAN POLICE, AND PARTS OF THE ARMY, HAVE RECEIVED ORDERS OF "STRICT CONFINEMENT TO BARRACKS" IN VIEW OF THE 17 MAY ANNIVERSARY OF THE TERRORIST ORGANIZATION SHINING PATH. THE ORGANIZATION HAS ANNOUNCED IT WILL CELEBRATE ITS 10TH ANNIVERSARY WITH AN INCREASE IN ARMED OPERATIONS.

PERUVIAN AUTHORITIES HAVE DISCOVERED THAT THE GROUP THAT REBELLED ON 17 MAY 1980 HAS DEVISED "A CELEBRATIONS PLAN" AND THAT IT INTENDS TO IMPLEMENT THE PLAN AS "A SIGN OF VICTORY" IN THE "STRUGGLE OF MOVEMENTS," AN IDEOLOGY INSPIRED IN MAO ZEDONG'S DOCTRINE.

ARMY PERSONNEL HAVE BEEN CONFINED TO BARRACKS SINCE THE NIGHT OF 12 MAY AND HAVE ALREADY PARTICIPATED ON JOINT OPERATIONS WITH THE POLICE TO ARREST 500 ALLEGED TERRORISTS.

IN LIMA, 8,000 POLICE AGENTS AND A SPECIAL ANTIEXPLOSIVES SQUAD LAUNCHED "A GIGANTIC OPERATION" OF "BLOCKADES AND SATURATION."

A POLICE SPOKESMAN TOLD EFE THAT THEY HAD ORDERS "TO CAREFULLY COMB THE NEW URBAN AREAS AND SEARCH FOR SUSPECTED CRIMINALS, ARMS, EXPLOSIVES, OR SUBVERSIVE MATERIAL."

ACCORDING TO THE SPOKESMAN, THE LIMA POLICE DEPARTMENT HEADED BY GENERAL OSVALDO DIAZ HAS ORDERS "TO WATCH ROADS ENTERING THE CITY, TO INSTALL EMERGENCY CHECK POINTS IN STRATEGIC LOCATIONS, AND TO REPORT ON ANYTHING UNUSUAL."

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, THE OPERATION WILL CONTINUE UNTIL AFTER THE RUNOFF ELECTION, WHICH IS EXPECTED TO BE HELD ON 10 JUNE.

THE POLICE HAVE LAUNCHED SIMILAR OPERATIONS IN REGIONS WHERE GUERRILLA ACTIVITY IS RAMPANT SUCH AS AYACUCHO, PUNO, HUANCAYO, AND HUANCAVELICA IN THE PERUVIAN CENTRAL HIGHLANDS. THESE REGIONS ARE ALL UNDER STATES OF EMERGENCY AND UNDER MILITARY CONTROL.

SHINING PATH, CONSIDERED ONE OF THE MOST IMPENETRABLE AND ORTHODOX ARMED MOVEMENTS IN LATIN AMERICA, BEGAN CELEBRATING ITS ANNIVERSARY IN LIMA LAST WEEK BY BURNING 11 STATE TRANSPORT COMPANY BUSES. THE BUSES WERE ATTACKED BY HOODED INDIVIDUALS THOUGHT TO BE SHINING PATH MILITANTS.

ON 11 MAY A BOMB DESTROYED A BUILDING OWNED BY THE FAMILY OF THE MAYOR OF LIMA. IN ANOTHER INCIDENT IN LIMA TODAY, POLICE CORPORAL OSWALDO PALOMINO, WHO SERVED IN AYACUCHO UNTIL A SHORT TIME AGO, WAS SHOT TO DEATH.

IN AYACUCHO, WHERE THE THE COMUNIST PARTY OF PERU -- "OFFICIAL" NAME OF SHINING PATH -- WAS BORN AND DEVELOPED, TWO PEOPLE WERE MURDERED, AND VARIOUS HOME-MADE BOMBS EXPLODED IN IN THE LAST 24 HOURS.

COUNCILMEN JUAN MANUEL GARABITO FROM PIURA, 1,100 KM NORTH OF LIMA, HAS ALSO BEEN SHOT TO DEATH. AUTHORITIES BLAMED SHINING PATH FOR THESE ATTACKS.

OBSERVERS OF THE PERUVIAN GUERRILLA MOVEMENT TOLD EFE THAT THE GROWING TIDE OF VIOLENCE ATTIBUTED TO SHINING PATH INDICATES THAT THE RADICAL, OR "RED" SECTOR, OF THE REBEL GROUP HAS TAKEN CONTROL OF THE ORGANIZATION.

ACCORDING TO THE SOURCES, TWO DIFFERENT FACTIONS WITHIN THE ORGANIZATION CLASHED OVER THE CELEBRATION OF THE GROUP'S ANNIVERSARY: THE YOUNGER AND RADICAL SECTORS FAVORED PURELY MILITARY OPERATIONS WHILE THE OLDER SECTOR, OR "BLACKS," FAVORED MORE POLITICAL AND HISTORIC ACTIVITIES.

SHINING PATH, WHICH OFFICIALLY OPERATES WITH APPROXIMATELY 5,000 ARMED MEN, HAS CAUSED THE DEATH OF 20,000 PEOPLE, INCLUDING 7,000 CIVILIANS, AND IT IS RESPONSIBLE FOR $17 BILLION IN DIRECT DAMAGES TO THE COUNTRY OVER ITS 10 YEAR HISTORY.

DEV-MUC3-1285 (BOEING)

GUATEMALA CITY, 16 MAY 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GOVERNMENT SOURCES ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT THREE POLICEMEN FROM THE GUATEMALA POLICE IDENTIFICATION DEPARTMENT WERE KILLED BY GUERRILLAS OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

POLICE SPOKESMEN SAID THAT POLICEMEN HUMBERTO DIAZ, A DRIVER; EDGAR CORONADO, A PHOTOGRAPHER; AND MARIO NAVARRO, A TECHNICAL SERGEANT, WERE AMBUSHED LAST NIGHT BY GUERRILLAS AT THE SAN ISIDRO FARM, 99 KM SOUTH OF THE CAPITAL.

THE POLICEMEN WERE ON THE WAY BACK FROM INVESTIGATING THE BURNING OF FIVE BUSES BY REBELS LAST WEEK AND WERE PRESUMABLY KILLED BY GUERRILLAS FROM THE REVOLUTIONARY ORGANIZATION OF THE PEOPLE IN ARMS (ORPA).

MEANWHILE, AMALIO ESCOBAR MONZON, 21, A MEMBER OF THE CIVIL SELF-DEFENSE PATROLS (PAC), WAS SHOT TO DEATH IN SAN PABLO, SAN MARCOS DEPARTMENT, IN THE NORTHWESTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY.

OFFICIAL SOURCES SAID THAT YESTERDAY ARMED MEN BROKE INTO MONZON'S RESIDENCE AND KILLED HIM.

IN SOLOLA DEPARTMENT, ALSO IN THE NORTHWESTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, OTHER INSURGENT GROUPS OCCUPIED STRETCHES OF HIGHWAY AND DEMANDED THAT TRAVELERS SURRENDER THEIR MONEY AND BELONGINGS.

THESE INSURGENT ACTIONS HAVE TAKEN PLACE LESS THAN TWO WEEKS BEFORE THE DIALOGUE THAT WILL BE HELD IN SPAIN BETWEEN GUERRILLA DELEGATES AND THE GUATEMALAN POLITICAL PARTIES TO AGREE ON A POSSIBLE CEASE-FIRE AND TO END 30 YEARS OF INTERNAL STRIFE.

THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY (URNG), WHICH INCLUDES THE ORPA AND OTHER INSURGENT MOVEMENTS, HAS ANNOUNCED THAT IT WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE TALKS BUT IN THE MEANTIME WILL CONTINUE ITS ARMED STRUGGLE.

DEV-MUC3-1286 (BOEING)

GUATEMALA CITY, 16 MAY 90 (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] TERRORIST ACTIONS WERE REPORTED TONIGHT SOUTH OF GUATEMALA CITY, A FEW HOURS AFTER A MASS TRANSIT BUS AND SEVERAL TIRES WERE BURNED IN OTHER PARTS OF THE CITY. TWO EXPLOSIONS TOOK PLACE IN A VACANT LOT AT APPROXIMATELY 2120 ON 15TH AVENUE AND 6TH STREET, ZONE 13. ACCORDING TO PERSONS WHO WERE NEARBY AT THAT TIME, SHOOTING WAS HEARD BEFORE THE EXPLOSIONS. A FEW MINUTES LATER, DEVICES, BELIEVED TO BE FRAGMENTATION GRENADES, WENT OFF. THE SHOCK WAVE CREATED BY THE BLAST SHATTERED THE WINDOWS OF HOUSE NUMBER 729 AND BUILDING 626, LOCATED IN FRONT OF THE VACANT LOT. THE EXPLOSION PROMPTED THE QUICK MOBILIZATION OF FIREMEN, POLICEMEN, AND SEVERAL ARMY ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS FROM LA AURORA MILITARY BASE.

SEVERAL MEMBERS OF THE SPECIAL ORANGE EXPLOSIVE SQUAD [UNIDAD NARANJA ESPECIAL DE LUCHA ANTIEXPLOSIVOS] ALSO ARRIVED TO DEFUSE ANOTHER DEVICE LEFT IN THE AREA. AT FIRST, IT WAS REPORTED THAT THE HOME CLOSE TO THE SITE OF THE EXPLOSION BELONGEDTO NEWSMAN ALVARO CONTRERAS VELEZ. WE WERE NOT ABLE TO VERIFY THIS REPORT. WE JUST LEARNED THAT A FAMILY BY THE NAME OF DIAZ NAVARRO LIVES THERE. THERE WERE NO FATALITIES, BUT DAMAGE TO THE BUILDINGS ARE REPORTED.

NEWSMAN CONTRERAS VELEZ, PRENSA LIBRE EDITOR AND AUTHOR OF THE "CACTO" COLUMN, CAME TO THE AREA TO OBSERVE THE DAMAGE. IT WAS UNOFFICIALLY ESTABLISHED THAT SOME GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS LIVE IN THIS SECTOR. MUNICIPAL FIREMEN HELPED POLICE AUTHORITIES IN COMBING THE AREA AFTER THE EXPLOSIONS.

THE RUMOR THAT A CAR BOMB EXPLODED ON 7TH AVENUE AND 7TH STREET, ZONE 9, CIRCULATED ALMOST SIMULTANEOUSLY. LATER, IT WAS LEARNED THAT THE EXPLOSION WAS CAUSED BY A BOOBY TRAP. THE AUTHORITIES ARE ON ALERT AND STEPPED UP OPERATIONS, A POLICE SPOKESMAN SAID.

AGAIN AT 2230 TONIGHT, NATIONAL POLICE EXPLOSIVE EXPERTS DISCOVERED ANOTHER DEVICE IN THE VACANT LOT WHERE TWO OTHER BOMBS HAD GONE OFF EARLIER. TEN HOMES WERE DAMAGED BY ONE OF THE EXPLOSIONS, INCLUDING THE HOMES OF DEPUTY FINANCES MINISTER GUSTAVO ADOLFO LEIVA AND GUATEMALA GOVERNOR MARIO LOGORGON. ONLY MATERIAL DAMAGE WAS CAUSED. THE AREA RESIDENTS HAVE BEEN EVACUATED FROM THE SITE. ANOTHER CHARGE WENT OFF IN FRONT OF THE AIR FORCE'S MAIN GATE ALMOST AT THE SAME TIME THE FIRST BOMB WENT OFF. AIR FORCE OFFICIALS CLOSED HINCAPIE AVENUE, FROM LIBERACION BOULEVARD TO SANTA FE. THE OFFICERS REPORTED MATERIAL DAMAGE AND AND AN EXCHANGE OF FIRE IN THE AREA NEARBY. FIREMEN AND POLICEMEN AND SEVERAL ARMY ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS PATROLLING THE CITY ARE MAINTANING SECURITY.

DEV-MUC3-1287 (BOEING)

TEL AVIV (ISRAEL), 17 MAY 90 (HADASHOT) -- [INTERVIEW WITH GUATEMALAN FOREIGN MINISTER ARIEL IRIAS RIVERA BY SHLOMO SLUTZKY] [TEXT] WHEN HE BEGAN HIS JOB AS GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT AFTER DECADES OF MILITARY REGIMES THAT LEFT BEHIND 100,000 FATALITIES, CHRISTIAN DEMOCRAT MARCO VINICIO AREVALO CEREZO HAD PROMISES FOR THE FUTURE AND THINGS TO HIS CREDIT IN THE PAST. THE THINGS TO HIS CREDIT WERE FOUR ASSASSINATION ATTEMPTS ON HIM BECAUSE OF HIS ATTEMPTS TO RESTORE DEMOCRACY IN HIS COUNTRY, AND HIS PROMISES WERE TO STOP POLITICAL VIOLENCE, CORRUPTION, AND MAINLY THE ACTIVITIES OF THE EXTREME RIGHT-WING DEATH SQUADS.

CEREZO HAS BEEN IN THIS POST FOR FIVE YEARS. NEW ELECTIONS ARE TO BE HELD SOON, AND THE ACTIVITIES OF THE DEATH SQUADS, SUPPORTED BY ELEMENTS IN THE DEFENSE FORCES, HAVE NOT STOPPED. THEY KILLED HUNDREDS OF LABOR UNION LEADERS AND LEFTISTS.

THE VISIT TO ISRAEL BY GUATEMALAN FOREIGN MINISTER ARIEL IRIAS RIVERA PROVIDES AN OPPORTUNITY TO UNDERSTAND WHAT IS HAPPENING IN HIS COUNTRY. AFTER ALL, NO ONE AT THE FOREIGN MINISTRY HAS EXPRESSED AN INTEREST IN IT.

[SLUTZKY] BEFORE YOU CAME HERE, YOU SAID THAT YOU INTEND TO MAKE A CONTRIBUTION HERE FROM YOUR EXPERIENCE IN BRINGING PEACE TO CENTRAL AMERICA. WHAT CAN THE MIDDLE EAST LEARN FROM CENTRAL AMERICA?

[RIVERA] YOU CAN LEARN THAT PROBLEMS CAN BE SOLVED WITHOUT VIOLENCE, THAT INTERNATIONAL ASSISTANCE AND GUARANTEES ARE IMPORTANT. IT SEEMS TO US THAT THE PROPOSITION TO HOLD AN INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE IS THE ONE THAT EVENTUALLY WILL BRING PEACE TO YOUR AREA. AT THE SAME TIME, WE ARE AWARE OF THE LARGE DIFFERENCES BETWEEN THE SITUATION IN OUR REGION, WHERE ALL THE PEOPLES HAVE THE SAME ORIGIN, AND YOURS, WHERE NATIONAL, COMMUNITY, AND RELIGIOUS CONFLICTS ARE INTERTWINED.

[SLUTZKY] IT WAS SAID IN JERUSALEM THAT YOU HAVE NOT COME HERE TO PURCHASE MILITARY EQUIPMENT. THAT SORT OF CLARIFICATION DOES NOT USUALLY PRECEDE A VISIT BY A FOREIGN MINISTER TO ISRAEL.

[RIVERA] IT IS POSSIBLE THAT THEY WANTED TO CLARIFY AN ISSUE THAT IS SELF-EVIDENT FOR US. WITH US, WEAPON DEALS ARE CARRIED OUT BY MILITARY PERSONNEL.

[SLUTZKY] THE ISRAELI CHAPTER OF AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL WANTED TO PRESENT YOU WITH A PETITION SIGNED BY HUNDREDS OF ISRAELIS DEMANDING THAT HUMAN RIGHTS' ABUSE IN GUATEMALA IN THE PAST SEVERAL YEARS BE INVESTIGATED.

[RIVERA] I HAVE A DEEP RESPECT FOR AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL, BUT WE FEEL IT IS OUTDATED TO USE TOOLS FROM A DICTATORIAL PAST ON PRESENT REGIMES. IT IS WELL KNOWN THAT CEREZO'S GOVERNMENT HAS A POLICY THAT IS DIFFERENT FROM ITS PREDECESSORS'. NEVERTHELESS, THERE STILL ARE CENTERS OF RIGHT-WING POWER IN OUR COUNTRY; THOSE GROUPS FEAR THE STABILIZATION OF DEMOCRACY.

[SLUTZKY] CEREZO PROMISED TO INVESTIGATE ISRAELI INVOLVEMENT IN GUATEMALA, INCLUDING ARMS AND DEFENSE TECHNOLOGY SALES. HAS ANYTHING BEEN DONE IN THAT RESPECT?

[RIVERA] FROM WHAT I KNOW, ISRAEL SOLD WEAPONS TO GUATEMALA AT THE FULL PRICE WHEN THE U.S. BOYCOTT WAS IN EFFECT AND OUR ARMY NEEDED MILITARY EQUIPMENT TO FIGHT THE GUERRILLAS. OTHER THAN THAT, OUR DECISION IS NOT TO SCRATCH THE WOUNDS OF THE PAST, BUT TO WORRY ABOUT PEACE IN THE FUTURE.

[SLUTZKY] CEREZO'S GOVERNMENT APPEARS TO BE ONE WITH GOOD INTENTIONS, BUT WITHOUT COMPLETE CONTROL OVER THE ARMY AND THOSE CONNECTED WITH THE DEATH SQUADS.

[RIVERA] THIS IS AN INCORRECT IMAGE. I WOULD NOT SAY THAT IT IS EASY TO OVERCOME ALL THE POWER ELEMENTS IN A FEW YEARS. STILL, I CAN SAY THAT PROGRESS IS BEING MADE IN THIS FIELD. THE ARMY'S COMMAND HEADED BY GENERAL GRAMAJO MORALES, THE DEFENSE MINISTER, GREATLY ASSISTED THE PROCESS OF DEMOCRATIZATION.

[SLUTZKY] ARE THE ELEMENTS THAT TOOK PART IN THE COUPS NOT CONNECTED TO THE EXTREME RIGHT-WING AND THE DEATH SQUADS WHICH MURDERED HUNDREDS OF CITIZENS IN THE PAST FEW YEARS, UNDER A DEMOCRATIC REGIME?

[RIVERA] IT IS VERY PROBABLE, BUT WE MUST REMEMBER THAT THESE ELEMENTS ARE A MINORITY, AFTER ALL. THE OFFICERS WHO WERE INVOLVED IN THE FIRST COUP WERE PARDONED. THE OFFICERS WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE SECOND COUP WERE BROUGHT TO TRIAL. I BELIEVE THIS INDICATES A POSITIVE DEVELOPMENT.

[SLUTZKY] IN YOUR OPINION, WILL CEREZO BE ABLE TO APPEAR BEFORE THE VOTERS IN A FEW MONTHS AND PROVE THAT HE HAS KEPT HIS PROMISES?

[RIVERA] TO A LARGE EXTENT, YES. ECONOMIC GROWTH HAS BEGUN; POLITICAL AND PROFESSIONAL ORGANIZATIONS ALLOWED; POLITICAL LEADERS ARE NO LONGER SYSTEMATICALLY MURDERED AS IN THE PAST; AND THERE IS NO VIOLENT SUPPRESSION OF DEMOCRATIC EXPRESSIONS. CEREZO IS TRYING TO PLAY THE DEMOCRATIC GAME ALL THE WAY.

[JERUSALEM DOMESTIC SERVICE IN HEBREW AT 0400 GMT ON 17 MAY 90 REPORTS THAT "GUATEMALA WILL SET UP A CULTURAL CENTER IN JERUSALEM IN THE BUILDING WHERE ITS CHANCERY WAS LOCATED UNTIL THE JERUSALEM LAW WAS PASSED. HOWEVER, BECAUSE OF ITS SENSITIVE POSITION IN INTERNATIONAL FORUMS, IT WILL NOT BE ABLE TO MOVE THE EMBASSY BACK FROM TEL AVIV TO THE CAPITAL, GUATEMALAN FOREIGN MINISTER ARIEL IRIAS RIVERA TOLD OUR CORRESPONDENT GID'ON REMEZ."]

DEV-MUC3-1288 (BOEING)

MANILA (PHILIPPINES), 18 MAY 90 (MANILA BULLETIN) -- [ARTICLE] [OLAF S. GIRON] [EXCERPT] THE UNHOLY UNION OF ILLICIT DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND POLITICAL TERRORISTS HAS BECOME EVIDENT IN THE PHILIPPINES AS IN OTHER COUNTRIES SUCH AS PERU AND COLOMBIA, MILITARY AUTHORITIES SAID YESTERDAY.

VIOLENCE FUELED BY BIG DRUG PROFITS IS VIEWED AS A MAJOR THREAT TO A NUMBER OF SOVEREIGN GOVERNMENTS, THEY ADDED.

LAST MARCH, AUTHORITIES IN MANILA ARRESTED TWO NEW PEOPLE'S ARMY (NPA) GUERRILLAS REPORTEDLY FROM THE ALEX BONCAYAO BRIGADE FOR TRAFFICKING IN NARCOTICS.

THE ARRESTS CAME AFTER A FOUR-MONTH INVESTIGATION OF REPORTS THAT THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF THE PHILIPPINES (CPP) WAS INVOLVED IN DRUG TRAFFICKING AS A MEANS TO SHORE UP RESOURCES FOR BUYING FIREARMS IN VIEW OF DECLINING DONATIONS FROM SUPPORTERS IN EUROPE.

FORTY-FOUR DECKS OF SHABU [METHAMPHETAMINE] WITH A STREET VALUE OF P[PESO]154,000 WERE FOUND IN THE POSSESSION OF THE SUSPECTS.

IN THE SAME MONTH, DRUG KINGPIN JOSE OYSON, ALSO KNOWN AS DON PEPE, WAS KILLED WHILE GRAPPLING WITH POLICE AS HE WAS BEING TAKEN TO THE NATIONAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (NBI) HEADQUARTERS FOR QUESTIONING.

AFTER HIS ACQUITTAL FOR THE 1984 KILLING OF AN ANTI-DRUG CRUSADING MANILA NEWSPAPER REPORTER, OYSON ALLEGEDLY ESTABLISHED CONNECTIONS WITH MAJOR DRUG SYNDICATE LEADERS IN HONG KONG AND TAIWAN. HE ALSO HAD BEEN UNDER SUSPICION OF FINANCING RIGHT-WING REVOLTS AGAINST PRESIDENT AQUINO.

THE ARRESTS OF THE TWO NPA GUERRILLAS PROVIDED THE FIRST HARD EVIDENCE IN THE PHILIPPINES OF THE UNHOLY ALLIANCE OF NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING AND TERRORISM THAT HAD ALREADY PLAGUED A NUMBER OF GOVERNMENTS ELSEWHERE.

AUTHORITIES SAID THEY ALSO SHOWED THAT ILLICIT DRUG PROFITS CAN FUEL REVOLUTIONS FROM THE RIGHT OR THE LEFT WITH EQUAL MAGNANIMITY AND EVEN SIMULTANEOUSLY.

AS A PRIME EXAMPLE, IN COLOMBIA, POWERFUL COCAINE LEADERS WHO WORKED IN CLOSE LEAGUE WITH COMMUNIST INSURGENTS 10 OR 15 YEARS AGO HAVE TURNED AGAINST THE INSURGENTS AS THEIR STAGGERING DRUG PROFITS ENABLED THEM TO BUY UP HUGE TRACTS OF RURAL FARM AND RANCH LAND AND URBAN REAL ESTATE IN THE 1980S [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-1289 (BOEING)

MADRID (SPAIN), 17 MAY 90 (EFE) -- [EXCERPT] LIMA, 17 MAY (EFE) -- SOURCES CLOSE TO THE GOVERNMENT TODAY SAID THAT THE "TEMPORARY WITHDRAWAL" FROM THE STRUGGLE ANNOUNCED BY THE "SHINING PATH" PERUVIAN MAOIST GUERRILLA GROUP ON ITS 10TH ANNIVERSARY IS A "PSYCHOLOGICAL WAR OPERATION" INITIATED BY THE MILITARY.

CIVILIAN SOURCES TOLD EFE THAT THE COMMUNIQUE THAT WAS RELEASED IN AYACUCHO -- THE CRADLE OF THE "SHINING PATH" -- ANNOUNCING THE GROUP'S TEMPORARY WITHDRAWAL FROM THE ARMED STRUGGLE "IS FICTITIOUS AND WAS RELEASED BY THE ARMED FORCES TO CREATE AN ATMOSPHERE OF UNCERTAINTY IN THE RANKS OF THE SHINING PATH" AT A TIME WHEN TERRORIST ACTIONS WERE EXPECTED TO INCREASE TO MARK THE GROUP'S ANNIVERSARY.

THE SOURCES SAID THAT THE COMMUNIQUE IS AIMED AT CONFUSING THE SHINING PATH COMMANDOS, WHO ARE DIVIDED AND HAVE NO CLEAR COMMUNICATION AMONG THEMSELVES OR WITH THEIR COMMANDING LEVELS. THE SOURCES ADDED THAT THE COMMUNIQUE IS AIMED AT DELAYING OR ABORTING THE ARMED ACTIONS THAT MAY HAVE BEEN PLANNED FOR TODAY AND TOMORROW.

THE SECURITY FORCES HAVE BEEN ON "RED ALERT" IN AYACUCHO TODAY TO PREVENT THE SHINING PATH FROM CELEBRATING ITS 10TH ANNIVERSARY WITH PROPAGANDA ATTACKS RECALLING THE BEGINNING OF THE "PEOPLE'S WAR" ON 17 JUNE 1980, WHEN THE GROUP ATTACKED AN ELECTORAL COURT OFFICE IN AN ANDEAN TOWN.

THE COMMUNIQUE, WHICH WAS RELEASED IN SUBURBAN AREAS OF AYACUCHO, ANNOUNCED THAT THE PERUVIAN COMMUNIST PARTY (PCP) -- WHICH IS THE OFFICIAL NAME OF THE SHINING PATH -- HAS "TEMPORARILY" WITHDRAWN FROM THE ARMED STRUGGLE AND WILL REORGANIZE ITSELF TO RETURN WITH "NEW IMPETUS."

THE AUTHENTICITY OF THE COMMUNIQUE WAS ALSO CALLED INTO QUESTION BY AYACUCHO JOURNALISTIC AND UNIVERSITY SOURCES CONSULTED BY EFE. THEY NOTED THAT THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME THAT COMMUNIQUES HAVE BEEN ATTRIBUTED TO THE SHINING PATH.

"WE ARE TEMPORARILY WITHDRAWING FORM THE ARMED STRUGGLE, BUT WE WILL CONTINUE THE IDEOLOGICAL FIGHT AND EXAMINE AND EVALUATE THE BRILLIANT ACTIONS THAT WE HAVE CARRIED OUT DURING THE PAST DECADE TO RETURN ONCE AGAIN, WITH MORE IDEAS AND A DETERMINATION THAT WILL PERMIT A STRATEGIC BALANCE UNDER BETTER CIRCUMSTANCES," THE COMMUNIQUE STATES.

"IT IS TIME FOR US TO SAY THAT THE TIME FOR CRIME FOR THE SAKE OF CRIME IS PASSED AND THAT THE CULT OF PERSONALITY IS ALSO OVER," IT ADDS. CONTRARY TO STANDARD SHINING PATH PRACTICE, THE NOTE, WHICH IS SIGNED BY THE "PCP-RANK-AND-FILE," DOES NOT MENTION THE MOVEMENT'S TOP LEADER AND FOUNDER ABIMAEL GUZMAN, KNOWN BY HIS SUPPORTERS AS "PRESIDENT GONZALO." SPECIALISTS BELIEVE THAT THIS PHRASE IS AN ATTACK AGAINST THE MORE MILITARIST SECTOR OF THE SHINING PATH AND AGAINST GUZMAN, AND THAT IT SEEKS TO FOMENT DIVISION WITHIN THE SHINING PATH.

SOME SPECIALISTS IN THE ACTIVITIES OF THE GROUP HAVE SAID THAT THERE IS A CONFRONTATION BETWEEN THE MORE MODERATE SECTOR, KNOWN AS THE "BLACK" WING, AND THE "RED" ORTHODOX, MILITARIST WING. OTHER OBSERVERS HAVE SAID THAT THERE ARE ONLY "FISSURES" CONCERNING OPERATIONAL METHODS. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-1290 (BOEING)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 16 MAY 90 (EL PANAMA AMERICA) -- [ARTICLE] [CARLOS VARGAS] [TEXT] THE PRESUMED SUBVERSIVE GROUP M-20 [20 DECEMBER MOVEMENT] THREATENED ON 15 MAY TO ENTER THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY AND FREE THE REFUGEES THERE. IT ALSO CALLED SEVERAL MEDIA CLAIMING THAT IT HAD KIDNAPPED A HIGH SCHOOL STUDENT AND PLACED BOMBS IN SEVERAL GOVERNMENT OFFICES.

IN VIEW OF THE TELEPHONE CALLS, THE GOVERNMENT, THROUGH FOREIGN MINISTER JULIO LINARES, HAS ANNOUNCED THAT IT HAS STRENGTHENED POLICE PROTECTION AROUND THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN THIS CAPITAL.

FORMER PANAMA DEFENSE FORCES OFFICERS GONZALO GONZALEZ AND HERACLIDES SUCRE, CLOSE COLLABORATORS OF OVERTHROWN GENERAL MANUEL NORIEGA, ARE REFUGEES AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY. GONZALEZ IS ALLEGEDLY INVOLVED IN THE MURDER OF SEVERAL MILITARY OFFICERS WHO TRIED UNSUCCESSFULLY TO OVERTHROW NORIEGA ON 3 OCTOBER 1989. FOREIGN MINISTER LINARES REVEALED THAT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY HAD RECEIVED TWO TELEPHONE CALLS FROM INDIVIDUALS WHO IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES AS M-20 MEMBERS AND THREATENED TO ENTER THE EMBASSY GROUNDS TO FREE THE REFUGEES THERE.

SECURITY AROUND THE EMBASSY WAS REINFORCED, ALTHOUGH IT HAD BEEN STRENGTHENED EARLIER AFTER SEVERAL OFFICERS OF THE FORMER REGIME SOUGHT ASYLUM THERE.

MEANWHILE, THE DIRECTOR OF THE "INSTITUTO AMERICA" HIGH SCHOOL DENIED THE M-20'S CLAIM THAT IT WAS HOLDING, AND THREATENED TO KILL, A STUDENT FROM THAT SCHOOL.

ALSO ON 15 MAY, PANAMANIAN AND AMERICAN POLICEMEN HAD TO ORDER THE EVACUATION OF WORKERS FROM SEVERAL GOVERNMENT OFFICES IN THE BANKING AREA OF VIA ESPANA DUE TO REPORTED BOMB THREATS FROM THE M- 20.

THE M-20 ALLEGEDLY IS A GROUP OF SUPPORTERS OF OVERTHROWN GENERAL NORIEGA WHO CLAIM RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE MARCH TERRORIST ATTACK ON THE "MY PLACE" BAR. ONE U.S. SOLDIER WAS KILLED AND 20 PANAMANIANS WERE WOUNDED IN THE ATTACK.

FOREIGN MINISTER LINARES SAID THAT HE COULD NOT CONFIRM THE EXISTENCE OF THE M-20.

A NUMBER OF DAYS AGO THE SOUTHERN COMMAND OFFERED A $10,000 REWARD TO ANY PERSON WHO PROVIDES INFORMATION LEADING TO THE ARREST OF THE MAN WHO THREW THE BOMB INTO THE AFOREMENTIONED BAR.

IT WAS ALSO LEARNED THAT THE JUDICIAL TECHNICAL POLICE ARE TRYING TO TRACE THE TELEPHONE CALLS, WHICH HAVE SCARED THE CITIZENS SOMEWHAT.

MAJOR GONZALO GONZALEZ, WHO HAS TAKEN REFUGE AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY, WAS ALSO ACCUSED OF BEING THE MASTERMIND BEHIND THE DEATH OF YOUNG MELQUIADES RODRIGUEZ JUSTINE, A GRANDSON OF FORMER COLONEL JUSTINE.

DEV-MUC3-1291 (BOEING)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 18 MAY 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO SAID TODAY IN CARACAS THAT HE "FIRMLY BELIEVES" THAT A SALVADORAN RIGHT-WING POLITICAL GROUP PARTICIPATED IN THE ASSASSINATION IN GUATEMALA OF SALVADORAN SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC LEADER HECTOR OQUELI AND HIS COMPANION GILDA FLORES IN LATE JANUARY.

IN A NEWS CONFERENCE TODAY AT THE AYACUCHO ROOM OF THE MIRAFLORES [PRESIDENTIAL] PALACE, CEREZO SAID HE WILL DELIVER A DETAILED REPORT ON THIS CASE TO VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, TO SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL, AND TO THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT, TO WHICH HE REQUESTED ALL THE NECESSARY ASSISTANCE TO IDENTIFY AND DETAIN THE ASSASSINS.

REFERRING TO THE TALKS BEING HELD WITH THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT TO RENEGOTIATE IN CONCEPT THE OIL DEBT THAT GUATEMALA HAS WITH VENEZUELA -- WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT -- CEREZO SAID PRESIDENT PEREZ HAD ACCEPTED THE [RESTRUCTURING] PROPOSAL. HOWEVER, THE TERMS ARE STILL BEING DISCUSSED.

THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT REQUESTED 20 YEARS TO PAY THE DEBT, A SIX-YEAR GRACE PERIOD, AND A FOUR-YEAR [GRACE PERIOD] ON THE INTEREST. THIS PROPOSAL WILL BE PRESENTED TO THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT (WHICH ALONG WITH VENEZUELA PARTICIPATES IN THE OIL SUPPLY AGREEMENT). THE PROPOSAL WILL THEN BE PRESENTED AT THE UPCOMING CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SUMMIT.

DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE WITH VENEZUELAN AND FOREIGN JOURNALISTS, THE GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT, WHO ARRIVED ON 17 MAY IN VENEZUELA, SAID THAT TO CONSOLIDATE PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA, IT IS ESSENTIAL TO HAVE GRADUAL DEMILITARIZATION, WITH THE RESULTING REDUCTION IN WEAPONS AND LOCAL ARMIES, "WHICH SHOULD BE LEFT UNSUITED TO CARRY OUT EXTERNAL ATTACKS."

CONCERNING NICARAGUA, CEREZO SAID THE PROFESSIONALIZATION AND IDEOLOGICAL INDEPENDENCE OF THE ARMY IS FUNDAMENTAL TO REAFFIRMING ITS DEMOCRACY.

DEV-MUC3-1293 (BOEING)

HAVANA (CUBA), 18 MAY 90 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] NINE YEARS AGO TODAY, THEN ECUADORAN PRESIDENT JAIME ROLDOS AGUILERA DIED WHEN HIS PLANE CRASHED WHILE ON A FLIGHT TO THE INTERIOR OF HIS COUNTRY. THE SMALL PLANE SUFFERED THE ACCIDENT WHILE FLYING THE PRESIDENT, HIS WIFE, AND A DELEGATION THAT INCLUDED HIGH- RANKING ARMY OFFICERS FROM QUITO TO LOJA PROVINCE. ALL OF THEM DIED. THE RELATIVES OF THE LATE PRESIDENT EXPRESSED DOUBTS THAT THE PLANE CRASHED ACCIDENTALLY AND FILED CHARGES AS PRIVATE CITIZENS, BUT THE CASE WAS LATER CLOSED.

DOUBTS HAVE BEEN EXPRESSED SEVERAL TIMES ABOUT THE ALLEGED ACCIDENT, AND THE CASE RESURFACED AGAIN WHEN A NEW INVESTIGATION WAS OPENED AND ONE OF THE WITNESSES DISCLOSED THAT THERE IS EVIDENCE OF PARTICIPATION BY THE U.S. CIA IN THE DEATH OF ROLDOS AND HIS RETINUE. ERNESTO BUENANO, ROLDOS' POLITICAL ADVISER, ASSERTED BEFORE A MULTIPARTY COMMISSION OF THE ECUADORAN CONGRESS THAT THE PLANE ACCIDENT IN WHICH THE FORMER PRESIDENT DIED DID NOT RESULT FROM HUMAN ERROR OR TECHNICAL FAILURE BUT FROM SABOTAGE, WHICH CONSISTED OF CONTAMINATING THE PLANE'S FUEL TO CAUSE ITS ENGINES TO STALL. THE WITNESS POINTED OUT THAT THERE IS INCONTESTABLE EVIDENCE ABOUT THIS AND URGED THE COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE THE PERSONS WHO WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR SUPPLYING FUEL TO THE PRESIDENT'S PLANE.

IT IS WORTH MENTIONING THAT ROLDOS' ADMINISTRATION WAS CHARACTERIZED BY A PROGRESSIVE ORIENTATION, AND MORE SPECIFICALLY BY HIS DIRECT OPPOSITION TO U.S. ATTEMPTS TO DOMINATE THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES. THE FORMER PRESIDENT WAS OPENLY IN SOLIDARITY WITH THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT OF NICARAGUA AND THE SALVADORAN INSURGENTS. HIS ADOPTION OF THIS STANCE LED U.S. IMPERIALISM TO CONSIDER THE ROLDOS DOCTRINE AS A DANGER TO ITS INTERESTS.

WHEN ONE RECALLS THE POSITION OF THE FORMER ECUADORAN PRESIDENT, THE DISAPPEARANCE OF FORMER PANAMANIAN LEADER OMAR TORRIJOS HERRERA ALSO COMES TO MIND. TORRIJOS' DEATH WAS SIMILAR IN CIRCUMSTANCES TO THAT OF JAIME ROLDOS, AND HIS PATRIOTIC ATTITUDE WITH REGARD TO HIS COUNTRY'S SOVEREIGNTY WAS ALSO SIMILAR. TORRIJOS AND ROLDOS WERE A NUISANCE TO U.S. PLANS IN LATIN AMERICA AND BOTH WERE MURDERED, AS VARIOUS SOURCES HAVE DISCLOSED. FORMER CHILEAN PRESIDENT SALVADOR ALLENDE [WORDS INDISTINCT] IT CANNOT BE SAID THAT THE CIA'S HAND DIRECTLY TOOK HIS LIFE, THE ORGANIZATION DID HELP DESTABILIZE HIS PROGRESSIVE GOVERNMENT.

THE INVESTIGATIONS ON JAIME ROLDOS' DEATH AND WHAT WAS SAID AT THE TIME ABOUT THE ALLEGED ACCIDENT SUFFERED BY OMAR TORRIJOS REVEAL ONCE MORE THE SINISTER PLANS OF THE U.S. CIA AGAINST OUR LATIN AMERICAN AND CARIBBEAN PEOPLE, WHO MUST REMAIN ON THE ALERT.

DEV-MUC3-1295 (BOEING)

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [EDITORIAL REPORT] [TEXT] FOLLOWING IS A COMPILATION OF REPORTS ON DRUG SEIZURES AND ARRESTS RELATED TO DRUG TRAFFICKING IN BUREAU COVERAGE AREA FROM 11 MAY TO 18 MAY.

COLOMBIA

NATIONAL POLICE IN BOGOTA DISMANTLED THREE COCAINE PROCESSING LABORATORIES AND SEIZED ONE TON OF COCAINE, IT WAS REPORTED ON 17 MAY.

HONDURAS

HONDURAN POLICE IN TEGUCIGALPA SEIZED SIX TONS OF MARIJUANA AT A PLANTATION LOCATED IN OCOTEPEQUE DEPARTMENT IN THE COUNTRY'S WESTERN REGION. THE POLICE INTERROGATED SEVERAL PERSONS LINKED WITH THE DRUGS AND REPORTED THAT THE MARIJUANA HAD A MARKET VALUE OF $1 MILLION.

POLICE LIEUTENANT JOSE DANIEL AMADOR ORDONEZ REPORTED THAT HONDURAN CARLOS MANUEL LOPEZ MATA WAS THE OWNER OF THE PLANTATION WHERE THE POLICE DISCOVERED MARIJUANA VALUED AT $8 MILLION LEMPIRAS. MATA ESCAPED TOGETHER WITH SALVADORANS LUIS AND GUILLERMO GUERRA WHO WERE ALSO CONNECTED WITH THE DRUGS FOUND. THE POLICE OFFICER SAID THE DRUGS WERE READY TO BE SHIPPED TO EL SALVADOR THROUGH THE BORDER REGION OF EL RINCON DE MARCHALA.

HONDURAN POLICE HAVE SEIZED 58 KG OF COCAINE WHICH DRUG BANDS INTENDED TO SMUGGLE INTO THE UNITED STATES. THE POLICE DISCOVERED THE DRUGS INSIDE VEHICLES WITH CAMOUFLAGED COMPARTMENTS IN THE NORTHERN CITY OF SAN PEDRO SULA, 255 KM FROM TEGUCIGALPA. THE TRAFFICKERS PLANNED TO TAKE THE DRUG FROM PANAMA TO THE UNITED STATES. FIVE HONDURANS AND COLOMBIAN RODOLFO ANTONIO MONTOYA WERE ARRESTED IN THIS CONNECTION. IT WAS ALSO LEARNED IN TEGUCIGALPA ON 18 MAY THAT COLOMBIAN DRUG LEADER GUILLERMO LEON VELASQUEZ, WHO IS AT THE SERVICE OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS ARRESTED ON 15 MAY AND DEPORTED TO THE UNITED STATES WHERE HE IS ACCUSED OF KILLING A PERSON SIX YEARS AGO. THE REPORT ADDED THAT LEON VELASQUEZ, KNOWN IN MEDELLIN AS "CHIRUZA," IS RESPONSIBLE FOR SEVEN OTHER MURDERS.

MEXICO

FEDERAL JUDICIAL POLICE [PJF] AGENTS SEIZED 1,850 KG OF COCAINE WHEN A COLOMBIAN AIRCRAFT CRASHED IN THE TOWN OF ESCALON IN CIUDAD JUARES, CHIHUAHUA. THE DRUGS WERE BEING FLOWN TO THE UNITED STATES. PJF COMMANDER GUILLERMO GONZALEZ CALDERONI SAID THAT THE DRUGS WERE FOUND 30 KM NORTHEAST OF THE CITY OF JIMENEZ. THE DRUGS ARE REPORTED TO HAVE A MARKET VALUE OF 1 BILLION PESOS.

FEDERAL HIGHWAY POLICE IN SALTILLO REPORTED THAT 781 KG OF PURE COCAINE, WHICH WAS BEING TRANSPORTED IN A TRAILER FROM GUATEMALA TO HOUSTON, TEXAS, WAS SEIZED TODAY. POLICE COMMANDER JORGE ESLAVA SAID THAT ANGEL GUADALUPE RIVERA RIVAS, DRIVER OF THE TRAILER, AND BALTAZAR FIGUEROA MATEO, HIS ASSISTANT, WERE ARRESTED.

THE NATIONAL DEFENSE SECRETARIAT REPORTED ON 13 MAY THAT A TOTAL OF 632 KG OF MARIJUANA WERE SEIZED IN DIFFERENT OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT IN THE STATES OF JALISCO AND OAXACA FROM 8 TO 11 MAY. MOST OF THE PERSONS ARRESTED WERE TURNED OVER TO THE PERTINENT AUTHORITIES. THE REPORT ADDS THAT OVER THE SAME PERIOD A TOTAL OF 37 HECTARES (26 WITH POPPY PLANTS AND 11 WITH MARIJUANA) WERE DESTROYED AND 122 FIREARMS WERE SEIZED. THE SAME SOURCE ADDED THAT MEMBERS OF THE 18TH INFANTRY BATTALION IN IXCOTEL, OAXACA, CLASHED WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS ON 10 MAY, RESULTING IN THE DEATHS OF A SOLDIER AND A CIVILIAN. THE POLICE ARRESTED 11 PERSONS AND SEIZED 300 KG OF MARIJUANA, TWO VEHICLES, AND LARGE CALIBER WEAPONS.

DURING OPERATIONS CARRIED OUT IN CIUDAD OBREGON, SALTILLO, AND MEXICALI, ANTIDRUG POLICEMEN SEIZED 1,382 KG OF COCAINE BASE AND ONE AND A HALF TONA OF MARIJUANA, AND ARRESTED 10 ALLEGED DRUG TRAFFICKERS, THE ATTORNEY GENERAL HAS REPORTED. IN MEXICALI, ANTINARCOTICS POLICEMEN SEIZED MORE THAN ONE AND A HALF TONS OF MARIJUANA AND ARRESTED FIVE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. DURING THE ENSUING CLASH, MARCO ANTONIO RESENDIZ GASTELUM, THE LEADER OF THE BAND, WAS KILLED.

DEV-MUC3-1296 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 21 MAY 90 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] A MILITARY SPOKESMAN HAS REPORTED THAT ONE CIVILIAN WAS KILLED AND FIVE OTHER PEOPLE, INCLUDING A POLICEMAN, WERE INJURED TODAY AS A RESULT OF THE EXPLOSION OF A GRENADE THROWN AT A POLICE PATROL CAR BY ALLEGED URBAN GUERRILLA COMMANDOS.

THE CIVILIAN WHO WAS KILLED HAS BEEN IDENTIFIED AS JOSE OVIDIO GOMEZ, A TAXI DRIVER, AND THE INJURED POLICEMAN IS RICARDO ANTONIO MARTINEZ. MARTINEZ AND THE OTHER PERSONS WHO WERE INJURED, SOME SERIOUSLY, WERE TAKEN TO A SAN SALVADOR MEDICAL CENTER.

ACCORDING TO THE SOURCE, THE GRENADE WAS THROWN AT 0630 (1230 GMT) TODAY. THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE NEAR THE CENTRAL MARKETPLACE, SAN SALVADOR'S MOST IMPORTANT SUPPLY CENTER, WHICH IS VERY CROWDED AT THAT TIME OF DAY.

THE SOURCE ATTRIBUTED THE ATTACK TO URBAN GUERRILLA COMMANDOS, BUT THE GUERRILLAS HAVE NOT CLAIMED CREDIT FOR IT.

THIS IS THE FIRST ATTACK THAT HAS TAKEN PLACE IN THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL SINCE THE PEACE NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT BEGAN LAST WEDNESDAY IN VENEZUELA.

THE TALKS ARE IN THEIR SIXTH DAY TODAY AND THERE IS AN ATMOSPHERE OF OPTIMISM. ACCORDING TO SOURCES CLOSE TO THE DIALOGUE, IMPORTANT PROGRESS HAS BEEN MADE TO SECURE THE PACIFICATION OF EL SALVADOR, WHICH FOR A DECADE HAS BEEN ENDURING A CIVIL WAR IN WHICH MORE THAN 70,000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED.

DEV-MUC3-1297 (BOEING)

SANTIAGO, 21 MAY 90 (EFE) -- [ARTICLE] [NELSON SANDOVAL] [TEXT] CHILEAN PRESIDENT PATRICIO AYLWIN WILL TODAY REPORT ON THE FIRST 70 DAYS OF HIS ADMINISTRATION AND WILL MAKE IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENTS CONCERNING HIS FUTURE PLANS IN A SPEECH TO A PLENARY MEETING OF THE CHILEAN CONGRESS THAT WILL MARK THE BEGINNING OF SPECIAL CONGRESSIONAL SESSIONS.

AYLWIN'S SPEECH AWAKENS CONSIDERABLE EXPECTATION BECAUSE OF RECENT UNPUBLICIZED CLASHES BETWEEN AYLWIN'S ADMINISTRATION AND GENERAL AUGUST PINOCHET, WHO HAS BEEN THROWING HIS WEIGHT AROUND AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMY, AND ALSO BECAUSE OF THE GROWING RIGHTWING OPPOSITION TO THE ACTIONS OF THE DEMOCRATIC ADMINISTRATION.

POLITICAL ANALYSTS HAVE POINTED OUT THAT THE PRESIDENTIAL SPEECH WILL COINCIDE WITH THE "END OF A GOVERNMENT-OPPOSITION HONEYMOON" THAT HAD MARKED THE INITIAL WEEKS OF THE NEW ADMINISTRATION.

THE ADMINISTRATION'S INITIATIVES REGARDING HUMAN RIGHTS, TAX REFORM, THE DEMOCRATIZATION OF LOCAL GOVERNMENTS, AND OTHER STEPS AIMED AT DEPRIVING MILITARY COURTS OF THEIR POWERS HAVE WORSENED THE CONFLICT AND HAVE MADE THINGS MORE DIFFICULT FOR AYLWIN'S ADMINISTRATION.

THIS IS HAPPENING BECAUSE, WHILE THE RIGHTWING PARTIES ARE LEANING MORE AND MORE TOWARD PINOCHET EVERY DAY AND LONGING FOR HIS AUTHORITARIAN REGIME, THE LEFTWING PARTIES AND EVEN SECTORS OF THE COALITION OF PARTIES FOR DEMOCRACY HAVE BEEN CRITICIZING AYLWIN FOR ALLEGED "LUKEWARM" APPROACH TO THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE DEMOCRATIC CHANGES THAT HE PROMISED DURING HIS ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN.

THE RIGHTWING HAS TAKEN DUE ADVANTAGE OF SEVERAL UNSOLVED TERRORIST ATTACKS OVER THE RECENT WEEKS TO PROP UP ITS OPPOSITION IN CONGRESS TO BILLS RELATED TO HUMAN RIGHTS.

HOWEVER, ACCORDING TO RECENT OPINION POLLS, AYLWIN WILL MAKE HIS SPEECH AMID GROWING POPULARITY, MUCH HIGHER THAN THE SUPPORT HE OBTAINED AT THE 14 DECEMBER ELECTIONS.

THE PRESIDENTIAL SPEECH TO CONGRESS AT THE LEGISLATIVE PALACE IN VALPARAISO, 125 KM WEST OF SANTIAGO, WILL MARK THE RETURN TO A LONG-STANDING DEMOCRATIC TRADITION THAT CHILEANS USED TO ENJOY EVERY 21 MAY.

ON THIS DAY, THE REPORT TO CONGRESS WAS YET ANOTHER REASON FOR POPULAR REJOICING BECAUSE IT COINCIDED WITH THE "NAVAL GLORIES DAY" WHICH IS ALSO COMMEMORATED ON 21 MAY IN MEMORY OF THE CHILE'S TOP NAVAL HERO ARTURO PRAT WHO DIED IN THE NAVAL BATTLE OF IQUIQUE DURING THE 1879 PACIFIC WAR.

SINCE CONGRESS WAS CLOSED DOWN DURING THE MILITARY REGIME, GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET USED TO READ HIS STATE OF THE NATION ADDRESS ON 11 SEPTEMBER, THE ANNIVERSARY OF THE MILITARY COUP D'ETAT THROUGH WHICH HE SEIZED POWER.

ACCORDING TO POLITICAL ANALYSTS, AYLWIN'S SPEECH MAY PROVIDE THE KEY TO THE LAYOUT OF CHILE'S TRANSITION IN THE FUTURE. THE MANNER IN WHICH THE PRESIDENT WILL MAKE HIS REPORT IS RATHER CURIOUS BECAUSE THEORETICALLY THIS REPORT SHOULD ENCOMPASS ONE YEAR OF GOVERNMENT, WHILE AYLWIN HAS BEEN PRESIDENT FOR ONLY 70 DAYS DURING WHICH THE ADMINISTRATION HAS BEEN HARSHLY CRITICIZED BY THE RIGHTWING EVERY TIME THE ADMINISTRATION HAD SOMETHING BAD TO SAY ABOUT THE PRIOR MILITARY REGIME.

GENERAL PINOCHET PERSONALLY TOLD AYLWIN THAT HE FELT OFFENDED BY AYLWIN'S LABOR DAY CELEBRATION SPEECH ON 1 MAY.

DURING HIS LATEST PRIVATE MEETING WITH THE PRESIDENT, PINOCHET TOLD AYLWIN THAT HE FELT THAT THE "TRUTH AND RECONCILIATION" COMMISSION THAT AYLWIN HAD CREATED TO INVESTIGATE HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS DURING THE MILITARY REGIME WAS A DIRECT ATTACK ON THE ARMY.

PINOCHET ALSO TOLD AYLWIN THAT BY WAY OF "PROTEST" AGAINST THESE ACTIONS HE WOULD NOT ATTEND THE LUNCHEON TO WHICH THE PRESIDENT HAD INVITED ALL THE COMMANDERS OF THE ARMED FORCES BRANCHES.

ACCORDING TO LEAKS ABOUT THIS MEETING, AYLWIN TOLD PINOCHET: "WATCH YOUR STEP, GENERAL" AND REMINDED HIM THAT OFFENSIVE BEHAVIOR AGAINST THE PRESIDENT COULD HARM PINOCHET'S IMAGE EVEN WITHIN HIS OWN INSTITUTION, THE ARMY.

PINOCHET DID NOT ATTEND THE LUNCHEON, HOWEVER, SENDING INSTEAD GENERAL HUGO SALAS, THE THIRD HIGHEST-RANKING ARMY OFFICER AND THE FORMER CHIEF OF THE CNI [NATIONAL INFORMATION CENTER], THE SECRET POLICE OF HIS REGIME.

PINOCHET FAILED IN HIS ATTEMPT TO CONVOKE THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL AND TO MAKE THIS COUNCIL ISSUE A STATEMENT AGAINST THE "TRUTH AND RECONCILIATION" COMMISSION, BUT PINOCHET'S SORTIE IN THE POLITICAL ARENA AWOKE CONCERN LACED WITH FEAR, AS ONE GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL ADMITTED TO EFE. THE SOURCE, WHO ASKED TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS, ADDED THAT "PINOCHET IS AWARE OF THE FEAR HE AWAKENS AND HE USES IT ADROITLY."

THE FORMER PRESIDENT WILL NOT ATTEND THE TODAY'S CEREMONY IN CONGRESS ALTHOUGH THE COMMANDERS OF THE OTHER ARMED FORCES BRANCHES, THE VERY SAME ONES THAT DID NOT SUPPORT HIS ATTEMPT TO CONVOKE THE NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL, WILL BE PRESENT.

PINOCHET CLAIMED THAT HE HAS "INSTITUTIONAL REASONS" FOR HIS ABSENCE AND HAS LEFT FOR NORTHERN CHILE WHERE HE IS CURRENTLY TOURING ARMY GARRISONS.

ANALYSTS BELIEVE THAT THE "PINOCHET EFFECT" WILL BE NOTICEABLE IN AYLWIN'S SPEECH THROUGH GREATER MODERATION IN ANNOUNCEMENTS OF NEW INSTITUTIONAL CHANGES AND THROUGH MORE BENIGN ASSESSMENTS OF THE PREVIOUS MILITARY REGIME.

DEV-MUC3-1298 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 21 MAY 90 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] INFORMS THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY:

1. SIMULTANEOUSLY WITH THE INITIATION OF THE CARACAS MEETING ON 16 MAY, THE ARMED FORCES LAUNCHED A GENERAL OFFENSIVE WITH AERIAL BOMBINGS, MASSIVE ARTILLERY ATTACKS, AND THE DEPLOYMENT OF PARATROOPERS AND INFANTRY SOLDIERS TO ALL OUR RURAL FRONTS. FOLLOWING FIVE DAYS OF INTENSE COMBAT, WE HAVE CONFIRMED THAT IT IS A ROUTINE OPERATION AND NOT A LARGE-SCALE OFFENSIVE.

2. OUR FORCES HAVE REJECTED THE ENEMY'S GENERAL OFFENSIVE AND TO DATE HAVE DOWNED ONE HELICOPTER, DAMAGED TWO OTHERS, AND INFLICTED DOZENS OF CASUALTIES ON THE ENEMY TROOPS. WE DENY THAT COMMANDER LEONCIO PICHINTE WAS KILLED IN COMBAT.

3. WHILE THE GOVERNMENT ACCUSES THE FMLN OF HAVING VIOLATED THE CONFIDENTIALITY OF THE TALKS, CRISTIANI AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE PROCESS HAVE BEEN MAKING A SERIES OF STATEMENTS CONCERNING CONFIDENTIAL ISSUES.

4. FROM THE SIGNING OF THE GENEVA AGREEMENT, THE GOVERNMENT HAS INCREASED ITS INTERFERENCE OF OUR RADIO VENCEREMOS AND RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI, WHICH REFLECTS THE GOVERNMENT'S WEAKNESS. IT CANNOT STAND TO HAVE OUR POSITIONS KNOWN. THEREFORE, THERE IS CLEARLY NO FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION, WHICH IN TURN DELAYS THE POSSIBILITY OF A CEASE-FIRE BECAUSE IT HINDERS THE NATIONAL DEBATE WE NEED IN ORDER TO REACH A POLITICAL SOLUTION.

5. FROM THE ABOVE SITUATION, WE CONCLUDE THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS USED THE CARACAS MEETING AS PART OF A WAR PLAN, WITH CRISTIANI PARTICIPATING AT THE PSYCHOLOGICAL WARFARE LEVEL WITH A VIEW TO POINTING OUT THE CONTRADICTORINESS OF THE FMLN'S POLITICAL ACTIVITY.

WITH THE NEGOTIATION AND THE INTERFERENCE OF OUR RADIO STATIONS, THE FMLN HAS SILENCED THE CONFIDENTIALITY ARGUMENT, WHILE THE ARMY IS TRYING TO MILITARILY ANNIHILATE US AND IS OPENLY PROCLAIMING IT BY SAYING THAT IT HAS ATTACKED COMMAND POSTS AND KILLED FMLN LEADERS.

6. THE FMLN REITERATES THAT AS LONG AS A CEASE-FIRE IS NOT AGREED UPON THROUGH A POLITICAL AGREEMENT THAT WILL END THE ARMY'S IMPUNITY, AND SPECIFIC PLEDGES ARE NOT MADE TO DEMILITARIZE THE COUNTRY, IT RESERVES THE LEGITIMATE RIGHT TO DEFEND ITSELF EVEN BY LAUNCHING OFFENSIVES, REGARDLESS OF THEIR SCOPE, WHENEVER NECESSARY ANYWHERE WITHIN THE NATIONAL TERRITORY.

DEV-MUC3-1299 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 21 MAY 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] FELLOW COUNTRYMEN: I ADDRESS YOU AT A MOMENT WHEN ALL GOOD COLOMBIANS ARE FILLED WITH PAIN. TERRORIST ACTIONS HAVE BROUGHT SADNESS AND MOURNING TO DOZENS OF OUR POOR HOMES, AS WELL AS TO FAMILIES OF NATIONAL LEADERS. COLOMBIA'S ENEMIES HAVE DEDICATED THEMSELVES TO ATTACKING UNARMED CITIZENS. THEIR INSANE ACTIONS ARE ENDING THE LIVES OF INNOCENT CHILDREN, WOMEN, AND HONEST COLOMBIANS. AT THESE TRYING TIMES, I SEND ALL THOSE WHO HAVE SUFFERED THE CONSEQUENCES OF THIS IRRATIONAL WAVE OF MONSTROUS CRIMES MY DEEPEST SENTIMENTS OF SOLIDARITY. I WANT TO TELL ALL THE VICTIMS' RELATIVES AND FRIENDS THAT WE SHARE THEIR SORROW AND SADNESS.

THE COUNTRY AND ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT HAVE BEEN DEALT A STRONG BLOW TODAY. ANOTHER GREAT MAN HAS BEEN ASSASSINATED. LIBERAL LEADER FEDERICO ESTRADA VELEZ WAS VIOLENTLY MURDERED IN THE STREETS OF MEDELLIN. THE LOSS OF SENATOR ESTRADA VELEZ LEAVES THE LIBERAL PARTY AND ANTIOQUIANS WITHOUT ONE OF ITS GREAT LEADERS. HE IS TO BE ADDED TO THE LIST OF MARTYRS THAT HAVE BEEN MURDERED FOR THEIR THOUGHTS AND BRAVE ATTITUDE IN CONFRONTING THE COUNTRY'S PROBLEMS. FEDERICO ESTRADA WAS A FIGHTER IN THIS ADMINISTARTION AND, AS OUR COLOMBIAN AMBASSADOR TO ITALY, CONTRIBUTED TO THE IMPROVEMENT OF RELATIONS WITH THAT COUNTRY AND WITH THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY. THE COUNTRY RECALLS HIM FOR HIS RECENT ACTIONS AS THE PROPONENT AND PROMOTER OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS PROJECT AT THE SENATE. HIS BRILLANT POLITICAL AND PROFESSIONAL CAREER ALLOWED HIM TO REACH THE HIGHEST POSITIONS OF THE COLOMBIAN CONGRESS AND OF THE JUDICIAL BRANCH. HE WAS A SUPREME COURT MAGISTRATE, UNIVERSITY PROFESSOR, PARLIAMENTARIAN, THE NATIONAL AND DEPARTMENTAL LEADER OF THE LIBERAL PARTY, A PUBLIC SERVANT OF MANY YEARS, AND A TIRELESS WORKER FOR THE WELLBEING OF THE PEOPLE OF ANTIOQUA. HIS LIFE WAS ENDED AT A TIME WHEN THE COUNTRY AND HIS PARTY NEEDED HIS EXPERIENCE AND KNOWLEDGE.

TO HIS WIFE, HIS FOUR CHILDREN, HIS FOLLOWERS, AND ALL ANTIOQUEANS, I SEND A HEARTFELT MESSAGE OF CONDOLENCE IN THE NAME OF ALL HIS FELLOW COUNTRYMEN. THE PEOPLE ARE SICK OF THIS IRRATIONAL VIOLENCE. ALL COLOMBIANS GET ANGRY EACH TIME A BARBARIC ACT TAKES PLACE AND EACH TIME ONE OF OUR LEADERS IS MURDERED. LET US TURN THIS ANGER INTO A PUBLIC CONDEMNATION OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THESE ACTIONS, IN A DECIDED ACTION BY ALL AGAINST THE EMPIRE OF CRIME, AND IN EFFECTIVE SOLIDARITY WITH GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS. RECOVERING PEACE AND TRANQUILLITY IS A JOINT TASK. EVERY DAY WE MUST DEMAND MORE EFFICIENCY FROM OUR PUBLIC FORCES BUT WE MUST ALSO GIVE THEM MORE SOLIDARITY AND SUPPORT SO THAT THEY CAN EFFICIENTLY COMPLY WITH THEIR SERIOUS RESPONSIBILITIES. THIS IS WHAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN DOING; IT HAS SUPPORTED THEM MORALLY AND MATERIALLY.

TO DEFEAT TERRORISM AND IMPUNITY DEPENDS ABOVE ALL ON THE COOPERATION OF CITIZENS. WE MUST ALL BECOME LIKE SOLDIERS IN THE SEARCH FOR PEACE BECAUSE THE FUTURE OF OUR FAMILIES, OUR PRINCIPLES, OUR RIGHTS, AND OUR DEMOCRACY ARE AT STAKE. LET THOSE WHO PROMOTE VIOLENCE FACE AN INVINCIBLE ARMY OF 30 MILLION HONEST COLOMBIANS. NO ONE SHOULD TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THIS PAINFUL MOMENT THE COUNTRY IS ENDURING. THE INTERESTS OF COLOMBIA ARE ABOVE ALL OTHER CONSIDERATIONS.

ON THE EVE OF THE ELECTIONS AND THE DECISION BY THE HONORABLE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE ON THE CONSTITUTIONAL ASSEMBLY, AND AFTER A THOROUGH ANALYSIS OF THE MOST RECENT PUBLIC ORDER DISTURBANCES, I HAVE DEEMED IT APPROPRIATE TO SEND THE FOREIGN MINISTER TO REPRESENT COLOMBIA AT THE ANDEAN GROUP PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT.

AS YOU ARE AWARE, THE ANDEAN GROUP PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT WILL BEGIN TOMORROW IN CUZCO, PERU. THIS MEETING WAS CALLED WITH THE OBJECTIVE OF ACHIEVING NEW PROGRESS IN THE INTEGRATION OF THE SUBREGION, THROUGH NEW MECHANISMS FOR INTEGRATION AND WITH THE CREATION OF THE ANDEAN PRESIDENTIAL COUNCIL.

THE FOREIGN MINISTER WILL BE ENTRUSTED WITH REAFFIRMING COLOMBIA'S FULL COMMITMENT TO THE INTEGRATION PROCESS AND TO CONCERTED NEW JOINT ACTIONS WITH PERU, ECUADOR, BOLIVIA, AND VENEZUELA TO FACE THE PROBLEM OF THE CONSUMPTION, SMUGGLING, AND DRUG PRODUCTION.

FELLOW COUNTRYMEN: I HEREBY REITERATE MY DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO ALL THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN AFFECTED BY VIOLENCE. IT IS AT THIS TIME OF SORROW AND SADNESS WHEN WE COLOMBIANS SHOULD BE MORE UNITED THAN EVER. I WANT TO INVITE YOU TO USE THE SUFFERING AND THE MEMORIES OF THOSE WHO HAVE FALLEN AS A FORCE THAT WILL GIVE US MORE COURAGE AND DETERMINATION TO CONTINUE TO PROGRESS IN BUILDING COLOMBIA IN PEACE, FREE OF TERRORISM AND VIOLENCE. GOOD NIGHT.

DEV-MUC3-1300 (BOEING)

QUITO, 21 MAY 90 (RADIO QUITO) -- [REPORT] [ALVARO GOMEZ] [TEXT] ALL MEDIA IN GUAYAQUIL AND MANY CORRESPONDENTS WHO HAVE COME TO THE PORT OF GUAYAQUIL TO COVER THE FOURTH ALFARO LIVES DAMMIT [AVC] NATIONAL CONFERENCE ARE STILL UNAWARE OF WHERE THE MEETING IS BEING HELD. THE SURRENDERING OF WEAPONS IN THE HANDS OF THIS GROUP WILL BE DISCUSSED AT THIS MEETING. THE FOUR-DAY MEETING BEGAN ON 18 MAY AT THE GUAYAS ELECTORAL TRIBUNAL. HOWEVER, THE MEETING WAS CONTINUED LATER AT AN UNDISCLOSED LOCATION IN GUAYAQUIL. DURING THEIR SESSIONS, IN ADDITION TO MAKING A DECISION ON THE SURRENDERING OF WEAPONS, AVC LEADERS WILL ALSO ASSESS THE AGREEMENT THEY SIGNED A YEAR AGO WITH THE PRESIDENT RODRIGO BORJA GOVERNMENT. THE ACCORD MADE IT POSSIBLE FOR THEM TO CEASE THE ARMED STRUGGLE IN EXCHANGE FOR A GOVERNMENT DIALOGUE WITH SOCIAL SECTORS IN THE COUNTRY. PRIOR TO THE BEGINNING OF THE FOURTH AVC NATIONAL CONFERENCE, AVC LEADER SANTIAGO DILLMAN REPORTED ON 18 MAY THAT THE FINAL DECISION ON THE SURRENDERING OF WEAPONS WAS A LOGICAL STEP -- AFTER TAKING INTO CONSIDERATION THAT THE ARMED STRUGGLE IN ECUADOR AND IN THE REST OF LATIN AMERICA IS NO LONGER THE PROPER COURSE. THEREFORE, HE ANNOUNCED, THIS ALFARIST MEETING WILL ALSO ANALYZE THE DECISION TO ORGANIZE A NEW POLITICAL PARTY OR TO ALLOW AVC LEADERS TO JOIN AN ALREADY EXISTING GROUP RECOGNIZED BY THE SUPREME ELECTORAL TRIBUNAL.

THESE ARE SOME OF THE POINTS ON THE AGENDA OF THE AVC MEETING, WHICH IS EXPECTED TO CONCLUDE ON 21 OR 22 MAY WITH A HISTORICAL RESOLUTION. HOWEVER, AVC LEADERS -- AMONG THEM SANTIAGO DILLMAN, MARCO TROYA, PEDRO MONCADA, AND JANETH SOSA -- HAVE PREFERRED NOT TO DISCLOSE THE SITE OF THE MEETING, WHICH HAS FRUSTRATED THE WORK OF JOURNALISTS. THE AVC LEADERS PLAN TO DISCUSS THE POSSIBILITY OF DELIVERING WEAPONS IN THE HANDS OF AVC MEMBERS TO A SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL DELEGATION IN A CEREMONY SIMILAR TO ONE RECENTLY HELD BY THE 19-APRIL MOVEMENT IN COLOMBIA, WHICH IN THE PAST HAS STAGED SEVERAL WELL-KNOWN MILITARY ACTIONS, INCLUDING THE KIDNAPPING OF BUSINESSMAN NAIM ISAIAS WITH THE HELP OF THE AVC.

THE AVC HAS SAID IT WANTS TO PARTICIPATE IN THE COUNTRY'S INSTITUTIONAL LIFE. IN ORDER TO DO THIS, IT WILL PLEDGE TO SURRENDER ITS WEAPONS -- THE SYMBOL OF ITS REBELLION -- WHICH IT WILL CONTINUE WITH OR WITHOUT WEAPONS, AVC LEADERS HAVE SAID. THE AVC LEADERS CONTINUE MEETING AT AN UNKNOWN LOCATION IN GUAYAQUIL AND EXPECT TO REACH AN AGREEMENT SOON ON LAYING DOWN THEIR WEAPONS, WHICH WOULD THEN BE DESTROYED IMMEDIATELY.